<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The absolute necessity of spiritual husbandry in breaking up our fallow ground. Together with a discourse of the terrible coming of Christ, to execute vengeance on all that remain fallow ground, and obey not the gospel. By Samuel Tomlyns, M.A. and minister of the gospel in Marlborough.</title>
            <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831187</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831187</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35650</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35650)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2115:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The absolute necessity of spiritual husbandry in breaking up our fallow ground. Together with a discourse of the terrible coming of Christ, to execute vengeance on all that remain fallow ground, and obey not the gospel. By Samuel Tomlyns, M.A. and minister of the gospel in Marlborough.</title>
                  <author>Tomlyns, Samuel, 1632 or 3-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 155, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst, at the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheap-side, near Mercers-Chapel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Copy is stained, also with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 2nd, I, 7-8 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ABSOLUTE NECESSITY OF <hi>Spiritual Husbandry,</hi> In breaking up our FALLOW GROUND.</p>
            <p>Together with a DISCOURSE Of the Terrible Coming of CHRIST, To Execute Vengeance on all that remain <hi>Fallow Ground,</hi> and Obey not the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL TOMLYNS,</hi> M.A. and Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Marlborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheap-ſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chapel.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:3"/>
            <head>TO Richard Wollaſton, <hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace, be multiplied, from God our Father, and from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>A Spiritual Lethargy is the reigning Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of this Age: The Deſign of theſe Diſcourſes is, to Alarm the Secure, to Awaken the Sleeping World. Tho' Chriſt hath been a great while Inviſible, yet he will Appear to the Confuſion and Terror of his Adverſaries. Tho' he hath long kept Silence, yet he will roar out of <hi>Zion.</hi> Tho' his Sword hath ſlept, yet it will awake; do Execution on, and be Bathed in the Blood of Impenitent Sinners. The Sins of Men, and the puniſhing Hand of Chriſt, will find out all his Enemies, <hi>Numb. 32.23. Pſal. 21.8.</hi> He that came at firſt to ſaſe Men from their Sins, yet being ſlighted, and rejected, will come a ſecond time to deſtroy Men for their Iniquities. They that have not prized a Day of Salvation, ſhall Experience, and feel a Day of Vengeance and Deſtruction. How woful will the Eſtate of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be, when their own Accuſing Conſciences ſhall be as <hi>a fiery Oven,</hi> Pſal. <hi>21.9.</hi> within, and the Vengeance of God be as a Furnace of Fire
<pb facs="tcp:35650:4"/>without; and Sinners ſhall be Supported (though but Tares and Chaff) to be Eternal Fuel to this Fire. It will be ſweet to have a <hi>Well of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Water ſpringing up within,</hi> John <hi>4.14.</hi> but it will be dreadful to have a Well of Fire to be burning in his Soul. <hi>Alvarez de Semedo,</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>China,</hi> ſpeaks of ſuch Wells of Fire, kindled from Sulphurous Matter, that burn and flame continually. The corruption of the Soul al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed will breed that Worm that never dies. I ſhall Rejoyce if the ſaid Diſcourſes do ſtir up Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to eſcape the Corruption that is in the World through Luſt, and to flee from the Wrath to come. I have a due Reſpect to you, for appearing for <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in your Station, that they might not be over-preſſed with Burdens. I ſhall be glad, if what I have written, may contribute to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of your Salvation, and ſtir you up to prepare to meet the Lord of Glory, and to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judge of the whole World, whoſe Eye, Book, and Balance, will be dreadful to hardened Sinners at laſt. But that Chriſt may appear as a Redeemer, to perfect your Liberty, and as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom to marry your Soul, is the earneſt deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Sincere, and Affectionate Friend, and Servant,</hi> Samuel Tomlyns.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35650:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Theſ. 1.7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And to you who are troubled, reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels,</p>
                  <p>In flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN theſe two Verſes, there are ſeveral weighty Truths, 1. A Benefit that will be beſtowed on Suffering Chriſtians, God will render Reſt to thoſe that are Troubled. And <hi>Paul</hi> applies this ſweet Truth to himſelf; he puts in for a ſhare, and claims an Intereſt in it, Reſt with us. 2. We have the Time when this Benefit
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35650:5"/>ſhall be beſtowed; it is when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed from Heaven. The full Deliverance of the Oppreſſed Saints, is Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended till the Revelation of Chriſt; he ſhall then do Right to the Oppreſſed, and execute Vengeance on the Oppreſſors: It is but reaſonable, that the Reſt of the Members ſhould depend on the Reſt of their Head, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.3, 4. Chriſt is now deſired <hi>to gird his Sword on his Thigh, and to ride proſperouſly on the word of Truth and Righteouſneſs.</hi> And Chriſt is ſet forth by <hi>one riding on a white Horſe, with a Bow in his Hand, and he went forth Conquering, and to Conquer.</hi> The Church is compared to the Horſes in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Chariot, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.9. becauſe by her Miniſters ſhe draws the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Victorious Chariot of Chriſt through the World. Though Chriſt hath a Reſt, as to his Perſon, in Heaven, and is above the reach and rage of his Enemies, yet he is contending with, and fighting againſt his Enemies: He is winning the Hearts of his Elect, and gathering them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Kingdom; and he is breaking his Enemies to pieces, and putting them under his Feet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25, 26. but at laſt Chriſt will perfect, and finiſh his Work. He will appear as a Glorious and Triumphant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, as one that hath won the Field, and gained the Day: He will ſit on the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35650:5"/>Throne of his Glory, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.31. This implies a perfect Reſt; he ſhall fight, and make War no more, his People ſhall enter into his Palace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14, 15. and ſit down with him in his Throne, <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. and his Enemies ſhall be adjudged to Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting Fire, and be ſhut up in an Eternal Priſon. 3. We have the Company that ſhall wait on Chriſt at his Appearing; he ſhall come with his mighty Angels. 4. We have the terrible manner of his Appearance, it ſhall be in flaming Fire. Chriſt is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Holy and Righteous; he can appear in flaming Fire, yet not be hurt by it, or ſuffer any thing from it. This Fire will be hurtful to Chriſt's Enemies, but harmleſs to himſelf. He that appeared at firſt as the Day ſpring from on high, comfortably to direct ſtraying Souls into the way of Peace: He that ariſes to thoſe, that fear God's Name, as a <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs, with healing under his wings,</hi> Mal. 4.2. will now be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in flaming Fire, to puniſh obſtinate Rebels. They that have refuſed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected Chriſt as a <hi>refining fire,</hi> Mal. 3.2, 3. ſhall now, to their coſt, feel him to be a <hi>conſuming fire.</hi> He that once appeared in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with beams of Love, ſhall now a ſecond time appear ſurrounded with flames of Wrath. 5. We have the end of Chriſt's Revelation, or why he will appear; it is to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35650:6"/>render Vengeance. It is in the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, giving Vengeance. O how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and terrible a Gift is this! He that is God's Almoner, to diſtribute God's Alms of Mercy to poor penitent begging Sinners, will have no other Gift to beſtow on impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and unbelieving Souls, but Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. <hi>It is ſaid vengeance belongeth to me, and I will recompence,</hi> Heb. 10.30. Though to the Penitents and Believing, it is ſaid, <hi>To the Lord belongeth Mercy,</hi> yet, as to obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Sinners, <hi>Vengeance belongs to God.</hi> Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment is a juſt Debt belonging to the Wicked, therefore it is ſaid that God will repay Fury to his Adverſaries, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 59.18. he will render his Anger with Fury, and his Rebukes with Flames of Fire, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 66.15. <hi>Paul</hi> charges Chriſtians to render to all their one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. ſo Chriſt will render to hardened Sinners their due. Sinners owe God glory, to be raiſed out of their Miſery and Eternal Torments: They will ſtill be making Reſtitution, yet never will be able to make Satisfaction to God: they will to Eternity be in debt to God, there will ſtill be an Arrear of Wrath, a Debt of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance due to them; and this Vengeance will come immediately from God and Chriſt. From God's angry frowning Face, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. from his puniſhing Hand, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31. his angry breath will blow up the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35650:6"/>Fire that ſhall torment them, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30: laſt. The weighty Feet of Chriſt, as fine Braſs, will bruiſe and cruſh Sinners as Grapes of Galls, as bitter Cluſters, when he ſhall tread the Wine-Preſs of the Fierceneſs and Wrath of Almighty God, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.15. 6. On whom ſhall this Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance be Executed? It is <hi>on thoſe</hi> that know not God, <hi>and obey</hi> not <hi>the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus.</hi> This is an extenſive compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Vengeance, it will reach the whole corrupt and unregenerate World. It is ſaid that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> knew not God, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.5. and there are too many in the Viſible Church that do hate Knowledge, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29. and that through deceit, do refuſe to know God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.6. leſt Light ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Deformity, awaken their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, diſturb their Carnal Peace, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and imbitter their Senſual Pleaſures, and Carnal Delights; therefore Chriſt Taxes and Cenſures the whole Unconverted World as guilty of Ignorance, <hi>O Righteous Father, the World hath not known thee,</hi> John 17.25. Thoſe that obey not the Goſpel, ſhall be the Objects of Chriſt's Wrath, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his Vengeance, where the Light of the Goſpel hath ſhined, where the Hands of Wiſdom have been ſtretched out; where Men have been beſeeched to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to God, have been wooed to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35650:7"/>Eſpouſed to Chriſt, but yet have cloſed their Eyes againſt the Light, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.15. and have ſtopped their Ears againſt the Call of the great Shepherd, and the Voice of the Bleſſed Bridegroom; theſe ſhall have the heavieſt Puniſhment, and the hotteſt Hell.</p>
            <div n="1" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doctrine 1. <hi>The Perſecuted People of God ſhall have Reſt at the Revelation of Chriſt.</hi> Iſaiah 14.3. <hi>The Lord ſhall give thee Rest from thy Sorrow, from thy Fear, and from the hard Bondage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou wast made to ſerve.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Saints ſhall have a Reſt, 1. From their Enemies; they ſhall no more tread on their Necks, or ride over their Backs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.12. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 51.23. Enemies have proudly ſaid, <hi>Bow down, that we may go over,</hi> and the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Saints have been laid as the Ground, and as the Street, to them that went over.</hi> The way that Enemies have choſen is over the Necks and Backs of the Saints; but it is ſaid to the People of God, The Lord hath taken away thy Judgments, he hath caſt out thine Enemy; thou ſhalt not ſee evil any more; the Plowers ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Plow on the Backs of the Righteous; the Rod of the Wicked ſhall not reſt on their Lot, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3. they ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35650:7"/>reach out the Cup of their Fury to Saints, becauſe they will not ſtain their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, defile and inſlave their Conſciences to their Luſts.</p>
               <p>Two things evidence that Saints ſhall have Reſt from their Enemies and Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Enemies ſhall be Conquered and totally Subdued: Thoſe that fear God's Name ſhall go forth and tread down the wicked, <hi>they ſhall be as Aſhes under the Soles of their Feet,</hi> Mal. 4.2, 3. And the God of Peace will bruiſe Satan under the Feet of Believers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. ſo that Satan, and wicked Men, ſhall be totally vanquiſhed and diſabled from hurting and offending the Saints, they ſhall be ſhut up in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and burn in the Furnace. The 92 <hi>Pſalm</hi> hath this Title, <hi>A Pſalm for the Sabbath day;</hi> in it the Pſalmiſt affirms, That the wicked ſhall be deſtroyed; and that the Enemies of God ſhall periſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92. 7, 9. This is a proper Meditation for the Sabbath day; God, and Saints too, will not have a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, perfect, and delightful Sabbath, till all the Workers of Iniquity are Conquered and Deſtroyed.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35650:8"/> 2. The Saints will be perfected in Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in the Life of God; ſo that they will not need afflictions any more. Where there is no Droſs, there needs no Refining Fire: Where there is no Folly, there is no Rod of Correction neceſſary; they do not need the Flail, nor the Fan, who are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly winnowed from their Chaff. They that are fully freed from Sin, ſhall be no more liable to Death, Pain, Sorrow, or Crying, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.4. the corrupt Root that bears all theſe Evils is withered and dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saints ſhall Reſt from their Labour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. Though the Son of Man give the Spiritual Bread, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. yet we are bid to Labour for it. It is hard to perſwade our ſelves of the Excellency and Neceſſity of this Bread, and that the Son of Man can, and will, give it to Creatures ſo vile, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and provoking, is a very difficult, hard, laborious thing; we need to wreſtle with God, and cry out, <hi>Lord, help our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief,</hi> Mark 9.24. evidence Spiritual, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Things to us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Saints ſhall Reſt from their Spiritual Journies and Travels. <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Sons took long Journies into <hi>Egypt</hi> to buy Corn, to procure Bread, but when <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Family re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved into <hi>Egypt,</hi> they ceaſed from ſuch
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35650:8"/>Journies; they were then at the very Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries of Corn. <hi>Joſeph</hi> there nouriſhed his Father, his Brethren, and their Houſholds, with Bread, without Travelling, or Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it; ſo Saints ſhall have acceſs to, and ſatisfaction, by eating of the Fruits of the Tree of Life, that ſhall ſtill be ripe, and ready to be enjoyed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Saints ſhall have Reſt by their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from all Evils, Sufferings, Enemies, Labours and Travels, ſo they ſhall reſt in the enjoyment of the higheſt, and beſt Good.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They ſhall reſt by the Fountain of Life, where they may be ſatisfied, and drink their fill as Caravans, or great Companies of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants do, Travel through dry Deſerts and Wilderneſſes, till they come to a Spring, and then, and there, they pitch their Tents, and refreſh themſelves by drinking of the Spring; ſo we muſt paſs on through Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures dry and barren, till we come to God the Fountain of Life. Here we muſt ſtop and delight our ſelves in him, and with him. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. <hi>With thee is the Fountain of Life, in thy Light we ſhall ſee Light;</hi> that is, the Light of Joy and Conſolation. <hi>The Lamb ſhall lead his Sheep to living Fountains of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Rev. 7.17 as if every Saint had a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35650:9"/>to himſelf, and did enjoy God as fully, as if he did ſolely, and only enjoy him: How ſweet is it to reſt by the Fountain of Life for ever?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saints ſhall reſt in the Houſe of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a Husband; in the Houſe of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>In my Fathers Houſe are many Manſions; I go to prepare a place for you,</hi> John 14.2. and ſo they that reſt in the Houſe of their Heavenly Husband. <hi>Naomi</hi> did pray her Daughters-in-Law might find reſt, each of them in the Houſe of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Saints ſhall reſt at the Table of Chriſt, they ſhall ſit, eat, and drink with him, at his Table, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. in his Kingdom. There is no Good abſent at this Feaſt, to cauſe a wandring of deſire; no Evil preſent to cauſe ſighs and ſorrow under it: Here Saints may eat, and be ſatisfied for ever.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This will be a moſt Honorable Reſt; Saints that ſit in the Throne with Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. and reign in life for evermore. As <hi>all Tears ſhall be wiped from their Eyes,</hi> ſo Crowns ſhall be ſet on their Heads, a Crown of Life and Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. This is the higheſt Honour that Creatures can aſpire to, and therefore may be fully ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35650:9"/>with, and reſt in it. This Honour ſhall never be forfeited, neither ſhall this Feaſt be diſturbed and interrupted.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Saints, that now are troubled, ſhall reſt with the beſt Company, they ſhall be where Chriſt is, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. and <hi>they ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>in the Kingdom of God,</hi> Matth. 8.11. As they have been Companions with other Suffering Saints, in the Kingdom, and patience of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9. ſo they ſhall enter into the ſame Joy, poſſeſs the ſame Inheritance, and partake of the ſame Feaſt with them. If Servants ſhall be where their Lord is, <hi>John</hi> 12.26. much more may they be aſſured of reſt and refreſhment with their Fellow Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. Though they be more eminent than they, for Gifts, Graces, and Services, yet they ſhall reſt in the ſame Boſom of Love, and ſit in the ſame Throne of Glory. What harmonious Melody, what ſweet Comfort will there be, when all Suffering Saints ſhall be gathered together, to ſing the Praiſes of their Father, to celebrate the Honour of the their Redeemer, and be ſwallowed up for ever in the love of the Father, Son, and Spirit?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>USE of the Doctrine.</hi> If Troubled Saints ſhall have reſt, then be not afraid of, do not ſtart or recoil from the Croſs of Chriſt, it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35650:10"/>will end, and iſſue in a Crown of Glory. Your Sufferings are light, your Glory will be weighty; your Afflictions and Sorrows will be momentary, but your Joys will be everlaſting, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17. Do not buy the Worlds Peace with the Trouble and Terror of your Conſciences: Some Apoſtate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>France</hi> had ſuch burdened Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, ſuch wounded Spirits, grew ſo weary of Life, that they came and offered themſelves to their Antichriſtian Enemies, and deſired that they would kill them. Do not ſlaviſhly dread Sufferings for Chriſt, did not your Lord endure greater Troubles for you? <hi>John</hi> 12.27, 28. Now, ſaith Chriſt, is my Soul troubled; he made his Soul an Offering for Sin, he poured out his Soul to the death, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.10, 12. You are but in ſhallow waters of afflictions, but Jeſus Chriſt was in a deep Sea of Sorrows: You have but ſome ſmall drops that ſprinkle you, but he had a dreadful Storm that fell on him. You have but ſome ſparks that fly on you, but the Lamb of God was roaſted by the Fire of his Fathers Anger. Do not think it ſtrange if ſiery Trials ſhould be kindled againſt you, and break out on you, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. Do not think to be Priviledged from Troubles, and to be Exempted from Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips on Earth, and yet be ſecured from Pains and Torments in another World. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:35650:10"/>will roar, and wicked Men will rage againſt you. <hi>In the World you ſhall have Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, but in Chriſt you ſhall have peace,</hi> John 16.33. Though wicked Men do ſcorch your Bodies, yet your Souls do ſit under Chriſts cold ſhadow, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And you ſhall have times of refreſhing from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> Acts 3.19. Though you are appointed to Afflictions, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3. yet God hath not appointed you to wrath, but to obtain Salvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9. You are now clouded with Sorrows and Reproaches, but you ſhall ſhine out in the Kingdom of your Father, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.43. Your ſmoaking Furnace will iſſue in a burning Lamp, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.17. your ſighs will be ſucceeded by Songs, your darkneſs and ſhadow of Death will end in a bright and glorious Morning. Perſecutors will be caſt into Priſon, and the Perſecuted taken into the Palace. Enemies ſhall ſeel cruel Bondage, and Saints be Tranſlated into glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Liberty. Wicked Men now Revile and Reproach the People of God, but the Time is at hand when <hi>Chriſt will laugh at their Calamity, and mock when their Fear co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,</hi> Prov. 1.26. but Saints ſhall have praiſe from Chriſt, enter into the joy of their Lord, and enjoy a reſt that will abundantly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence all their Troubles.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35650:11"/> 2. When ſhall this reſt be enjoyed? It is ſaid, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed; Two things are here affirmed, 1. That the Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed. 2. That he ſhall be Revealed from Heaven. The words give this Doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="doctrine">
               <head>Doct. 2. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed from Heaven.</hi> 1. <hi>The Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed.</hi> 2. <hi>He ſhall be Revealed from Heaven.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The Lord Jeſus ſhall be Revealed: This is neceſſary on a double Account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Jeſus Chriſt was veiled and clouded in the World; the Sun of Righteouſneſs was in a continual Eclipſe for about 33 Years. Tho' he was Rich, yet for our ſakes he became Poor, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 9. Tho' he was full, yet he emptied himſelf, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7, 8. Tho' he was Lord over all, God over all, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. yet he took on him the form of a Servant; and this was as a thick Veil caſt over all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. The World ſaw no beauty in him, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53.2. He was a Man of ſorrows, and acquainted with grief, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.6. He was trod on as a Worm, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 10.9.23. and toſſed up and down as a Locuſt by the Wind of his Adverſaries fury. From the Garden he was offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to <hi>Annas,</hi> from <hi>Annas</hi> to <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35650:11"/>
                  <hi>Caiaphas</hi> to <hi>Pilate,</hi> from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>Herod,</hi> from <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>Pilate</hi> again, then to <hi>Golgotha.</hi> Thus the Scripture was fulfilled, That he was toſſed up and down as a Locuſt: So mean was his Condition, and ſo low his Circumſtances, that the World did not know him, <hi>John</hi> 3.1. and therefore a glorious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of his is neceſſary, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. to let all the World know who, and what he is, and how they have been miſtaken.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Jeſus removed, and withdrew himſelf from the World; he is Travelled into a far Country, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.12. He is gone within the Veil, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.19, 20. He is hid with God, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. Thouſands do love him tho' they have not ſeen him; and believe on him, tho' they do not yet ſee him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. The Object of our Faith is become inviſible, and far removed from the Eye of Senſe; and Chriſt doth ſtay ſo long, that Wiſe and Fooliſh Virgins do fall aſleep, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.5. And his Rebellious Citizens ſend a Meſſage after him, ſaying, <hi>We will not have this Man to reign over us,</hi> Luke 19.14. All thoſe they cruelly perſecuted, and wickedly ſlew, for Proclaiming Chriſt as King, and calling them to bow down to his Royal Scepter, were ſent in this Embaſſy, or with this Meſſage, after Chriſt, to tell him his Citizens, the <hi>Jews,</hi> would not admit him as their King to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35650:12"/>Reign over them; and the Prophane and Atheiſtical World do ridicule, mock and ſcorn, at the Promiſe of his coming, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. They that walk after their own Luſts, and place their Happineſs in ſatisfying of them, would not have Chriſt come to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt their Life of Senſuality, or to puniſh them for it. They would never have Chriſt come, and hope he will not appear; and therefore, with inſulting Belief, ſay, Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</p>
               <p>In the Proſecution of this Subject, I ſhall inſiſt on theſe three Things. 1. I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that the Lord Jeſus will be Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2. What the Scripture aſſerts about his coming. 3. When the Lord Jeſus will be Revealed. Tho' we cannot point out the particular Time, yet there are ſome general Intimations given us in Scripture when he will come.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Lord Jeſus will come,</hi> 1. God the Father will ſend him, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, That God would ſend Jeſus, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was preached to them. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the appearing of Chriſt, he affirms, that in his Times, he ſhall ſhew this Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, who is the bleſſed and only Potentate. The Father will exhibit Chriſt again to the World; this will be the moſt wonderful
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35650:12"/>glorious ſhew that ever was preſented to Mankind: He that did ſtand as a Criminal before the Tribunal of <hi>Pilate, Matt.</hi> 27.11. he that did hang on a Croſs of Ignominy, ſhall now ſit on a Throne of Glory, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.31. He will Arraign Men for all the Acts of Time, and adjudge them to the Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Rewards of Eternity. All Nations ſhall be gathered before him, ſhall receive their Sentence from him, and be diſpoſed of either to a Bleſſed or Miſerable Eternity by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath told us of his Return; he compares himſelf to a Noble Man Travelling into a far Country to receive a Kingdom, and return. As the Spirits of Men do return to God to be judged, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.7.3. ſo Chriſt will return again to judge the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Saints live in expectation of Chriſts return; they wait for Jeſus Chriſt from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. They look for him from Heaven, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. They look <hi>for the bleſſed Hope, and the glorious Appearing of the great God, and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Tit. 2.14. Tho' the moſt of Men live, as if they had no Concern in Chriſt's Appearing, as if it would be no Marriage-Day, Feaſt-Day, or Harveſt-Day to them; as if they did not think, or expect to reap any Harveſt of Bleſſedneſs, or to receive any Reward of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35650:13"/>Happineſs at Chriſt's coming, yet it would be a great diſappointment to the People of God if he ſhould not return. They look for him as a <hi>Bridegroom,</hi> as a <hi>Saviour,</hi> as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer;</hi> and he will appear a <hi>ſecond time unto Salvation, to thoſe that look for him,</hi> Heb. 9.28.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Angels have teſtified to this Truth, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould come from Heaven, as the Apoſtles ſaw him go to Heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. And the Angels cannot be falſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Deceivers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Jeſus Chriſt hath work to do at his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming: He hath a Harveſt to reap, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.30. A Floor to Purge, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.12. A Wife to Marry, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.25. Servants to reckon with, <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.21, 30. The Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and Faithful he will commend, and call to enter into his own joy; and the Idle and Slothful he will adjudge to be caſt into outer Darkneſs. The great Shepherd will gather his Flock to him, and lead them to ſweet and delicious Paſtures in the Heavenly Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let us obſerve what the Scripture aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts concerning his coming.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Jeſus Chriſt teſtifies, that he comes quickly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Behold I come quickly. Yet a little while, and he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry,</hi> Heb. 10.37. It is but a little time to the day of Chriſt's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35650:13"/>compared with the time that is run out, ſince the beginning of the World, it will be quickly, conſidering how near our end is, and that Death is at hand. Death is the end of the World to us; we paſs into a fixed, unchangeable, Eternal Eſtate, as thoſe do who live to the end of the World. Time is folded up to us, and the Door of Eternity is opened to us. Chriſt's coming to call us out of the World, and to Summon us to his Judgment Seat, may quickly be; it may be within a few Years, yea, within a few Months, yea, within a few Days. That which is future will come, and be preſent; and our Souls ſhould be affected now, as if we ſaw the Judge appearing, the Throne ſet, the Books opened, and our ſelves Preſented before the Judgment-Seat of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt will be ſudden, ſurprizing, and very amazing to the greateſt part of the World, as the Old World was, drowned in Senſual Pleaſures, Earthly Buſineſs, Carnal Security. They were poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with, and hardened in unbelief; they did not look for the Flood, they <hi>knew not till it came and took them all away,</hi> Matt. 24.39. They did not believe God's threatning, or regard <hi>Noah</hi>'s preaching and warnings, or conſider what the building of the Ark did mean; they would not know things by Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35650:14"/>but only by Seeing and Feeling. They did not know till the Rain did fall, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the great Deep were broken up, and the Waters did riſe to ſwallow them up; ſo <hi>ſhall the coming of the Son of Man be,</hi> Rev. 16.15. The World will not believe, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for it, till they ſee Chriſt coming in the Clouds; he will as to moſt, <hi>come as a Thief in the Night,</hi> that is not thought of, or look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3. The World is as looſe, as careleſs, as ſecure, as if they had heard no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Chriſt's coming, as if they had not been informed of his appearing, or been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to look and wait for it, and been warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to prepare for it; the evil Servant faith no more, <hi>but my Lord delayeth his coming,</hi> Matt. 24.48. Tho' yet he acts, and carries it, as if he would never come at all, Chriſt's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing will come as a Snare on them that dwell on the Earth, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.35. Tho' they have often been taught, and told, that Jeſus Chriſt will come, yet they will be as ſtupid, and ſenſeleſs, and fooliſh, as the Birds and Beaſts; they will take no warning, but will fall into the Snare, as a Bird doth, and be utterly ruined and deſtroyed by Chriſt's ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming. Tho' Chriſt doth bring Grace, and Glory to others, yet he will totally take away all Good, all that is ſweet and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, from impenitent Sinners. Men are wofully degenerate, that they will not know
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35650:14"/>things by Faith, or the Teſtimony of the Word of God, but only by Senſe, and ſo will not diſcern dreadful Evils till they fall upon them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt will be Revealed in great Glory, and <hi>ſit upon the Throne of his Glory,</hi> Matt. 25.31. He will alſo cauſe his Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to appear in glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. Our Saviour comes not only to be glorified himſelf, <hi>but to be glorified in his Saints, and to be admired in all them that believe,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.10. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſtiled, <hi>The glorius Appearing</hi> of the <hi>great God,</hi> even of <hi>our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Titus 2.13. Chriſt at his coming will be clothed with ſuch glory, that will put it out of doubt that he is the Son of God, that he is the Son of Man, the true Meſſiah that was promiſed and exhibited to the World: It is ſaid, <hi>Then ſhall appear the Sign of the Son of Man,</hi> Matt. 24.30. <hi>Ferus</hi> takes this Sign of the Son of Man to be the Sign of the Croſs, but the Note of <hi>Calvin</hi> on the Text is more ſolid and judicious. He takes that eminent and tranſcendent Glory, that Chriſt will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in, to be the Sign of the Son of Man. Thoſe that were not convinced, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by all the Signs and Miracles that Chriſt wrought, that he was the Meſſiah, ſhall, by his glorious Appearing, by his Illuſtrious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as a demonſtrative, and convincing Sign, be aſſured fully, that he is the Son of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35650:15"/>Man, the Promiſed Meſſiah: None ſhall doubt, none ſhall be left at uncertainties about it, no Unbeliever ſhall remain. Tho' the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> would not regard Chriſt's Miracles, or be induced by them to believe, yet he tells them of an invincible convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing evidence, that ſhould one day be afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, but too late. He inſiſts on, and minds them of this very ſign of the Son of Man, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.64. <hi>Hereafter you ſhall ſee the Son of man ſitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of Heaven.</hi> You that now condemn me, for ſaying that I am the Meſſiah, and the Son of God, ſhall one day ſee me as a Judge, coming to Arraign, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and Condemn you.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The coming of Chriſt will be very open, and evident to the whole World.</hi> When he firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, he ſhewed himſelf to few but to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation. After his Reſurrection, we read of none of the unbelieving World that beheld him. He appeared only to, and was ſeen by none, but by his Diſciples, who were to inform the World of this truth, that he was raiſed. The unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> were not to ſee Chriſt's raiſed, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Body, but to believe his Reſurrection; but Chriſt will ſo openly at laſt appear, <hi>that every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> Rev. 1.7. They alſo that pierced him ſhall behold him; <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Heathens</hi> and <hi>Mahumetans, Looſe</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35650:15"/>
                  <hi>Prophane Chriſtians,</hi> ſhall ſee him. Believers and Saints ſhall then point him out with joy, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him,</hi> Iſ. 25.9. <hi>And he hath not deceived our Faith, or frustrated our Hope and Expectation.</hi> They that would not believe what they did not ſee, ſhall now ſee, but to their terror. They that were averſe from the Life of Faith, and wholly devoted to the Life of Senſe, ſhall now have Seeing enough; they ſhall behold what will affright, diſmay, and overwhelm them. God doth now require, and call for a high and noble Exerciſe of Faith, in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to inviſible things (at which the Heathen of Old ſcoffed); yet he doth, and will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend, to give evidence and ſatisfaction, as at Chriſt's firſt appearing, he was viſible to the eye of the Body, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.9. O Zion, <hi>that bringeſt glad tidings, lift up thy voice,</hi> and <hi>be not afraid; ſay unto the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold your God.</hi> This was a ſtrange and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful truth, and <hi>Zion</hi> might be afraid to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it; yet ſhe is twice bid to lift up her voice, and that with ſtrength, not to be afraid aloud to ſound out, and proclaim this amazing, and aſtoniſhing truth: Say to the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> Behold your God, behold God is come down to you in a Humane Nature, God is walking among you in a Body of Fleſh, preaching, working Miracles, familiarly converſing with you. <hi>The Word was made fleſh, and dwelt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35650:16"/>among us, and we beheld his Glory,</hi> John 1.14. So at his ſecond coming, Chriſt will be evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the eye, and, as it were, pointed out by the Finger of Men: <hi>Behold he cometh in the clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him,</hi> Rev. 1.7. Saints ſhall ſay to thoſe that have upbraided them with the inviſible object of their Faith, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him,</hi> Iſ. 25.9. Tho' the unbelieving World did Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach Chriſtians, and ſay, <hi>Where is your God,</hi> yet Saints one day conſute all their Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and ſilence all their Inſultings and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braidings; they ſhall point out Chriſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in all his Majeſty and Glory, and ſay, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him, and he will ſave us,</hi> and <hi>we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation,</hi> Iſ. 25.9.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Revelation of Chriſt will cauſe Mourning to the greateſt part of the World; it will be a black, bitter, terrible day to moſt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.30. All the Tribes of the Earth ſhall mourn, all the Kindreds of the Earth ſhall wail becauſe of him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. when they ſhall ſee the Son of Man coming in the Clouds of Heaven, with power and great glory. They ſhall mourn when it is too late to repent; they ſhall wail when their ſorrow will not prevent, but begin their Puniſhment and Hell. Now they ſhall, to their coſt, know how great a Perſon they have refuſed, and how high an Happineſs they have rejected; that they have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35650:16"/>turned from a <hi>Saviour,</hi> and ſo forfeited true Bleſſedneſs; and rebelled againſt the great God, and ſo have incurred the <hi>worſt</hi> and <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> penalties. Theſe three things ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viewed and reflected on, 1. What they have done. 2. What they have loſt. 3. What they muſt ſuffer and endure to Eternity, when they ſhall bleed by the edge of God's Sword, and ſmart under the Chaſtiſement of the Scorpions of Revenging Juſtice, 1. Sinners that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what they have done, that they have turned away from him that ſpake out of the boſom of his Fathers love, and from the Throne of his own glory, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81.11. That they would have none of him who is the true God, and eternal Life; that they ſtopped their Ears, and hardned their Hearts againſt the wooings of the beſt Bridegroom, againſt the call of the great Shepherd, and of the Captain of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt the intreaties of a Saviour and Redeemer. They will now reflect on the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent denials they gave to, and the many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts they put upon the Lord of Glory; how they hated and abhorred his Yoke, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and loathed his Feaſt; did not ſubmit to, and come into his Righteouſneſs, but rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, reſiſted, vexed, and quenched the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God. 2. They ſhall know now what they have loſt; that the Treaſury of Grace will now be locked, the Fountain of Life ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the bowels of Chriſt will be for ever ſhut
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35650:17"/>againſt them, notwithſtanding their extream poverty and miſery. The door of God's Houſe will be ſhut, never to be opened again: How woful will this be, to be excluded out of God's Palace, and to be thruſt out of his Kingdom? They that ſhould have uſed violence to preſs into God's Kingdom, but now Chriſt will uſe force to thruſt them out of his Kingdom. They wiſh now to ſee the excellency and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kingdom of God, that they would even, with violence, force into it, but they ſhall be violently thruſt out of it, they ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taſt of Chriſt's Supper. They would not come into Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and this was their great ſin; and they ſhall not come into Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and this will be their grievous puniſhment. They ſhall not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into God's reſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.18. They ſhall not partake of Chriſt's joy or glory: They would not open their Hearts to Chriſt, and Chriſt will not open his Heaven to them. They would not know Chriſt's voice, when he knocked and called, ſaying, <hi>Open to me:</hi> And Chriſt will not hear their voice, when they cry, <hi>Lord, open to us.</hi> They would not give entertainment and reſt to Chriſt in their Souls, and Chriſt will not give them enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment and reſt in his Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This will cauſe wailing, when Sinners ſee what they muſt ſuffer and endure; they that in their whole <hi>time did drink iniquity like
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35650:17"/>water,</hi> muſt, during God's eternity, drink the wrath of the Almighty, <hi>Job</hi> 21.20. They muſt be drunk with the Cup of God's fury, feel the edge of his glittering Sword, and the weight of his puniſhing hand. His face will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiled to frown and ſcorch, and his arm be made bare to ſmite and wound. Chriſt will come to expreſs his moſt fierce reſentments of Sinners ſlighting the Grace offered to 'em, and deſpiſing the mercy preſſed on them. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Diſobedience ſhall be broken with Chriſt's Iron rod, and Veſſels of wrath ſhall be filled up to the brim with the fury of God. This Mourning will be dreadful, becauſe there is no comfort to be adminiſtred; no peace to be ſpoken to theſe Mourners. There will be no baniſhing of their fears, removing of their burdens, no ſweetning of their cup, or healing of their wounds, for ever. God will ſet his face againſt them, and will never hide, or turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his angry countenance from them. Thoſe that have been ſecure, ſtupid, hard-hearted, even till now, ſhall then begin to mourn, but the firſt fruits of their ſorrow will be the firſt fruits of their woe, and prove the earneſt, and preſages of their eternal miſery. They begin to ſorrow on the utmoſt confines and bounds of Time, and muſt continue ſorrowing to an endleſs and unbounded Eternity. Godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin may ſomewhat avail to remove the Tranſgreſſor's burden; but Worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35650:18"/>under the feeling of preſent anguiſh, or the fear of further, future, approaching miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, will not advantage Sinners to roul away their guilt, to prevent or diminiſh their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their mourning is a part of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.11, 12. <hi>and thou mourn at laſt, and ſay, How have I hated inſtruction, and my heart deſpiſed reproof?</hi> Therefore this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall never ceaſe, ſhall never be taken off. Saints have but days of mourning, and theſe ſhall have an end, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 60.20. but Sinners ſhall have an eternal mourning, which ſhall have no end. The day of Chriſt's Revelation will be a time of joy to his Loyal Spouſe, to his Living Members, to his Faithful and Sincere Servants; when he appeareth, they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with exceeding great joy, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.13. But this appearing will cauſe eternal ſorrow to Rebels and Enemies, when their ſins ſhall be remembred and revenged.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When will the Lord Jeſus be Revealed? Tho' the end of the Old World, and the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual time of its deſtruction was foretold, that after a hundred and twenty Years the Flood ſhould come, yet the exact day or time of the end of the ſecond World none knows, no not the Angels of God, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.36. yet the Scripture gives us ſome general hints, and intimations, when Chriſt will come. 1. When he hath received a Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.12. He was to travel into a far Country to receive a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35650:18"/>Kingdom, and to return. Jeſus Chriſt hath not yet fully received his Kingdom, all the Elect are not yet born, they are not all ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered and converted, they have not all yet viſited the Son, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12. performed their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and yielded obedience to him. It is a Work for a long time for Chriſt to ride forth proſperouſly, conquer a Kingdom, and ſubject Rebels to himſelf, and then to reign proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly over them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.5. more to refine, ſanctify, and fit them for himſelf. All Chriſts Servants muſt have time to occupy, and trade with his Pounds and Talents, before he will come, call them to an account, and reckon with them, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.16, 19. Chriſt muſt wound the hearts of his Enemies, and cauſe them, as foiled, to fall under him, and as worſhippers to fall before him. Chriſt muſt alſo ſhew his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious power for ſome time, in ruling in the midſt of his enemies, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.2. 2. That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their rage, they cannot hinder Chriſt's Kingdom to riſe, or cauſe it to fall, but Chriſt will go on more Levening the World with his Doctrine, more ſubduing the Nations by his Word, till this ſtone did fill the whole Earth, and the Name of this Shepherd was great to the ends of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt will come, when all his Members are compleat, and he hath the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Body, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.23. When his Spouſe hath made her ſelf ready, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. <hi>The mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35650:19"/>of the Lamb is come, and his Wife hath made her ſelf ready.</hi> When ſhe is cloathed in fine Linnen, white and clean, and adorned with Clothing of wrought Gold, and Raiment of Needle-work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Jeſus Chriſt will come, when he hath prepared a place to lead and bring his people to, <hi>John</hi> 14.3. <hi>If I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you to my ſelf, that where I am you may be.</hi> But when may Chriſt be ſaid to have prepared a place for all his Members? Surely when Chriſt hath ſprinkled the Throne, and the Heavenly Sanctuary with his Blood, when he hath pleaded his Sufferings and Death for each of them, that they may be let into the glorious Preſence and Kingdom of God, then he may be ſaid to have prepared a place for them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When Chriſt's Corn and Harveſt is fully ripe, then he will come to reap, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.28, 29. When <hi>the earth bringeth forth the blade, then the ear, then the full Corn in the ear; but when the fruit is brought forth, immediately he putteth in the ſickle, becauſe the harveſt is come.</hi> Chriſt will not delay, or loſe time, when the Harveſt is ripe, when the Members are grown up <hi>to a perfect man, to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Jeſus Chriſt will be Revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, 1. To juſtifie the Hiſtory and Doctrine of the Goſpel, that <hi>he was received up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35650:19"/>and ſat on the right hand of God,</hi> Mark 16.19. That <hi>he entred into Heaven, Angels, Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Powers, being made ſubject to him,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.22. <hi>that he was received up into glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. To anſwer the hopes and expectation of his People, they wait for a Saviour from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.20. and look for God's Son Jeſus from Heaven, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſt will be Revealed from Heaven, to ſhew the Spiritual Nature of his Kingdom, that it is a heavenly Kingdom; That he hath had his Throne in Heaven, and from thence his Kingdom hath ruled over all. He hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved all the rage and actings of his enemies, and all the love and obedience of his friends. He hath inſpected all the concerns of his Members, and tranſacted all the affairs of his Kingdom. This hath been honorable and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to Chriſt, that he hath had a reſt, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.10. in Heaven, and yet neglected none of his work in repreſſing the rage of his enemies, and in reviving the fainting ſpirits of his friends, and ſteering all the affairs of his Church to a ſafe and happy Port. He hath ſupplied his poor, and ſupported his weak Members.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Jeſus Chriſt will be Revealed from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for the greater confuſion and terror of his Enemies. How will this affright and amaze them, that he, who they thought ſlept under the clods of the Earth, ſhould appear riding on the clouds of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35650:20"/>he, who the <hi>Jews</hi> thought was ſuffering in Hell, for deluding and deceiving the World, ſhould come to Judge the World, and to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Men to Hell, for not believing on him, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.16. <hi>Joſeph</hi> was thought by his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be loſt, or dead, but how were they confounded and troubled, when they found him alive, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.3. heard him ſpeaking to them, ſaw him under <hi>Pharaoh</hi> Ruling over all the Land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> So how will it diſmay, and overwhelm the unbelieving World, when Chriſt that was thought to remain dead ſhall be preſented to their eyes as alive? When he that was ill treated by Men in the form of a Servant, ſhall appear in the glory of a Lord, to judge both the Quick and the Dead, and ſhall be manifeſted as having all Power in Heaven and Earth committed to him, and can juſtifie and crown thoſe that have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on him; and condemn and puniſh thoſe that have rebelled againſt him, who neither have believed his Doctrine, or obeyed his Commands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <hi>USE</hi> of Examination. <hi>Examine your ſelves under what Notion Chriſt will be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and come to you at laſt. Whether he will appear as your Friend, or as your Enemy; To your joy or ſorrow: As a loving Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom to receive you to himſelf,</hi> John 14.3. <hi>Or as an incenſed Judge to Sentence and Caſt you from himſelf, ſaying,</hi> Go ye curſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting fire, <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.41.</head>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35650:20"/>
               <p> Will Chriſt come to give you any thing? Will he beſtow <hi>a Crown of Righteouſneſs?</hi> 2 Tim. 4.18. <hi>A Crown of Life,</hi> Rev. 2.10. Will he call you to inherit an everlaſting Kingdom? <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.34. Or will Chriſt come upon you <hi>as a Thief in the Night,</hi> to impoveriſh, ſpoil, deprive you of all the good things you now poſſeſs and enjoy? Will not your Ciſterns then be broken, your Candles and Lamps be put out? Will not your whole Paradiſe of ſenſual and ſinful delights be lighted and blaſted? Will not Creatures be withdrawn from you, and God himſelf alſo depart? <hi>The floor and the Wine-preſs ſhall not feed you, and God himſelf will leave and forſake you,</hi> Hoſ. 9.2, 12. Will you not at once be turned out of your Stewardſhip, and alſo be cut off from all hope of the heavenly Inheritance? Will not Chriſt's coming be your utter undoing? Will you not ſuſtain a damage and loſs never to be repaired? For your wooing and buying time will be over; the Spiritual Market will be at an end. Will it not be ſad, when others are rich Heirs, for you to be poor Bankrupts, emptied and ſtript of all valuable and deſirable good for ever? Inquire therefore ſeriouſly and diligently, how it ſtands with you, in relation to Chriſt's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. Is Jeſus Chriſt Revealed in you, and to you; and is his new Nature formed in you? <hi>It is not Fleſh and Blood, but our Father that is in heaven, that muſt reveal Christ to us,</hi> Matt. 16.17.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35650:21"/>he that hath heard, and learned of the Father, comes to the Son. Hath the ſpirit ever glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Chriſt in your eyes? Is he moſt precious to you? If Chriſt be not Revealed to you while you are on Earth, he cannot be Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Heaven, to your joy and comfort. Have you an underſtanding to know the worth, excellency, and preciouſneſs of Chriſt, ſo that you give your ſelves to him, and are in him? If Chriſt do dwell in your hearts below, you may be aſſured that you ſhall dwell in his Houſe above. Are you related to Chriſt? Are you really his? <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24. <hi>They that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh.</hi> They that are Chriſts ſhall <hi>be made alive at his coming,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.23. Is the Match made up between Chriſt and you, by a mutual Spiritual kiſs? Doth Chriſt kiſs you, expreſſing his ſervent love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and ſpeaking powerfully and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to you the Doctrine of Grace, the Word of Reconciliation? The Goſpel of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is your own Intereſt in Chriſt's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Promiſes, ſealed and delivered to you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do you kiſs Chriſt the Son of God? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.1. <hi>When Iſhould find thee without I would kiſs thee.</hi> And <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> are ſaid to ſalute, kiſs, or embrace the Promiſes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Where the mouth of Faith doth meet, with the mouth of Chriſt ſpeaking the Word of Life, and the promiſes of Spiritual Benefits, is perſwaded of them, doth embrace
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35650:21"/>them; then the Soul kiſſes Chriſt. There is alſo a kiſs of Homage, as <hi>Samuel</hi> kiſſed <hi>Saul,</hi> acknowledging him as the Lord's Anointed. When we receive the Law from Chriſt's mouth, and profeſs our ſubjection to his Scepter, and obedience to his Laws, then we kiſs Chriſt. 3. Are you willing that Chriſt ſhould come? Do you deſire, long for, and love Chriſt's appearing? The Church ſaith, <hi>Make haſte my beloved,</hi> Cant. 8.14. When Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I come quickly,</hi> ſhe adds her <hi>Amen; Even ſo come Lord Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 22.20. Chriſtians are ſaid not only to look for, but to haſten the coming of the day of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that is, by their wiſhings, longings, earneſt deſires. Do you fervently love the appearing of Chriſt, as that which will be exceeding ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable to him, comfortable and beneficial to you? Do you love Chriſt's appearing, as that which will be exceeding glorious to him? For by his voice he ſhall quicken, raiſe, call forth all that are in their Graves, <hi>John</hi> 5.28. That Chriſt knows all that ever lived, can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh their duſt from the duſt of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from the duſt of the Earth: That he knows all their thoughts, words and actions, remembers them, and will call them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.5. Then Chriſt will ſit on the Throne of his glory, and all Nations ſhall be gathered before him, to be judged by by him. This is the perfection of Chriſt's
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35650:22"/>Kingdom, and his higheſt act of Royalty, to ſentence all Men to their eternal ſtate: It is ſaid he ſhall <hi>judge the quick and dead</hi> at his Appearing and Kingdom. Now is his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom moſt highly magnified and exalted, when the <hi>quick and dead</hi> muſt be Judged by him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This appearing of Chriſt will be moſt comfortable to his People; he will come to beſtow Crowns, to give Rewards, to divide eternal Portions and Inheritances to them. he comes with the Keys of Hell and Death in his Hand: He hath the Key of Hell to ſhut it, that the Souls of his People may not enter in, elſe the mouth of the bottomleſs Pit, and of the roaring Lion, would gape for them, and ſwallow them up. And Chriſt hath the Key of Death to open the Graves, that the Bodies of Saints may come forth. May not Chriſtians well love the appearing of Chriſt, who hath delivered them from the wrath to come, and as a Captain of Salvation will lead them to glory? Do you long for Chriſt's co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as that which will be a Harveſt-day, a Marriage-day, and a day of full Redemption? Or are you averſe from Chriſt's coming? Do you not loath and dread the thoughts of it? Is not Chriſt's coming full ſore againſt your Will? There is a vaſt difference between theſe two expreſſions; the breaking up the Houſe, and the opening of the door to Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35650:22"/>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 12.36. The Houſe of a carnal unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Man is broken through; Chriſt breaks in upon him irreſiſtibly, unavoidably: a force is put upon Sinners. If they could Fetter Chriſt's feet, obſtruct his way, clog and ſtop his Chariot-wheels, Chriſt ſhould never come or be Revealed; but Saints that hang their hopes, and put all their happineſs in Chriſt's Appearing, do readily open the door, and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully will come and entertain Chriſt. Do you look for his coming, as a beloved Bridegroom, as a deſired Gueſt? Or do you not mind, or deſire Chriſt's coming, but will be as much ſurprized by it, and aſtoniſhed at it, as at the coming of a Thief, that was not thought of at all?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Do you prepare, and make ready for Chriſt's coming? Is all your Week day of life nothing but a preparation for the eternal Sabbath? Are your Loines girded, that you may do the Work of your heavenly Calling? Are your Lamps burning, that you may do your Work skilfully and diligently? Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in it continually. It is ſaid of the good Woman, <hi>that her Candle goeth not out by night,</hi> Prov. 31.18. Do your Candles continue burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through this dark night of Time? Others have put out their light, and given themſelves up to ſloth and ſleep. It is a great thing to watch, and keep our Garments on and about us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Bleſſed is he that watcheth, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35650:23"/>keepeth his Garments.</hi> Chriſt may ſuddenly come, and ſurprize Sinners, that they may not have time to put on Spiritual Garments to <hi>put on Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 13.14. <hi>and the new man,</hi> Epheſ. 4.24. We are too apt to put off our Coat, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.3. to lay aſide a gracious, ſpiritual holy, and heavenly frame, and to give way to ſloth, ſleep, and carnal ſecurity. This Spiritual Garment is ſoon put off, but it is hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. I have put off my Coat, and how ſhall I put it on? It is highly commendable to have our Lamps burning, when the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of others are put out; and it is a Night of groſs and thick darkneſs with them. It is to the Honour of Chriſt the Bridegroom to be expected, waited for, and to be lighted to his Fathers Houſe, with bright and burning Lamps, with Graces active, and in a moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous and lively Exerciſe. Is this Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Light of Time, as a Paſſoever Night to you? <hi>Are your Loins girded? Are your Shoes on your Feet?</hi> The Feet of the Church are ſaid to be beautiful with Shoes; ſhe was fit to Journy, to Travel. Are you waiting for God's Call out of the <hi>Egypt</hi> of this World? Are you fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ready to Travel hence into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan?</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come with me my Spouſe, with me from</hi> Lebanon: Are you willing and ready to follow Jeſus Chriſt? Are you like Servants, that look for the return of their Lord from the Wedding Feaſt, to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35650:23"/>have you a way as Gueſts to his Table in his heavenly Kingdom? <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. There is much in theſe words, <hi>And be you like ſuch as look for the return of your Lord,</hi> Luke 12.36. The watchfulneſs, diligence, the conſtant la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, activity and zeal of ſome Chriſtians, doth evidence to themſelves, and demonſtrate to others, that they look for the coming of Chriſt: That they prepare, make ready, ſet all things in order, for their receiving and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of the Lord Jeſus. Their great care and endeavour is, that they may not be found ſleeping and undreſſed; that they may not walk naked, and their ſhame be ſeen for ever, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.15. It will be the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, to have had a long time to adorn the Soul allowed to Men, and yet to neglect and trifle it away, and their Souls to be found dead without the life of God, and to be found na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked without the Image and Righteouſneſs of God. Do you trim your Lamps, dreſs your Souls, and finiſh the Work which God hath given you to do, and that Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed you, that you may open to Chriſt immediately, without put offs, or delays, or excuſes, as thoſe that are not ſurprized or unready, as thoſe that would ſtay here no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that would have Time end, and Eternity begin? As thoſe that would have ſhadows fly away, and the everlaſting day to dawn? Theſe are great words, that Chriſt will knock
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35650:24"/>for a full entrance into us, and a total poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of us; and we muſt open immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as thoſe that are ready to let Chriſt in, and to go away preſently with him: But are you not rather minding earthly things, ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering your ways and affections to unlawful Beloyeds? Do not your thoughts creep on the ground, and your Hearts dwell below? Would you not ſtay in a Natural Body? Would you not continue in, and be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Stewardſhip? Would you not dwell on Earth? Do you not eagerly drive the Chariot of your Trade? Do you not indulge your Carnal Affections, and give the Reins to your Senſual Appetites? So that there is no evidence that you look for Chriſt's Appearing; for you are not like thoſe that wait for the return of Chriſt from Heaven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. With what Attendance Jeſus Chriſt will come from Heaven? What Retinue will accompany him? He will be Revealed with his mighty Angels. How much doth the firſt and ſecond coming of Chriſt differ? He came firſt attended with weak Fiſhermen, but now he is ſurrounded and compaſſed with mighty Angels to wait on him. Two things are here obſervable, 1. That the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are called Chriſt's Angels. 2. That they are Stiled mighty Angels. 1. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are ſaid to be the Angels of the Lord Jeſus. This is an high Honour to Chriſt, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35650:24"/>all the Angels of Heaven are his Angels; He is Captain of God's Militia, and General of all the Hoſts of Heaven. They are Miniſters to attend on him, and his; and Hoſts to fight againſt his, and his Churches enemies. And well they may be called his Angels, for he made them; <hi>they were created by him,</hi> Col. 1.16, 17. <hi>and for him; and by him they do ſubſiſt,</hi> and have their Being upheld and continued to them, elſe they would ceaſe to be, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to nothing. 2. God therefore called the Angels to worſhip his Son made Fleſh, come into the World in our Nature. When he brought the firſt begotten into the World, he ſaith, <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him,</hi> Heb. 1.6. It may be inquired whether they do not owe the Son of God adoration, on the account of their being graciouſly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, and preſerved in their Integrity. The two Cherubims that figured the Angels, were made out of the Mercy-Seat, as well as ſtood upon it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.18, 19. There are Elect Angels, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. as well as Elect Men. Herein did the various and manifold Wiſdom of God ſhine, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.10. in keeping Elect Angels ſtanding, and in raiſing up Elect Men when they are fallen. 3. The Angels Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to Chriſt, and probably brought him Food, after the Devil had tempted him, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſion from his hunger. And an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel came from Heaven, and ſtrengthned Chriſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35650:25"/>in his Agony, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.43. 4. Jeſus Chriſt is the Ladder, that joins Earth and Heaven together, and it is on this Ladder the Angels of God aſcend, and deſcend, <hi>John</hi> 1.51. All Correſpondence, all Commerce, and Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, between the upper and lower World, is carried on by this Ladder. The Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to ſerve the Members of Chriſt, and then aſcend to give an Account of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſcharge of their Office and Truſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe Angels are called mighty Angels. And it is a great and mighty Work they are to undertake and execute; there is a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Malefactors to be Arreſted; there are great and mighty Enemies to be Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; there is a great and mighty Harveſt to be cut down, to be reaped, and ſeparated from the Field of the Church: There are Goats to be ſeparated from the Sheep, and bad Fiſh to be taken out from among the good. The Angels ſhall come forth to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Chriſt, Heaven ſhall be emptied of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints, to wait on Chriſt. The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, when they come forth, ſhall ſever the Wicked from among the Juſt; the Harveſt is the end of the World, the Wicked are the Tares, and the Reapers are the Angels, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.38, 39. Sinful Men and Women are as weak and feeble Tares, they cannot ſtand againſt, or before the Hook of theſe mighty Reapers, they ſhall be eaſily cut, they ſhall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35650:25"/>quickly fall before a ſharp hook managed by ſuch mighty Arms. The far greateſt part of the World will be found Tares, therefore there needs many mighty Reapers to cut down ſo vaſt a Harveſt; and skill will be requiſite to diſcern and diſtinguiſh ſome of the Tares, ſome cloſe and refined Hipocrites, from the good Corn. 2. They are to bind the Tares faſt in bundles, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.30. that they ſhall none of them eſcape. He that had not a Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Garment was to be bound hand and foot, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.13. His hands were to be bound, that he ſhould not fight or reſiſt; his feet were bound, that he ſhould not fly or run away. 3. Theſe Angels are as mighty Sergeants, to preſent Malefactors to the Judge. As for <hi>thoſe mine enemies</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>which would not that I ſhould reign over them, bring them before me,</hi> Luke 19.27. The Angels are to execute this Order, and fulfil this Command: They are to preſent Criminals at the Bar of the Judge. 4. When Chriſt doth Sentence and Condemn wicked Men, the Angels are ready to execute the Sentence; They gather thoſe that offend and commit iniquity; they pluck out the had Fiſh, and caſt them into a Furnace of unquenchable fire, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13 40, 50. Chriſt ſaith of his enemies, <hi>Let them be ſlain in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> Luke 14.27. Theſe condemned Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors may be ſaid to be ſlain by the Angels, when they caſt them into the Furnace; for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35650:26"/>then all this ſweet, pleaſant, and deſireable Life and Being, is conſumed and gone, thoſe are no better than woful, ſtinking Carkaſſes, that muſt be Food to the Worm that never dies, and fuel to the Fire that never goes out, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 66.24. 5. The Angels are to gather the Elect: It is ſaid that Chriſt ſhall ſend forth his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet, and ſhall gather his Elect from the four Winds, and from one end of Heaven to the other. Obſerve, 1. That the Elect are called Chriſt's Elect, he chuſes as well as the Father; the Lamb hath his Book of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. Thoſe that the Father gives him, the Names of thoſe he writes down in his Book. Theſe Chriſt chuſes to redeem, reconcile, and ſatisfie for: With the Salvation of theſe he charges himſelf. Theſe he muſt bring to his Fold, and they ſhall hear his voice, <hi>John</hi> 10.16. Theſe he muſt keep, and loſe none of them, <hi>John</hi> 17.1.2. The Angels are to gather theſe, as a <hi>Spouſe to Chriſt her Husband,</hi> Pſ. 45.14, 15. with joy ſhall ſhe be brought in Raiment of Needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work to the King: The Virgins her Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſhall be brought, they ſhall enter into the Kings Palace. When <hi>Abraham</hi> imploy'd his Servant to fetch a Wife out of <hi>Padan Aram</hi> for <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Son, he ſaid the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhould ſend his Angel before his Servant, and he ſhould take thence a Wife for his Son, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.7. As an Angel was imploy'd to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35650:26"/>the Work and Way of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Servant, and to bring a Wife to <hi>Iſaac:</hi> ſo the Angels of God ſhall bring, and preſent Chriſt's Wife to him; they ſhall know who are the Elect, find them out, and diſtinguiſh them from others. 2. They ſhall gather the Elect as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to their Head, as Loyal Subjects to their King, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.1. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the coming of the Lord Jeſus as a moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing, and the gathering of the Elect to him as a moſt ſweet, and comfortable thing; and the Angels ſhall do this Work to gather Saints to Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>USE. <hi>We may learn from the ATtendance of Christ, what Honour ſhall be put on Chriſt at his Appearing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Heaven ſhall be emptied of the Angels and glorified Saints to follow <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the Graves ſhall be emptied of the dead Bodies of the Saints to meet <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.14. <hi>Thoſe that ſleep in Jeſus, ſhall God bring with him.</hi> They ſhall be brought from death to life, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to Jeſus Chriſt. Chriſt ſhall come in his own Glory, as he is the Son of God; and <hi>thought it no robbery to be equal with God,</hi> Luke 9.26. And he ſhall come in the Fathers glory; that is, he ſhall come in that Glory the Father hath put on him, as his Righteous Servant. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>God hath exalted Chriſt, and given him a Name above every Name, that at the Name of Chriſt every knee ſhould bow, and every tongue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35650:27"/>ſhould confeſs that Jeſus is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</hi> The Father is glorified in the glory of Chriſt. And it is further ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.26. <hi>That he ſhall come in the glory of the holy Angels.</hi> They ſhall be Chriſt's Servitors, ſhall attend on his Nod, and wait at his beck, and be ready to fulfil his pleaſure. And what terror may this truth ſpeak to the wicked, that mighty Angels ſhall be Reapers to cut them down, and execute the Sentence of Chriſt upon them? And what comfort may this truth adminiſter to the Godly, that mighty Angels ſhall gather them to Chriſt? They ſhall not miſcarry, becauſe the Angels ſhall find them out and preſent them to Chriſt, as thoſe that will be juſtified by him, and enjoy communion with him. 4. In what manner will Chriſt appear? It is ſaid in a flame of fire. Our Tranſlators render it, in flaming fire. Chriſt's coming will be terrible to the Unbelieving World; his frowning Face will then be unveiled, his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Arm will then be made bare. His fury will then come up into his Face, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.18. Long meekneſs and patience will end in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity. Sinners do weary out the patience and Long-Suffering of God, that he can bear no more, no longer, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.22. He is even weary of repenting, <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.6. becauſe Sinners are not weary of ſinning.</p>
               <p>Doct. 4. <hi>Chriſt will be Revealed in flaming fire.</hi> 1. That he will be ſo Revealed in flaming fire.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35650:27"/>2. The <hi>Cauſes</hi> of it. 3. The <hi>dreadful Effects</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Lord Chriſt will be Revealed in flaming fire. 1. His <hi>eyes will be as a flame of fire,</hi> Rev. 1.14. to diſcern and diſcover the moſt ſecret wickedneſſes, and the hidden things of darkneſs, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.14. <hi>He will come burning with anger, his lips will be full of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and his tongue as a conſuming fire,</hi> Iſ. 30.27, 28. He will ſpeak to Sinners in his anger, and vex them in his ſore diſpleaſure; he will ſpeak hot, burning devouring words. <hi>Let them be ſlain in my preſence,</hi> Pſ. 2.5. <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire.</hi> In this Sentence his Tongue is like conſuming fire. <hi>Behold the Lord will come with fire, to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of fire,</hi> Iſ. 66.15. His Throne will be like the fiery flame, and his Wheels as the burning fire. Chriſt's Throne hath Wheels of Fire, to purſue fugitive and guilty Offenders. 4. From this Throne a fiery ſtream iſſueth, and cometh forth to puniſh the Wicked; as from the Throne of God, and the Lamb, a pure <hi>River of Water of Life</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, clear as Chryſtal, to refreſh the Saints. As the ſame Sun, at the ſame time, ſcorches ſome parts of the World, and revives and chears other parts with his more benign beams and rays, the Heaven of the Bleſſed, and the Hell of the Damned, will come from the ſame face of God, as ſmiling, or as frowning, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16. laſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why will Chriſt come in flaming fire?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35650:28"/>It is becauſe his abuſed Grace is turned into fury; he knocked, but Sinners would not open to him. They have ſhut out Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Salvation, and Eternal Life, from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and they have detained Sin, Satan, and Death, and ſhut them into their own Souls. Chriſt called, but they would not anſwer; he ſtretched out his hands full of Gifts, and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Bleſſings, and no Man regarded. They would not come to Chriſt, that they might have life, <hi>John</hi> 5.40. They would not be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered under his Wings, that they might have ſafety. They would not enter into his Fold, that they might be ſaved; go out and in, and find Paſture. They would not repair to his Houſe, that they might find reſt; or preſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Kingdom, that they might obtain a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying Feaſt at his Table, and an eternal Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his Throne. They would not kiſs the Son with a kiſs of Faithful Homage and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, therefore he becomes angry; yea, his anger riſeth up to fury, and breaks forth as Fire, ſo that there is no quenching of it. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have been loading Chriſt with contempt, affronts, provocations, all their days: They have been Treaſuring up Wrath, the Storm hath long been a gathering; Offenders have long been bringing Fuel to the Fire during their whole time, and God will be blowing it up during his Eternity. They thought Chriſt did not ſee, or obſerve their Iniquities; that he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35650:28"/>would not reſent, and could not puniſh their Tranſgreſſions: But Chriſt comes now in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire to ſhew the height of his anger, his fixed purpoſe to puniſh, and his power to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. As God turned Fallen <hi>Adam</hi> out of the Earthly Paradiſe, a ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> comes in a <hi>flame of Fire,</hi> to exclude Unbelievers, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners, from the <hi>Heavenly Paradiſe.</hi> 3. Conſider the dreadful effects of this <hi>flaming Fire;</hi> it will break forth, and take hold of the Creatures, and kindle a Conflagration both in the upper and lower World. <hi>The Heavens ſhall paſs away with a noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat;</hi> as if Metal ſhould be melted, and diſtil in ſcalding burning drops. The Earth, and the Works of it, ſhall be burnt up: The Earth is the Home of the Wicked, the Creatures they have doted on, and made them as their Idol Gods. And how dreadful will this be to the Ungodly, to ſee their Houſe, their Home, their Heaven, their Idol Gods, to be burnt up together? That the Creatures that were once Food to their Luſts, ſhall now become Fuel to the Fire of God's Anger? As the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> left their Images, their Idols, and <hi>David</hi> and his Men burnt them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.21. ſo Sinners muſt leave their Heaven, and all their Idol Gods below, and God will burn and conſume them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Fire will not ſtop here; the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture joins the burning of Heaven and Earth,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:35650:29"/>and the Perdition of ungodly Men together. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. <hi>The heavens; and the earth, that are now by the ſame word, are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire, againſt the day of judgment, and perdition of ungodly men.</hi> Shall the Traytors Houſe be burnt, and the Traytors themſelves eſcape? Shall the Creatures, that have been but paſſive Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſin, be conſumed? And ſhall the active Agents go Scot-free? Shall thoſe that have been Preſſed, forced Soldiers, ſuffer ſuch hard things? And ſhall the Voluntiers in this wicked War againſt God be exempted from puniſhment? The Heavens and the Earth fly from the face of the Judge <hi>ſitting on his white Throne, and their place was found no more.</hi> If the defiled Creatures could not brook or bear the <hi>angry face of the Judge,</hi> what ſhall become of the defilers of them? It is Men that have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and abuſed the Creatures, contrary to their natural inclinations and tendency, to ſerve their Luſts, and fight againſt God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt dreadful, ſcorching, and laſting Fire, muſt be their Portion and Puniſhment. God ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.22. <hi>A fire is kindled in mine anger, and ſhall burn to the loweſt Hell;</hi> it ſhall follow and purſue its fuel thither. God ſaith further, This fire <hi>ſhall conſume the earth and its increaſe.</hi> Theſe words may well expound the Text of <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.10. <hi>That the earth, and the works of it, or therein,</hi> that is, <hi>its fruits and increaſe, ſhall be burnt up.</hi> This Fire ſhall inflame, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35650:29"/>burn the very Foundations of the Mountains. If ſtrong Mountains cannot withſtand this Fire, how ſhall weak Sinners reſiſt it? The ſame Fire that burns Heaven and Earth, ſhall purſue Tranſgreſſors, as its moſt proper, kindly, and perpetual Fuel. Immortal Criminals ever dying, yet never dying Sinners, ſhall be the Fuel of it, <hi>and an eternal God ſhall blow up the flame over them,</hi> Iſ. 30.3.3. This <hi>fire</hi> will be dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: For, 1. It is the Fire, this is proper to, and will go forth againſt the Enemies, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 26.11. <hi>The fire of thine enemies ſhall conſume them;</hi> that is, the Fire that ſhall burn againſt, and prey on Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. So it is ſaid, <hi>Fiery indignation ſhall devour the Adverſaries,</hi> Heb. 10.27. Thoſe that are the Fuel of this fire, they are ſuch as were God's Enemies in time, and will continue his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to Eternity, and ſo be fit objects of his Fury. 2. This Fire ſhall burn to the utmoſt, it ſhall put forth its zeal to the utmoſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27. The zeal of Fire, <hi>as the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of darkneſs,</hi> Jude 13. doth terribly ſet forth the privative part of Hell; ſo the zeal of fire doth dreadfully expreſs the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive part. God will puniſh with the <hi>glory of his power,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.8. that is, <hi>with his power put forth moſt gloriouſly.</hi> Theſe expreſſions, <hi>the zeal of fire, and the glory of God's power,</hi> do illuſtrate one another. 3. This fire it will torment, but it will never refine. Never was, nor can any be brought to <hi>repentance by the fire of Hell.</hi> Sinners
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35650:30"/>will continue obſtinate in Sin, and God's heart will be hardened, his bowels be ſhut up; he will be fully reſolved to puniſh. 4. This Fire will come immediately from God and Chriſt, 1. From the <hi>face of God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>from the face of the Lord.</hi> So they are ſaid to <hi>fall into the hands of the living God,</hi> Heb. 10.31. He doth puniſh them immediately. God hath to do with them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Can thy hands be ſtrong, can thy heart endure in the day that I ſhall have to do with thee?</hi> The hands of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners cannot be ſtrong to reſiſt or keep off puniſhment; neither can their hearts be ſtout enough to endure and ſtand under it. Can Stubble, Chaff, Tares, reſiſt a God that is <hi>conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire?</hi> Heb. 12.29. Chriſt will kindle this Fire, and heat the Souls of Sinners, <hi>as an Oven.</hi> As Satans temptations, as his ſuggeſtions, as a <hi>Baker,</hi> Hoſ. 7.4, 6. and Mens own Luſts, did ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>heat this Oven,</hi> ſo Chriſt's wrath will, in a way of Righteous puniſhment, heat it. It is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.8, 9. That <hi>his hand ſhall find out all his enemies; his right hand ſhall find out all that hate him; thou ſhalt make them as an fiery Oven in the time of thine anger.</hi> 5. This Fire will. eat up the Adverſaries, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27. it will be eating of <hi>Adverſaries continually,</hi> yet <hi>never totally devour them.</hi> It will be eating of them to Eternity, and <hi>never make a full end of them.</hi> That Fire that devoures, will alſo ſalt the Subject it preys on, that it ſhall be preſerved
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:35650:30"/>to Eternity. Sinners are ſaid not to fall into the hand, but the <hi>hands of God:</hi> Both his <hi>hands, all his power is imployed for their miſery.</hi> As there is a puniſhing Hand, ſo there is a ſupporting Hand, to bear up the Sinner to endure tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Eternity; Stubble and Chaff, Tares and Thorns, could never hold out as Eternal Fuel to the Fire of God's wrath, were there not an Eternal God, and an Eternal Power to ſupport the Damned. 6. Sinners ſhall be <hi>tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with Fire and Brimſtone in the preſence of the Lamb,</hi> Rev. 14.10. This anſwers thoſe words of Chriſt, <hi>Let them be ſlain in my preſence,</hi> Luke 19.27. Tho' Chriſt be a Lamb, yet we read <hi>of the wrath of the Lamb;</hi> and that great day of his wrath will come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16.17. The <hi>Lamb will look on</hi> the torments of the wicked, and <hi>will not</hi> commiſerate them, or relent in the leaſt towards them. The Lamb <hi>will look on their torments, and will rejoice at them, and be much pleaſed with them,</hi> Rev. 7.14. They that neglected to <hi>waſh their Robes white in the Blood of the Lamb,</hi> Chriſt, in honour to himſelf, <hi>will stain all his Raiment;</hi> their <hi>blood ſhall be ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on his Garments,</hi> and this will render his Apparel as a Victorious Conquering Captain, glorious, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 63.1.3. Chriſt will never leſſen, or put out this Fire: It is a Fire to puniſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Rebellious Creatures, hardened and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies; a Fire of Jealouſie againſt Adulterous Souls.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:35650:31"/>
               <p> USE 1. <hi>This Truth may inform us how much Mens Sins, and obſtinate Unbelief, doth alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and transform the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: That he, that is ſtiled Love, ſhould be Revealed in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire: That he, whoſe Office is to be a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to quench Wrath, to make Peace, ſhould come to pour out Fury: That he, who beſeeched Men to be Reconciled to God, and wooed them to be Eſpouſed to himſelf, ſhould now come to Execute Vengeance: That he that long and often did knock, and call Sinners to open to him ſhould now riſe up, ſhut the Door, and be deaf to all the knocks and beſeeching of Sinners,</hi> Luke 13.26. <hi>That he who ſpread out his Hands, and ſtretched out his Wings, to call and gather Sinners to himſelf, doth now ſhut them out from himſelf, and expoſe them to an Eternal Storm of Vengeance: That he who once acted as a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, to heal, ſhould now come to deſtroy: That he that is a Redeemer to others, ſhould come now to bind obſtinate Sinners in Chains, and caſt them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon, and ſubject them to Eternal Bondage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſecond Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>USE 2. <hi>This may ſtrike a Terror into Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Chriſt will come in flaming Fire, what then will become of Stubble fully dry? What will thoſe ſuffer that are but Chaff? That are Reprobate Silver? And that are but Droſs? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.119. <hi>Veſſels of wrath fitted for Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> When the <hi>Harveſt of the Earth is ripe, when the Grapes of the Vine of the Earth are fully ripe,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35650:31"/>the Sickle muſt be thruſt in, and made uſe of, to reap the Harveſt, and cut the Grapes, that they may be caſt into the Wine-preſs of the wrath of God,</hi> Rev. 14.15, 18. Tares, barren, and dry Trees, <hi>muſt be fuel to this flaming fire,</hi> Matt. 3.10.</p>
               <p>USE 3. <hi>Endeavour to prevent deſtruction by this flaming Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O make ſure that you ſhall not dwell with <hi>Conſuming Fire,</hi> that you ſhall not inhabit with <hi>Everlaſting Burnings.</hi> O come to the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that he may make peace. O come to the <hi>Blood of ſprinkling,</hi> that it may ſpeak, and plead for your Pardon. Fly to Chriſt, that you may be found <hi>in him,</hi> Pſ. 3.9. and ſo may find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with God, and may be found in peace, and your Faith may be found to Honor and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at the Appearing of Chriſt. It is the Blood of Chriſt that muſt quench the Fire of God's wrath; and it is the Spirit of Chriſt, as mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, as ſanctifying, that muſt pull away the Fuel of this Fire. There is a ſweet and gracious Promiſe, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 1.25. <hi>I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy Droſs, and take away all thy Tin.</hi> How full, how rich, and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, is this Promiſe, that the Droſs of Prophaneſs, and the Tin of Hipocriſie, ſhall be purely purged away? If open Sin, and ſecret Hipocriſie, be removed, the Euel of this Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fire will be put away. We muſt be put into <hi>Chriſt's Refining Fire,</hi> that we may not be expoſed to God's <hi>Conſuming Fire.</hi> If Chriſt now
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35650:32"/>appear for you in Heaven, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.23, 24. he will not appear againſt you in the great Day. Thoſe he has made <hi>Righteouſueſs and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> to, he cannot Condemn; he will not deſtroy at his Appearing.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>For what end will Chriſt be Revealed in Flaming Fire?</hi> It is thus expreſſed, <hi>He comes in a Flame of Fire,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>giving Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance.</hi> 1. He that is a merciful, and gracious God, yet will have no other gift to beſtow on impenitent Unbelievers. Tho' Mercy belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to God, which he will Exerciſe towards his People; tho' Forgiveneſs belong to him, which he will beſtow on penitent Believers, yet only Vengeance belongs to God, to be executed on hardened Tranſgreſſors, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.30. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 94.1, 2. He hath no other Attributes but <hi>Juſtice and Power,</hi> Rom. 9.22. <hi>to be glorified in them.</hi> 2. This is an Impoveriſhing Gift, when Chriſt gives Vengeance, <hi>the one Talent ſhall be taken away,</hi> Matt. 25.28. All that the Souls of Sinners do <hi>Luſt after ſhall depart; all the things that are dainty and goodly ſhall depart, and they ſhall find them no more at all,</hi> Rev. 18.14. 3. This is a Formenting Gift; <hi>it is a Cup of trembling, a Cup of fury,</hi> If, 51.21, 22. <hi>it is a Cup of red Wine, and full of mixture;</hi> all bitter, all fatal, deadly Ingredients, are ſqueezed into, joined, and are rempered in this Cup, yet it is without mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not one drop of Mercy or Kindneſs in it, but it is pure <hi>Wrath and Severity,</hi> as if all the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35650:32"/>ſtrongeſt, moſt griping, tormenting Poyſons, did meet in one Cup, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.10. and there was nothing to antidote or allay their dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly force and operation. 4. This is a Gift they muſt receive, they cannot decline, avoid, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.15, 28. <hi>Take the Wine-cup of this fury at my hand, and cauſe all the Nations, to whom I ſend thee, to drink it. If they refuſe to take the cup and to drink, then ſhalt thou ſay unto them, Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, ye ſhall certainly drink.</hi> I may allude to this Text, Tho' Condemned Sinners do loath the bitter and dreadful Cup, that God giveth to them, tho' they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coil, ſtart from it, and refuſe it, yet they ſhall certainly drink it. 5. This is a Gift that is Debt and Wages, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>The wages of ſin is death.</hi> So God is ſaid to <hi>repay fury, to repay recompence,</hi> Iſ. 59.18. and to render his anger with fury, and his rebuke with flames of Fire. <hi>We are commanded to render to all their dues,</hi> Rom. 13.7. Miſery and puniſhment is due to Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, if Chriſt ſhould not pay it he would not be true to his Word, or juſt to himſelf. <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and anguiſh belongs to every Soul that ſins,</hi> Rom. 2.9. We are <hi>bid to owe nothing to any man but love,</hi> Rom. 13.8. And this is a Debt that muſt be always paying, and yet can never be fully diſcharged; ſo God owes Sinners en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and vengeance, and this Debt will be paying, and yet never be wholly paid off, or diſcharged to Eternity. What Preſents do
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35650:33"/>Sinners make to, or what Gifts do they beſtow on God? What Fruit did God's Vineyard yield to him? <hi>Were they not ſowre, and wild grapes, grapes of gall, and bitter cluſters? Wine that is the poyſon of Dragons, the cruel venom of Aſps?</hi> Deut. 32.32, 33. What <hi>crop, or harveſt, doth barren, and bad ground, yield to the Husbandman, but briers and thorns?</hi> Heb. 6.8. How Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is it then, that Chriſt ſhould give venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to them? Deal out blows, ſtripes, and wounds to them, and that for ever? Chriſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered them Mercy once, and they would not receive it, but he will give them Puniſhment, he will ſhew Severity to them, and they ſhall not be able to decline, refuſe, or reject it. <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners would not do Chriſt right, would not give him their hearts,</hi> Prov. 23.26. <hi>They would not give him glory</hi> Jer. 13.16. Chriſt muſt therefore inflict puniſhment on them, and give vengeance to them. If Men will not <hi>give God, and Chriſt glory,</hi> Chriſt will get honour on them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or no. Compare thoſe two Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.16. <hi>Give glory to the Lord your God.</hi> And that in <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.17. <hi>I will get me honour on</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>and all his Hoſt.</hi> Thoſe that will not give Chriſt glory by repenting and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Chriſt will get Honour by pouring out his fury, and executing vengeance on them. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.22. O Zidon, <hi>in thee I will be glorified, they ſhall know I am the Lord, when I ſhall have executed judgments in her. The day of vengeance
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35650:33"/>is in Gods heart,</hi> Iſ. 63.4. And the ſtrokes of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhall ſhortly be dealt out by Chriſt's hands. <hi>The whirlwind of the Lord will go forth in fury, it ſhall fall grievouſly on the head of the wicked,</hi> Jer. 23.19. 6. But on whom will Chriſt take vengeance? This Text informs us, it is on all that know not, and obey not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. As it is <hi>life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal to know the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent,</hi> John 17.3. ſo this cauſeth death eternal to be ignorant of the true God, and <hi>Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</hi> Thoſe that hear the Goſpel, and do not liſten to it, and receive it, are guilty of a wilful and affected Ignorance of God, and Chriſt. The light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but they come not to it; yea, <hi>they ſhut their eyes againſt it,</hi> Matt. 13.15. and ſo concur with Satan to promote their own deſtruction. The Devil blinds their minds, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. leſt they ſhould believe, <hi>and they cloſe their own eyes,</hi> leſt they ſhould ſee with their Eyes, hear with their Ears, underſtand with their Hearts, and <hi>ſo ſhould be converted, and God ſhould heal them.</hi> How guilty are Men before God, who impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſhut in Natural Light? <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. and exclude, ſhut out, Supernatural Lights. <hi>The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man receiveth not the things of the ſpirit, for they are fooliſhneſs to him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.14. The blindneſs, folly, and vanity of their minds, is as a dark Lanthorn about the Candle of Natural Light, to hinder it from ſhining out in their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35650:34"/>Words and Actions: They detain, and hold it under unrighteouſly: Their Luſts are too hard for their Light, and do Rebel againſt it. And Men come not to that Supernatural Light, that ſhines in the Goſpel, leſt their deeds ſhould be reproved, and themſelves condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Tho' Men may pleaſe themſelves with Notional, and Speculative Knowledge, as it may ſwell their Pride, and commend them to the Eſteem of Men, yet when it ſhould touch and wound Conſcience, affect the Heart, be reduced to Practiſe, and reform the Life, then <hi>they hate knowledge,</hi> Prov. 1 29. Thus thoſe two Texts are to be reconciled, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 58.2. <hi>They ſeek me daily, and delight to know my ways.</hi> Yet this is charged even on <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> That they hated Knowledge, and would not chuſe the Fear of the Lord; they did not like to pleaſe, fear, worſhip, and ſerve God in ſincerity.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But is there no diſtinction of Perſons meant in theſe words? Are they to be underſtood of the ſame Unregenerate Perſons within the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, that both know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, that there are Carnal, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted Perſons within the Church, that may be ſaid neither to know God, nor yet to obey the Goſpel of Chriſt. Eli<hi>'s Sons,</hi> tho' they were Prieſts, are ſaid <hi>not to know the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.12. And the Jews are thus charged, <hi>Through deceit they refuſe to know me, ſaith the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35650:34"/>Lord.</hi> Jer. 9.6. Either they thought they had found ſome better Good, ſome ſweeter Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than God, or that the knowledge of God would diſturb their Peace, and imbitter their Pleaſures and Luſts to them; and thus thro' deceit they did refuſe to know God. God complains, <hi>That his People are deſtroy'd for lack of knowledge,</hi> Hoſ 4.5, 6. It may be Day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as Men are under a clear diſpenſation of the words of Reconciliation, Righteouſneſs and Salvation, yet it may be Night within, by reaſon of the blindneſs of the Mind, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy of the Will. If Men <hi>did rightly know God, they would truſt in him,</hi> Pſ. 9.10. and ſet their love on him. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 91.14. They that know Gods name, are ſaid to give their hearts to him, to ſet their love on him. But it is apparent, that the Truſt of many, called Chriſtians, is with-held, and their love withdrawn from God. <hi>They caſt God himſelf, and his Word too, behind their backs,</hi> Pſal. 50.17. and therefore do not know God. If they did indeed know the perfect Holineſs of God, the Purity of his Word, the ſtrictneſs of his Law, the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity and Terror of his Threatnings, they would fly to Chriſt, ſubmit to the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God, obey the Goſpel, and Truſt on the Lord Jeſus, both for Reconciliation and Sanctification, <hi>Matt:</hi> 5.6. It is too evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that all Unconverted Perſons in the Church, though called Chriſtians, do not
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:35650:35"/>know God, <hi>Their Light doth not ſhine before men,</hi> Phil. 2.15, 16. And they do not hold forth the Word of Life in their Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4, 3. They do not think of God, he is not in all their thoughts, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. They do not truſt in him. They do not love God. Chriſt ſaith to the <hi>Jews, I know you, that the love of God is not in you,</hi> John 5.42. <hi>They delight not in the Almighty, Job</hi> 27.10. they fear not God. <hi>My fear, ſaith God, is not in thee,</hi> Jer. 2.19. <hi>There is no fear of God before their eyes,</hi> Rom. 3.18. <hi>They lightly eſteem of God, are unmindful of him, and forget him,</hi> Deut. 32.5, 18. They do not ſeek after God, draw near to him, converſe and enjoy communion with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.11. If Men deſigned to pleaſe God, would they paſs the bounds that <hi>he ſets to them?</hi> Eph. 2.2. <hi>break the yoke he puts on them?</hi> Would they affront and reject his Authority? Would they make God's Laws void, and live in the open and notorious breach of his Commands? If Men did know God, could they allow themſelves in Envy, Hatred, Malice? In Curſing, Swearing, Lying, Stealing, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Adultery? Could they go on in vain, unprofitable Talks; yea, in filthy and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Communication, in Wanton and Laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Language? Could Men be ſo unjuſt one to another, as to Plow away one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Land at Seed-time, and to cut over
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:35650:35"/>their Furrows, and take away their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Corn at Harveſt? Could Men ſo gripe, and oppreſs one another? Could they live without Prayer, and not call upon God in their Families? Would they ſo neglect their Children? Not Teach, Inſtruct, and Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them for God, but rather yield, and give them up to Satan, by leaving them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Power of Darkneſs, and the Law of Sin? Could they ſo connive at their Sins, and not ſeverely check and chaſtize them for, and reſtrain them from their Vices, if they did know God? If Men neither own God as a Father, and do not acknowledge Men as Brethren, do not all theſe Evils loudly proclaim, and ſtrongly evidence, that many, called Chriſtians, <hi>do not know God?</hi> Therefore Chriſt will come to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Vengeance on them; to thruſt them into a dark, dreadful Priſon, and to caſt them into a Furnace of unquenchable Fire.</p>
               <p>But this expreſſion, <hi>thoſe that know not God,</hi> doth mainly and chiefly concern the Heathen World, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.8. <hi>While the</hi> Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians <hi>did not know God, they did ſervice to them that were no Gods.</hi> And the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were carried to Dumb Idols, even as they were led. They did not know the right Object of Adoration, but did Service to them that were no Gods by Nature. They did endow a falſe God with their Religious Adoration.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35650:36"/>Many of the Heathen did think the World was from Eternity, and never made: They did not acknowledge the Author of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or the end for which they were made. They ſought after nothing but what they ſhould eat, what they ſhould drink, and wherewithal they ſhould be clothed, <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.32. as if they were all Body, and there were no other Life but this preſent Life. Now this is a heinous Sin for Heathens, not to know God, not to ſeek after him. This is a great and inexcuſable ſin not to know, when there are ſo many Witneſſes that do teſtify for God. <hi>He hath not left himſelf without witneſs,</hi> Acts 14.16, 17. Theſe Witneſſes ſhould be called and examined, <hi>Job</hi> 12.7, 8. <hi>Ask now the Beaſts, and they ſhall teach thee; and the Fowls of the Air, and they ſhall tell thee; or ſpeak to the Earth, and it ſhall teach thee; and the Fiſhes of the Sea ſhall declare unto thee.</hi> There is a great Cauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending about the Being of God. When this weighty Matter is to be tried, ſurely we ſhould, by Meditation, call and ask the Witneſſes, what they can teſtify for God, his Being, Power, and Goodneſs?</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are ſo many Preachers that declare his Glory, and ſhew forth his Handy-work. As this is Engraven on the Scriptures, <hi>God ſpake me,</hi> ſo this is in Capital Letters writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35650:36"/>on the Creature, <hi>God made me.</hi> That Hand that ſtretched out that ſpangled Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py above our Heads, and that hath ſpread this flowery Carpet that is under our Feet, <hi>day unto day uttereth ſpeech,</hi> Pſal. 9.2. Every day doth abundantly utter ſomething of God. And the ſame word is uſed of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.7. <hi>I ſhall abundantly utter the memory of that Goodneſs.</hi> Two things are here to be obſerved, 1. That the Creatures are ſuch Preachers, as never do keep ſilence, <hi>day unto day uttereth ſpeech.</hi> It offers new Matter of Contemplation and Admiration, and Night unto Night ſheweth Knowledge. Every ſucceeding Night inſtructs the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Night, and makes ſome farther and new Diſcoveries of God, that ſhould more enlighten the Minds, and affect the Hearts of Men towards God. 2. The Creatures preach God in a Speech and Language, that all Nations may underſtand, though their Languages are ſo confounded, and are not underſtood by other People and Nations; there is no Speech, or Language, where their voice is not heard. The moſt ignorant and brutiſh <hi>Barbarians,</hi> may underſtand the Speech and Language that the Creatures do preach in. The confuſion of <hi>Babel</hi> doth not hinder the Creatures from being under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in what they publiſh, and declare of God.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:35650:37"/> 3. There is a great Book in which Men may read God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Their Line is gone forth into all the Earth, and their Words to the end of the Earth.</hi> The Pages of this great Book are the Sea, the Heavens, and the Earth. And this Book ſtill lieth open, and the moſt ignorant, illiterate, and unskilful, may read in this Book, and underſtand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of its Contents. This is a long Line that reacheth to the ends of the Earth; and it is written in ſuch great and Capital Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that all may read it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Men are in the World as in a great Room all hung round with Glaſſes; he that is in ſuch a Room, may clearly and plainly ſee the Attributes, and Excellencies of God. <hi>The inviſible things of God, from the Creation of the World, are clearly ſeen,</hi> Rom. 1.20. They are evidenced and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to Senſe; yet ſo, that the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doth help the Senſes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They are underſtood by the Mind, that contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates the things that are made; and ſo Senſe, by the aſſiſtance of the Mind, doth clearly ſee inviſible things.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There are Garments, with which God is Clothed, and in which he may be ſeen, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.2. <hi>David</hi> ſaith to God, <hi>Who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt thy ſelf with Light, as with a Garment.</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:35650:37"/>The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> plainly refers to God's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Light. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.3. <hi>God ſaid let there be Light, and there was Light.</hi> God did then put on this bright and glorious Creature as a Garment. As the Greatneſs, Majeſty, and Glory of Kings, is ſeen in their Clothing, ſo God is known how Powerful, how Good, how Wiſe, he is by his Works. <hi>Scultetus</hi> ſaith, (on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.) Veſtis Dei Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planda, ſi Deum Contemplari volueris; <hi>You muſt view God's Garment, if you will Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate God himſelf, for God himſelf otherwiſe is inviſible.</hi> We cannot come to the naked Divine Eſſence, but we muſt ſee the firſt Cauſe clothed with Effects in the Works of Creation and Providence: As when God comes forth to execute Juſtice, he is ſaid <hi>to Clothe himſelf with the Garments of Vengeance.</hi> Iſa. 59.17. He puts on the <hi>Garments of Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for Clothing, and was clad with Zeal as a Cloak.</hi> Hath God Clothed himſelf with ſo many, and ſuch glorious Garments? Are his Attributes ſo viſible in his Creatures? And are not Men inexcuſable, that know not God, who daily comes forth to us Clothed in his Works of Creation and Providence, and thereby renders himſelf viſible to us?</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But what do theſe Witneſſes, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Books, Glaſſes, Garments of God, diſcover and make known?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:35650:38"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Being, the Eternity, Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Being of a God, the inviſible things of God from the Creation of the World, are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his Eternal Power and Godhead, or his Divine Being. Where there are Effects, there muſt be a Cauſe; where there are Streams, there muſt be a Fountain. If you will trace, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and perſue the ſmalleſt ſtream, it will at laſt bring you to the Ocean; ſo follow the ſmalleſt Rivulet of Creature-Beings, and it will bring you to God, the infinite Sea of Being. Where there is ſo great a Houſe raiſed with ſo much Art and Skill, there muſt needs be a Builder: None ever ſaw a Houſe built by Chance, or Accident, and what Folly and Madneſs is it to think, that this great Houſe of the World was built by a Caſual, yet Lucky meeting of Stones toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? The Creatures are not of themſelves, and therefore cannot be from Eternity. That only that is Infinite, Omnipotent, All wiſe, can be from Eternity; Creatures are not ſo, and therefore cannot be from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Ask any Man living, did you make your ſelf, none can be ſo impudent to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he made himſelf. And there is the ſame Reaſon againſt his Father; or any
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35650:38"/>other Man, that he did not make himſelf; therefore Men muſt neceſſarily come to a Firſt Man, and to a God that made him. Thus the Creatures do demonſtrate the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Creatures declare the Eternity of God. He that made all things muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be before them. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.17. <hi>He is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, and by him all things were made and conſiſt,</hi> Col. 1.16, 17. <hi>From everlasting to everlaſting he is God,</hi> Pſal. 90.2. If God were not from Eternity, the World could not have had a beginning, or any Creature have been formed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Creatures proclaim the power of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. <hi>his eternal power.</hi> Men ſpeak words, but God ſpeaks things; <hi>by his word he calls things that are not,</hi> Rom. 4.17. And their anſwer is to riſe, ſpring up, and exiſt; that which is nothing, yet hears and obeys God. <hi>God ſaid let their be Light,</hi> let the Earth bring forth Trees, Plants, Herbs, and Flowers, and it was ſo; and yet the Earth had no Seed of theſe things in it ſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.11, 12. And as God ſpeaks Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſo he breaths the Soul, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>God breathed into mans noſtrils the breath of life, and he became a living ſoul.</hi> And God writes in the Minds and Wills of Men; none but he
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:35650:39"/>can reach, or come at theſe Tables, and write in them. And God doth not as Men, write Syllables, and Words, but he writes new Principles, Habits, Diſpoſitions, and Inclinations; he writes Light in the Mind, and Love in the Will. Conſider of theſe three glorious Effects of the power of God, That <hi>he ſpeaks Creatures, breathes Souls, writes new Principles and Inclinations in the Soul.</hi> The power of God gloriouſly ſhines in the Work of Creation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That he made all things out of nothing. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.3. <hi>Things which are ſeen, were not made of things which do appear.</hi> That is, They were made out of nothing. There did not appear any eternal Firſt Matter, out of which God made all things. Other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts do not make their Matter, but they muſt have it made to their Hands, but God made all things out of nothing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God made all things: By the Word of his Power, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. <hi>were the heavens made, and all the hoſt of them, by the breath of his mouth.</hi> Pſal. 33.9. <hi>He ſpake, and it was done; he commanded, and it ſtood faſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. God made all things without any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant or Heiper, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.24. <hi>I am the Lord that maketh all things, that ſtretcheth forth the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:35650:39"/>Heaven alone, that ſpreadeth abroad the Earth by my ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. There was none that invented a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, or drew a Scheme or Draught, to direct God to Work by.</p>
               <p n="4">4. None gave God Counſel, or Inſtructed him, what he ſhould do, or how he ſhould Work. <hi>Who hath directed the ſpirit of the Lord, or being his counſellor hath taught him? With whom took he counſel, and who inſtructed him, and taught him in the path of judgment, and taught him knowledge, and ſhewed to him the way of understanding?</hi> Iſa. 40.13, 14.</p>
               <p n="5">5. God <hi>hangs the earth on nothing,</hi> Job 26.7. This amazed <hi>Ariſtotle, (de Mundo.)</hi> That if you did throw up a clod of Earth into the Air, it would not hang there; and that yet, the whole Globe of the Earth, and Water, ſhould hang in the Air, and all things be born up by the Word of God's power, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. It is ſaid of God, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.4. <hi>In his hand are the deep places of the earth.</hi> God's Hand carries the whole Globe of the Earth; its Foundation is laid in his Hand, and is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There is a daily ſtrong confirmation of the Hiſtory of the Creation, and ſuch an
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35650:40"/>evident demonſtration of the power of God, it plainly appears that it is true, That all things came from nothing at firſt, becauſe they daily ſpring, and riſe from ſuch ſmall, contemptible beginnings, as are next kin to nothing: As that from an Acron ſhould grow an Oak of above twenty four Tun of Timber. In the <hi>New Foreſt</hi> it is ſaid there was cut an Oak, that Top, Lop, Root, and Body, was eight and twenty Tun of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. That from a ſmall Grain of Muſtard-Seed, ſuch a Tree ſhould grow as Chriſt ſpeaks of, <hi>Matt.</hi> 13.31, 32.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Creatures declare the Wiſdom of God: That out of a Chaos, without Form, Beauty, or Order, God ſhould draw forth, and raiſe ſo beautiful a World. <hi>Athenagoras</hi> (in his <hi>Legat. for the Chriſtians</hi>) tells us, That <hi>Plato</hi> called the World <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Art of God.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> uſes a Word much to the ſame Senſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. <hi>The World,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in the Wiſdom of God;</hi> that is, in the Frame of Heaven and Earth, in which the Wiſdom of God doth ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſhine, by their Natural Wiſdom, or Underſtanding, did not know God. The Wiſdom of God appears in the making of the World.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:35650:40"/> 1. In making ſuch various ſorts of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Sixteen hundred ſorts of Herbs are ſaid to grow in <hi>England;</hi> and four thouſand diſtinct Vegetables, Plants, and Trees, are reported to be, and grow in the Phyſick Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Oxford.</hi> None but an Infinite Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding could form the different Ideas of ſo many thouſands of ſorts of Flowers, Trees, Birds, Beaſts, and Fiſhes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Objects ſhould be ſo exactly fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Senſes of Men; Colours to the Eyes, fragrant Smells to the Noſe, ſweet and grateful Reliſhes to the Taſte, Sounds to the Ear; this could not be a Work of Chance, but of Infinite Wiſdom.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That God ſhould form ſeveral Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, one higher than another, and ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate to another. God is ſaid to build his Stories in the Heaven, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.6. There is the loweſt, the middle, the higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, as ſeveral Stories, in a great and high Building; ſo God buildeth up Stories of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures on the Earth. There are Plants that are the loweſt Story, Beaſts that are a higher Story, and Man that is the higheſt Story in this lower World; and theſe are ſubſervient to each other. The Plants and Graſs ſeed the Beaſts, and Beaſts do nouriſh Men; and they ſhould devote themſelves to the Service and Worſhip of God.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:35650:41"/> 4. That God ſhould put ſuch Shapes and Signatures on Herbs, to ſhew ſomething, what they were made, and are good for. <hi>Eye-bright</hi> hath the figure and ſhape of an Eye, and is an excellent Herb to cure the Maladies of the Eye. <hi>Pimpernel</hi> hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like the Plague-ſpots under its Leaves, and is of excellent Virtue againſt the Plague.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That Herbs, proper to cure Diſeaſes, do naturally grow in the Country, where the Diſeaſe reigns: As <hi>Scurvy-graſs</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and in other Northern Countries, doth ſpring up Naturally. And yet an Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment hath been made, and much Art uſed, and Care taken, to Plant and Cultivate <hi>Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy-Graſs</hi> in ſome parts of <hi>France,</hi> where the Diſeaſe is not known, and it would not grow.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Some Herbs do Figure the Part that they are good to Heal: As Adders-Tongue, Hearts-Tongue, Rib-wort, Wood-Sorrel, that hath the ſhape of a Heart, is accounted a good Cordial Herb.</p>
               <p n="7">7. How doth God's Wiſdom appear in placing the Sun, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.4. In the Heaven God is ſaid to have made a Tabernacle, or Dwelling-place for the Sun. That part of the Heavens that is between the two Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:35650:41"/>of <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> in which the Sun ſtill moves, or is, may be ſtiled the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of the Sun.</hi> This is wonderful Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that the Sun ſhould be ſo ſituated in the midſt of the Heavens, to communicate Light and Heat to the whole World ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively: That the Sun never goes beyond the Tropicks, but doth in ſo orderly a way re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to us again, and obſerve ſuch an exact Courſe in the lengthning or ſhortning of the days, the Sun doth not Riſe or Set two days in the ſame place. God puts this Queſtion to <hi>Job,</hi> Job 38.12. <hi>Haſt thou commanded the morning? Haſt thou cauſed the day-ſpring to know its place?</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.19. The Sun know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his going down. The Sun doth Riſe and Set in different places every day, yet it is ſaid to know the place of its Riſing and Setting, as if it had a Principle of Reaſon and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that the Days and Heat ſhould increaſe and decreaſe, in ſuch a ſtated courſe. That we do not paſs from the extremity of Cold into the ſcorching Heat of Summer, but through a Spring, that doth partake of Gold and Heat mixed: And that we do not paſs out of the heat of the Summer, into the extremity of Winter cold, but through an Autumn, that hath a mixture of ſome heat and cold. This is wonderful Wiſdom, that God hath clothed and beautified the Sun with ſuch a glorious Garment of Light, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:35650:42"/>19.5, 6. <hi>Which is as a Bridegroom coming out of his chamber;</hi> that God hath given him ſo ſwift a motion, that he <hi>rejoyceth as a ſtrong man to run a race. His going forth is from the end of the heaven, and his circuit unto the ends of it.</hi> O how wonderful is God's Wiſdom and Power, to make a Sun that ſhould run round the World every day with ſo ſwift a motion! That God ſhould furniſh the Sun with ſo great a heat, that it is ſaid there is nothing hid from the heat of it! It pierces even to the Roots of Plants and Trees, and reaches into the bowels of the Earth. This alſo is wonderful, That the Sun riſing every Morning, doth give a new ſtamp and beauty to the Earth, and the Creatures in it, <hi>Job</hi> 38.13, 14. <hi>The day-light takes hold of the ends of the earth;</hi> that is, <hi>the earth is turned as clay to the ſeal.</hi> The Light is as a Seal that ſtamps the Earth; the Earth by darkneſs loſeth its luſtre, (for then we cannot diſcern it) but by the Morning light doth (as to our ſenſe) recover a new luſtre, as if Clay were new ſtamped, and received a new impreſſion by a Seal: and as if the Earth were decked with a new Garment, and variety of Ornaments, and had a new beauty and luſtre put on it. <hi>Manifold are Gods works, and in wiſdom he hath made them all,</hi> Pſal. 104.24.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:35650:42"/> 5. The Goodneſs of God eminently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the making of the Creatures. The <hi>earth is full of the goodneſs of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 33.5. The Earth is ſaid to be full of the Mercy of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.64. The <hi>Lord is good to all, and his tender mercies are over all his works,</hi> Pſal. 145.9. This was wonderful Goodneſs, that God prepared a place for Mans Habitation before he was made. God commanded the Waters to be gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into one place, and the dry Land to appear, that Man might have a place of Abode: <hi>The waters ſtood above the mountains, they covered all,</hi> Pſal. 104.6, 7, 8. But God rebuked this as a diſorder; he gave forth a thundering Command to the Waters, at which they fled, and haſted away. Two things here are obſervable:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God brake up a deep and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low place in the Earth, large enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſuch vaſt quantities of Waters, <hi>Job</hi> 38.10. <hi>I brake up for it my decreed place,</hi> that the Earth ſhould ſink ſo deep as to entertain theſe huge Treaſures of Waters. It is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what probable, that as the Earth was depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo low in ſome places, ſo it did propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably ſwell, and riſe high in other places. The low Valley, in which the deep Sea doth lie, is anſwered by high Mountains, that aſcend ſo much above the plain ground.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35650:43"/> 2. This is obſervable, That God ſhut in the Sea; he ſets bars and doors. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Sea, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come, but no further; and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed,</hi> Job 35.10, 11. This is wonderful Power and Goodneſs, for God to Park in, and Incloſe, ſo wild and furious a Creature as the Sea is; and when its Waves riſe to be as high Mountains, God is ſaid to tread on the Waves of the Sea, <hi>Job</hi> 9.8. And God treads theſe ſwelling and mountainous Waves into a Plain when he allys the Wind; cauſeth the Storm to ceaſe, and makes a Calm. God hath ſet a bound, that they may not paſs over; that they turn not again to cover the Earth. The ſand is fixed as a bound to this furious Creature <hi>by a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual decree,</hi> Jer. 5.22.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is more Goodneſs, that reſtrains the Waters that are over our Heads: <hi>God binds up the waters in his thick clouds, and the clouds are not rent under them,</hi> Job 26.8. We dwell between two Seas, a Sea below, and a Sea in the Clouds. There are vaſt quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Waters in the Clouds, that would fall down and overwhelm us, did not the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God bear them up. For this reaſon, as well as others, Gods <hi>ſtrength</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>in the clouds,</hi> Pſal. 68.34.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:35650:43"/> 3. That God hath made ſuch variety, and abundance of Creatures, for Mans uſe: Bread to ſtrengthen, and Wine to chear his Heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. Birds, Beaſts, and Fiſhes, for his uſe. God did not make Man till he had ſtocked a Farm, and furniſhed a Houſe for him. <hi>The earth is full of Gods riches,</hi> Pſal. 104.24. which were made not to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, or enrich God, <hi>for he hath need of nothing,</hi> Acts 17.25. but Man was to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by being made Proprietor and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of this great Houſe and Farm.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That God ſhould ſo graciouſly ſhare, and divide the Sun, Moon, and Stars, and by turns communicate their light to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.19. The Sun ſhines to ſome, and makes a day with them, when it's night with others. The Sun gives a ſix Months day to ſome, and a ſix Months night to others; ſo the Moon and Stars do by turns afford light to ſeveral parts of the Earth.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That God hath made Beaſts for bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, to carry Men, and their Goods, up and down; to Draw and Plow their Ground. And God hath made other Beaſts, Birds and Fiſh, to feed Men.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That God hath not only made Herbs and Plants for Food, but alſo for Medicine,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35650:44"/>Healing of Diſeaſes, and Curing of Wounds.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the Earth doth not only ſerve us, with its ſurface and outſide, bearing under-Wood, Trees, Broom, Furzes, and Turf, but with its inſide, Heart and Bowels. There are ſeveral rich Mines, precious Stones, Peat and Coals, growing in the Bowels of the Earth for Fuel. The Earth ſerves us with its outſide and inſide, which ſhould oblige us to ſerve God with our Souls and bodies, with our Hearts and Lives.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Though particular Creatures, as Men, Beaſts, Birds, Fiſh, Flowers, Herbs, Trees, do die, yet God doth not ſuffer any Species of Creatures utterly to periſh, and be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, but new Creatures do ſpring up and riſe in the room of thoſe that decay and periſh, and ſo do fill up their place. <hi>Thou ſendeſt forth thy ſpirit, and they are created, thou reneweſt the face of the earth,</hi> Pſal. 104.30. God's Spirit gives Life to the Creatures, he brings forth a new Stock of Men, Beaſts, Birds, Trees, and Plants, ſo that God's great Farm is not left unſtocked and unfurniſhed; God may be ſeen and felt in his Creatures. Thoſe that do not ſee God's Glory, that do not adore his Wiſdom and Power, that do not admire his Goodneſs, deſerve to be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed out of the earth,</hi> and to ceaſe their being
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35650:44"/>here, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.4. yea, that Chriſt ſhould come in flaming Fire, to take Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on them for their Ignorance of God: That they cloſe their Eyes againſt ſuch a light as ſhines through the World, ſpreads and diffuſes it ſelf among all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Man was made to ſeek God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.26, 27. And God endued Man with a <hi>Life of Light,</hi> John 1.40. Taught him more than the Beaſts of the Earth, and made him wiſer than the Fowls of Heaven, <hi>Job</hi> 35.10, 11. and this was to fit Man to ask and inquire after God. Every Rational Creature ſhould ſay, Where is God my Maſter, that gives Songs in the Night? God did not breathe a Soul into Man, that he ſhould pant after the duſt of the Earth, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.7. but ſhould breathe and pant after God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Chriſt will come in flaming fire, to take Vengeance on thoſe that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Three things here I ſhall inſiſt upon: 1. I ſhall ſhew what the Goſpel is. 2. What it is to obey the Goſpel. 3. How great and heinous a ſin it is, not to obey the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What the Goſpel is, I Anſwer, It is not only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Promiſe, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Good News that this Promiſe is performed, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.32, 33. <hi>We declare unto you glad tidings, how that the promiſe, which was made unto the fathers, God hath fulfilled the ſame unto us their
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35650:45"/>children, in that he hath raiſed up Jeſus again.</hi> Theſe glad Tidings are brought by the <hi>Son out of the boſom of the Father,</hi> John 1.18. It is good News of the beſt Good, the ſweeteſt Feaſt, the richeſt Inheritance, the moſt Noble and Honorable Relation to God; and that when a Sentence of Death might have been dreaded, and an Eternal Vengeance felt. It is <hi>a Goſpel of grace,</hi> Acts 20.24. <hi>A Goſpel of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Eph. 13.1, 24. <hi>The goſpel of the kingdom,</hi> Matt. 4.23. Here is Salvation from the moſt dreadful Evils, the poſſeſſion of a glorious and everlaſting Kingdom, and all beſtowed in a way of pure Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What is it to obey the Goſpel: we read of obeying the Truth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. and what ſhall be the end of them that obey not the Goſpel of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. Theſe expreſſions of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Truth, and obeying the Goſpel, do ſeem to intimate that the Goſpel is ſomething more than a meer Promiſe. To obey the Goſpel, is to Believe and Repent; we muſt credit God's Teſtimony, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.17. Believe the Report he gives, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Gifts that he offers, elſe we reject the higheſt Mercy, and make God a Liar, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. if we believe not the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We muſt alſo Repent of our Sins. To be called to Repent of our Sins, and to have ſuch ſweet, great, and ſtrong Incouragements to Repent, is certainly Goſpel-grace. <hi>Muſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:35650:45"/>(on <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.5.) ſaith, He doth not preach the Goſpel that doth not preach Repentance. That Repentance is a Goſpel Duty, theſe three things do evidence and demonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a Call from an offended provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Husband, to return from our Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and to be Loyal to him. <hi>Thou haſt play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the harlot with many Lovers, yet return again to me, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 3.1. God acting ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Covenant of Works, would for ever divorce, and eternally puniſh Sinners for their Adulteries, not call 'em to be reconciled.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Call to Repentance is a Call from Chriſt as a Phyſician, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.12, 13. <hi>The whole have no need of a Phyſician; I am come to call ſinners to repentance.</hi> Chriſt in this acts as a Phyſician, in calling Sinners to Repentance, that they may be his Patients, and that he may heal and recover them from their Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Call to Repentance flows from God, and Chriſt as a Shepherd: He ſeeks out that which was loſt, and brings back that which was gone aſtray, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.10. Theſe are Acts proper to Chriſt as a Shepherd, and therefore Repentance muſt needs be a Duty of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.8. <hi>I will hiſs for them, and gather them, for I have redeemed them.</hi> Here is a plain Alluſion to the Shepherds hiſs, to gather the Sheep that are ſcattered; and he gathers them, becauſe he hath Redeemed them. This ſtill more evidences, that a Call to Repentance is grounded on the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:35650:46"/> 3. <hi>I ſhall ſhew you what a heinous Sin it is not to obey the Goſpel.</hi> 1. The Goſpel requires us to be reconciled to God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. O what Mercy is it, that Reconciliation is poſſible; we could not be Reconciled but by the death of God's Son. We could not be healed but by his ſtripes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. God could not make Peace with us, but he muſt make War with his Son, <hi>Zech</hi> 13.7. <hi>Awake, O ſword, againſt my ſhepherd, and ſmite the man that is my fellow.</hi> Devils are not invited to be Reconciled, the blind Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then World are not called to be Reconciled. Let Heaven and Earth be Witneſs and Judge, whether it be not reaſonable that Sinners ſhould be reconciled to God; that is Love, and Goodneſs, that never did them any wrong; that is their Creator, Preſerver, and Benefactor: Is not the enmity of Men unjuſt, fooliſh, and pernicious to themſelves? Shall Graſhoppers leap up againſt Heaven? <hi>Iſ.</hi> 40.22. Shall Worms, <hi>Job</hi> 25.6. contend with the Almighty? Shall Potters Veſſels challenge a Rod of Iron? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. Shall Stubble and Chaff, Briers and Thorns, ſet themſelves in Battle againſt devouring Fire? Hath God found out a way to appeaſe his own wrath? <hi>Iſ.</hi> 27.4, 5. To cut off his own plea and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages againſt us? <hi>Nahum</hi> 10.3. To end the dreadful Controverſie between Heaven and Earth, and to ſheath his glittering Sword, and will you yet perſiſt in your enmity,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35650:46"/>and continue the War againſt God? Do you reſolve to pluck down his wrath and vengeance on you? Will the ſhort, momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary pleaſures of Sin, countervail eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? When God calls you to be Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, what is contained in it, but that you ſhould lay down your weapons of Hoſtility, and lay hold on Chriſt's atoning Sacrifice, as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly means of Reconciliation? O ſhall not your Scum go out of you? Shall not your Droſs be ſeparated from you? Shall not all the Tranſgreſſions be caſt away by you? Should you not return to your place, ſubmit, and be ſubject to God? You muſt turn from your Iniquity, God will never change and depart from his Holineſs. 2. The Goſpel calls men to be Eſpouſed to Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.8. The little Siſter, that is, the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> are ſaid to be ſpoken for; that is, to give her Heart to, and ſet her love on Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. Chriſt doth wooe you to be joined to him, to give your ſelves to him, and to be his, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. Is not Chriſt the moſt beautiful, rich, loving, and glorious Bridegroom? Can you find any other Match, that may compare with him? <hi>He is fairer than the children of men,</hi> Pſal. 45.2. He is white, and ruddy, and the chiefeſt of ten thouſands, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. <hi>He hath unſearchable riches,</hi> Epheſ. 3.8. He is love it ſelf, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.5. All power in Heaven and Earth is given to him. He was dead, but he is alive, and lives for
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35650:47"/>more, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.15. He will never put you away or leave you a deſolate diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Widow. Is it not amazing, that Beauty ſhould wooe Deformity? Riches ſolicit Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty? Nobility ſuit Vileneſs and Baſeneſs, and yet be rejected? If you match not with Chriſt, who ſhall pay your Debts? Protect and cover you from Arreſts? Who ſhall make you a Jointure, or provide you a Houſe and Home in another World? Who ſhall waſh away your Guilt and Filth? Supply your Wants? Cloth and Cover your Nakedneſs? If Jeſus Chriſt be not your Husband, will you ſtill dote on baſe and beggarly Objects? Will you ſtill go a Whoring from God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.27. Will you continue <hi>Aholah,</hi> dwelling in your own Tent, and broken off from the Houſe of God? Thoſe that ſlight, and ſpurn at Chriſt's love, are they not worthy to feel the ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire of his wrath? Carnal Creatures do not love a Spiritual Bridegroom; they ruſh into the embraces of carnal and preſent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but Souls conſider not they muſt ſhortly be ſnatched out of the boſom of beloved Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, muſt be ſeparated from them, and be for ever puniſhed for their Adulterous Embraces of them. 3. <hi>It is a heinous ſin not to be willing to be Chriſt's Patients.</hi> He is a Phyſician, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.12. His Blood is a Soveraign Medicine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the guilt of Sin, his Spirit is a mighty Antidote againſt the power of Iniquity. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35650:47"/>was there ſuch a Phyſician as Chriſt, that did Die to provide the Medicine, and then roſe again, and viſits the Dead to apply it, <hi>John</hi> 5.25. None can viſit and recover the Dead but Jeſus Chriſt; but who regards, or minds, a cure for his Soul? Do not the wounds of Sinners more rankle, feſter, and putrify? Do not their Diſeaſes grow ſtronger on 'em? Do not their Luſts root deeper? Yea, are not Sinners ſo blinded, that they think their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes to be Members neceſſary and profitable? How many do not account themſelves ſick, but rather whole? <hi>Matt.</hi> 9.12, 13. The Jews, thought themſelves to be ſound, and free from Spiritual Diſeaſes. This highly provokes Jeſus Chriſt, that on ſuch coſtly terms he became a Phyſician, and yet Men ſeel no want, or need of him, <hi>John</hi> 3.14, 15. Tho' our diſeaſes are dangerous, and threaten us with eternal Death; tho' the cure ſeems to be ſo eaſie, that Perſons may look to Chriſt, and be rid of the deadly Poyſon of the Old Serpent; a touch of Chriſt may heal the Spiritual Leproſie and our touching of Chriſt by Faith, may cauſe our iſſue of Blood to dry up, yet Sinners ſee not, know not the plague of their own hearts, they are pleaſed with their <hi>Dropſie,</hi> with <hi>Thirſt,</hi> their Feveriſh Fire, and burning Luſts; they think they ſhould be maimed, if their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers on Earth were cut off; and that their Lives would be uncomfortable, if bereaved
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35650:48"/>of the Pleaſures of Sin; tho' their condition without Chriſt be wholly deſperate, yet they will not part with their Diſeaſes, but languiſh under them, pine away in them, and die eternally.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is heinous Diſobedience againſt the Goſpel, that Men will not be Chriſt's Gueſts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.1, 2, 3. The <hi>Jews</hi> were invited to a Marriage-Feaſt, made by the Father for his Son Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. ult. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26. to partake of his Reſt, his Pleaſure, his Joy, his Glory; but Sinners make light of the Chear, tho' it be ſpiritual, ſuited to the nature and duration of the Soul; tho' it be ſatisfactory, and will make the Hearts of Men to live for ever, yet, as ſick Perſons, they abhor this dainty Meat, <hi>Job</hi> 33.20. They luſt after the Dainties of Carnal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, they are prepoſſeſſed with the love of the World, and ſo do haſten to the Feaſt that Satan bids them to, but they invent and make Excuſes to blind their own Minds, and harden their own Hearts, and to hold them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves back from this Feaſt; they lay out their Money for that which is not Bread, and their Labour for that which ſatisfies not; they muſt ſhortly fall under an eternal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min of all Good, and then muſt eat the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Fruit of their own ways and doings, and drink the Wrath of the Almighty. This is a heinous Sin, that Men will not come to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35650:48"/>Chriſt's Feaſt, 1. when they are not able to keep alive their own Souls, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.29. they have nothing to ſuſtain and ſupport their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and dying Souls, but, as the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, they are ready to periſh with Famine. 2. This is a Feaſt made on a Sacrifice, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſover is ſacrificed for us, let us therefore keep the Feaſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.6. How precious, how coſtly is this Feaſt! 3. It is a Feaſt of Marrow and fat things: here is Pardon and Juſtification thro' the Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that is in Jeſus Chriſt: here is Adoption, Salvation, a Kingdom of Glory; God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf will be the Father and Portion of thoſe that come to this Feaſt; here are Wines well refined from all droſs and dregs. 4. It is a Feaſt made <hi>for all Nations, Hedges are pluck'd up,</hi> and Incloſures are thrown open, this is a <hi>common Salvation, Iſa.</hi> 25.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. 5. Chriſt's Miniſters, as they are to pluck ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Sinners out of the Fire, ſo they are to ſtrive, and compel them to come in to the Feaſt, <hi>Jud.</hi> 23 <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This is affronting and highly provoking Diſobedience to the Goſpel, that Men will not traffick and trade with Chriſt, that they will not be Chriſt's Chapmen and his Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, when 1. Chriſt's Goods are excellent and neceſſary: We muſt be poor, without his Gold tried in the Fire; we muſt be ſhamefully naked, without his white Raiment;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35650:49"/>we muſt be eternally blind without his Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalve; we muſt ſtarve, if we do not eat of his good things, and delight our ſelves in the fat things offer'd: here is Milk for nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſpiritual Wine, as a moſt noble and generous Cordial; we may eat and not die, <hi>John</hi> 6.50. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.26. we may eat and be ſatisfied, and our <hi>Hearts will live for ever.</hi> 2. Theſe Goods are brought near, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Come down to the Waters,</hi> as Goods brought from a foreign Country to the Wharf, Key, or Shore of a Town or City; and ſome are ſent up into the City, to proclaim that the Goods are arrived, and are to be had at the Water-ſide: The Blood of Chriſt is the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> by which all Chriſt's ſpiritual Goods are imported into the World. 3. Chriſt keeps a Market for the Poor, and none but he doth ſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>buy Wine and Milk without mony and price.</hi> Trade is driven by Mony, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of Goods, but here neither Mony nor Price, we part with nothing that doth impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſh us or enrich Chriſt. If there were Markets and Fairs kept for the Poor here in the World, how would they be frequented? what flocking, what crowding would there be to get to ſuch Markets? yet how do Chriſt's goods lie by, as ſlighted and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! 4. Chriſt counſels us to buy of him, and his <hi>Counſel</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Command</hi> to us, and lay a Neceſſity on us, but (alas!) how ſtupid and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35650:49"/>ſenſleſs are Men, that provide no Treaſure for their Souls or Eternity? they have no <hi>Good</hi> to carry away with them, or to enjoy for ever, they ſeek not for their own things, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.12. but content themſelves with the things of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; ſo they are only Stewards, not Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors; <hi>Riches</hi> are the things of another, but <hi>Graces</hi> are our own things: but Sinners ſee not their own Wants and Poverty, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, prize not <hi>Chriſt's Riches</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Rev.</hi> 3.17. they are contented to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue poor, as deſtitute of an <hi>inherent,</hi> and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, as void of an <hi>imputed Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. This ſtirs up Chriſt's Anger againſt, and plucks down his Vengeance on Sinners, that when Chriſt comes near to them, knocks with Importunity, and waits with much Patience, yet they will not open to Chriſt; <hi>He came to his own, yet his own received him not, John</hi> 1.11. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.7. If <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his Body were on Earth, would not they be accounted very unkind and inhuman, that would not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and lodge <hi>Chriſt</hi> in their Houſes? But yet do not thouſands of nominal and titular <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhut <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of their Hearts? they ſuffer Sin, Satan, and the World to keep poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, but they ſhut out the Prince of Life, the King of Glory, the Heir of all things: they are not willing that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould come in, ſubject all to himſelf, order and govern all for himſelf: Guilt, Poverty, and Miſery
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35650:50"/>are ſhut into their Souls; Righteouſneſs, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Life are ſhut out.</p>
               <p n="7">7. This is grievous Diſobedience to the Goſpel, that Men are not willing to be made clean, or ſet free. 1. They are not willing to be made clean; <hi>As a Fountain caſteth out her waters, ſo</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>caſteth out her wickedneſs: O</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>wilt thou not be made clean?</hi> Jer. 6.7. When ſhall it once be? Is it not moſt reaſonable that Souls ſhould be made clean? yet they return as <hi>the Dog to his vomit, and as the Sow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. laſt. God pronounces woe to thoſe that will not be made clean, and will you deceive your ſelves, and ſay, it ſhall be well with you? <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells us, <hi>Except he waſhes us, we can have no part with him in the Kingdom of Glory,</hi> John 13.8. and will you give the Ly to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and credit <hi>Satan,</hi> that you ſhall go to Heaven tho' you are not waſhed? Can you thruſt into the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> into which no unclean thing ſhall enter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. laſt? Men ſometimes promiſe fair, and faintly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to cleanſe themſelves, but when ſhall it once be? they that cleanſe not away their Filth, muſt themſelves be waſhed away, as Spots from the Face of the <hi>Church,</hi> and be abhorred by God for ever. 2. Men are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſobedient to the Goſpel, in that they will not be made free; they are fond of their Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hug their Chains, as the Servant that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35650:50"/>rejected the benefit of the Year of Releaſe or Jubilee, ſaying, <hi>I love my Maſter, I will not go out free, Exod.</hi> 21.5, 6. So Men love <hi>Sin,</hi> their old Maſter; when a better choice is offer'd, they ſtick to their old and firſt choice; <hi>yea, they have choſen their own ways, and their Soul delights in their abominations,</hi> Iſa. 66.3. The moſt of Men are like the carnal <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with their Slavery: They ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Let us alone to ſerve the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.12. So Sinners would not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed, they would be let alone to ſerve the Devil, and enjoy their Luſts.</p>
               <p n="8">8. This is high diſobedience to the Goſpel, that Men will not have <hi>Chriſt</hi> to reign over them; they are <hi>incenſed,</hi> Iſa. 45.24. they rage againſt <hi>Chriſt, Luke</hi> 19.14, 27. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.1. but I may renew the Queſtion that <hi>Pilate</hi> put to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they were ſo inflam'd againſt <hi>Chriſt, What evil hath he done?</hi> Mat. 27.23. <hi>Chriſt</hi> calls Souls out of Priſon, and from their wandrings and ſtrayings, he makes Men free from the Law of Sin and Death, and is this to do Evil? how unreaſonable is it that Men ſhould be ſo diſaffected towards, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd againſt the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he reigns to deſtroy the reigning power of Sin, Satan, and Death, and to exalt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects now to reign with him in the Kingdom of Grace, and hereafter to ſit in the Throne, and reign with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Kingdom of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:35650:51"/>Glory. O that Sinners ſhould ever be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo injurious to their own Souls! how mild, benign, and gracious is the Government of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> he rules not only as a Political Head that gives Laws, but as a Natural Head that gives Life, and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; he governs as a Husband, Brother, and Saviour: how reaſonable therefore is it, that our homage and ſubjection to him ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in a Kiſs of Faith and Love? <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2. laſt. But how provoking is this, that Men chuſe Sin and Satan a Murtherer, and prefer him Before a Saviour? This is to renew and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the Affronts put on Chriſt at his Paſſion, and to chuſe <hi>Barabbas</hi> rather than <hi>Jeſus.</hi> Thoſe that would not have <hi>Chriſt</hi> to reign over them for their Salvation, do ſet up <hi>Satan</hi> to rule over them for their Deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This is ungrateful, and highly provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Diſobedience to the Goſpel, that Men would have Chriſt to buy, yet to poſſeſs and enjoy nothing: They can be willing Chriſt ſhould hire them, and promiſe them a reward, but they ſtand idle all the day long, will do no Work for Chriſt, they are idle, and barren in the knowledg of Chriſt, yea, walk as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Croſs of Chriſt, while they ſet up what he came to pull down, and keep alive what he came to deſtroy. Chriſt hath acted as a Shepherd, and doth demand his <hi>price, Zech.</hi> 11.12. Surely <hi>Love, Service,</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> is
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35650:51"/>due to him, but Men put off Chriſt with an empty Name of <hi>Lord,</hi> and with a dead form of Religion; they do not render the Fruits of a Vineyard, or bring forth the Fruits of God's Kingdom; their Knowledge is cold, idle and barren, as the light of a Glow-worm, that is not ſufficient to direct a Traveller in his way. The Goſpel ſhould bring forth Fruit, from the firſt day that Men know it, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.5, 6. it ſhould be a Seal, to ſtamp the Image of <hi>God</hi> on <hi>Men;</hi> it ſhould be a Mould, to ſhape and faſhion Mens Hearts and Lives, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17. as the Sun riſeth, and <hi>Man goes forth to his work,</hi> Pſ. 104 23. ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> ariſeth and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in any Country, Men ſhould go forth to all the work of their <hi>heavenly</hi> calling; <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> ſhould not only float in the <hi>Head,</hi> or be impriſon'd in the <hi>Mind,</hi> but ſhould be a light to <hi>Mens Feet,</hi> and <hi>a Lamp to their Paths,</hi> Pſal. 119.105. But how many nominal <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do love darkneſs and hate the light? they ſtill love to <hi>wander,</hi> and in the broad day <hi>to follow Sin and Satan;</hi> they do nothing of all that God <hi>commands them;</hi> they only <hi>ſtray, and work Iniquity,</hi> and ſo deſerve to be caſt into <hi>outer darkneſs,</hi> Jer. 14.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.23, 30. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:35650:52"/>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:35650:52"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JEREMIAH IV. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For thus ſaith the Lord to the men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Break up your fallow Ground, and ſow not among Thorns.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the words we may obſerve, 1. a Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, the Lord: All Men ſhould have an Ear to liſten, when the Lord hath a Tongue to ſpeak. 2. The Perſons ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to, the Men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> 3. The Exhortation or Counſel given to them, <hi>Break up your fallow ground.</hi> Three things are to be remarked in theſe words, 1. That there were <hi>fallow grounds</hi> in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that were a People choſen to be holy to the Lord, and that might ſeem to themſelves a fruitful Field, a pleaſant and delightful Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. 2. This may alſo ſeem ſtrange, that they ſhould be call'd to <hi>break up their fallow ground.</hi> What an humbling, abaſing Expreſſion is this! they might think they had made a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in Religion, and were advanced far to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a ripe Harveſt of Righteouſneſs, and was not this to lower and ſet them back, to call on them to <hi>break up their fallow ground?</hi> as tho' they had yet done nothing, had not yet begun or done the firſt work in Religion, or taken the firſt ſtep in the way of God, but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35650:53"/>were to begin all anew, and ſet their hand to the Plough, <hi>to break up their fallow ground.</hi> 3. This is obſervable, that this Exhortation is given to the Men of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that were then the only Church of God: this intimates, that in the Church only there is the ſpiritual Plow, the Plow-men, and the right Seed to ſow the Soil, and no where elſe; there is a direction and dehortation, <hi>Sow not among Thorns.</hi> Some do think that if they hear Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, read the Scriptures and good Books, and do ſome Actions materially good, that this is Seed ſown for a Harveſt of Glory; but yet all is labour loſt, if the Ground be not cleanſed, if the Soul be not purified from baſe Luſts and Affections: theſe <hi>Thorns</hi> do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwarf, rob, ſtarve the good Seed, ſo that no Fruit is brought to perfection. Holy Duties do not ſanctifie a carnal Man, but are defiled by him. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.13, 14 they that are unclean themſelves do pollute all they meddle with; the Plague that is in the heart infects <hi>thoughts, intentions, words</hi> and <hi>actions,</hi> 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 18.38. The fore-skin of the Heart will carnalize all we meddle with, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. The words may vield us theſe two Doctrines; 1. That the Hearts of unregenerate Men are like to <hi>fallow Ground.</hi> 2. That it is their Duty to <hi>break up their fallow Ground.</hi> For the proſecuting of the firſt Doctrin, I ſhall ſhew why the Hearts of unregenerate Men are compar'd to <hi>fallow Ground.</hi> 1. A <hi>fallow Ground</hi> is that which once
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35650:53"/>was plow'd and ſow'd: Mankind in our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were once ſow'd with original Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, beautified with the Image of God, and eno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a divine life. The firſt Tables that <hi>Moſes</hi> receiv'd were the Work of God; and the Writing was the Writing of God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.16. The Writings and the Tables ſeem to be created together: ſo our firſt Parents had their Soil and ſpiritual Seed created together; the Tables and the Writing were fram'd at once; the Law of God was engraven on the Mind and Will of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eve:</hi> the Meal of the faculties of their Souls was always leaven'd with holineſs and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; Man's Soul was once ſowed <hi>by,</hi> and became a fruitful field <hi>to God.</hi> 2. This is implied, that now this holy Seed is killed or rooted out; as when Wheat and Barley is ripe and cut, the ſtalks and root dies, and it will never bring forth any more Wheat or Barley; ſo the Law of God is blotted out of, the Image of God defaced from, the Life of God extinguiſhed in our Souls, ſo that we ſhall never pleaſe God, or bring forth any acceptable Fruit to him, if we are not broken up and ſowed anew: our Souls are like the ſecond Tables that <hi>Moſes</hi> brought to God, meer blanks, till God doth again write his Law in them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As a <hi>fallow Ground</hi> ordinarily brings forth only Briars, Thiſtles, Thorns, and ſo is uſeleſs and unprofitable to the Husbandman; ſo our Nature is ſo void and deſtitute of what is good, ſo prone and inclinable to that which is evil, that they that are in the Fleſh cannot pleaſe God, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.9.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:35650:54"/>
               <hi>A corrupt Tree cannot bring forth good Fruit,</hi> Mat. 7.18. Original Sin dwells in us, it dwells alone, hath poſſeſſion of the whole Soul, and all its fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and it hath not only a Houſe, but a Throne in us naturally; it works in us all manner of <hi>Concupiſcence, Rom.</hi> 7.8. but in this Fleſh of ours dwelleth nothing that is good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. but <hi>the Spirit that dwelleth in us luſteth to envy</hi> and all unrighteouſneſs, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As a <hi>fallow Ground</hi> muſt be plow'd and ſow'd, elſe 'twill not bear Wheat, or yield Bread, ſo our Hearts muſt be broken, and ſowed with good Seed, elſe Holineſs will never root deep in the Heart, and ſpring up in the Life; we muſt have the Law of God written in us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33. we muſt have the <hi>Fear of God</hi> put into us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39, 40. and the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> Ezek. 36.27. or elſe we ſhall yield no Harveſt of Righteouſneſs or Obedience to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> 1. Be convinc'd of this, that you are a <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> that you have Souls poor and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty of that which is good, and that your carnal Minds are Enmity to God, are not ſubject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. yea, tho' in ſome ſence you may be ſaid to be ſowed, as the <hi>Highway-ground,</hi> the <hi>Stony,</hi> the <hi>Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ground</hi> were, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20, 21, 22. yet you may be ſaid ſtill to be a <hi>fallow,</hi> becauſe the Seed wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is ſtarved and choked, ſo that no Fruit is brought forth to pleaſe and delight the heavenly Husbandman.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Be humbled deeply for this, that you have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35650:54"/>ſo long continued a <hi>fallow,</hi> ſo that God hath had no Harveſt of Righteouſneſs, no ſheaves or glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of good Works: you have done nothing of all that God hath commanded you, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.23. have only done Evil, and wrought Iniquity, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.30. <hi>your thoughts have been only evil,</hi> Gen. 6.5. your words evil, <hi>How can a corrupt generation ſpeak good things,</hi> Mat. 12.34? your actions evil, <hi>a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Tree bringeth forth corrupt Fruit,</hi> Matt. 7.17. The Prodigal that went into a far Country did neither perform ſervice to his Father, nor enjoy communion with him, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Do not remain a <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> it will be ſad to enjoy no good hereafter, for God to reap no Fruits of Righteouſneſs from you, and you to reap no fruits of Mercy from him: therefore be not contented to lie in the ruines of your Falls, and not to be better'd or benefited at all by the Word of Grace, the Goſpel of Reconciliation: It will be bad for the Founder to <hi>melt in vain, Jer.</hi> 6.29. Becauſe wickedneſs is not ſeparated from you, and you refined from your Droſs, it will be ſad for Chriſt and his Miniſters to labour in vain, becauſe you are not gather'd in; for the Dew and Rain to come often on you, and yet you bring forth only Briars and Thorns, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. O conſider theſe following things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Your <hi>fallow Ground</hi> is capable of manuring and improvement; as <hi>Iſaac</hi> by plowing and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Canaan</hi> did make a great advantage to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; that Land which before did only yield Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage, and feed his Flock, did now bear Corn, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35650:55"/>did nouriſh himſelf and his large Family; he ſow'd in that Land, and receiv'd in the ſame year an hundred fold, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.12. that is, he had reap'd a hundred buſhels of Corn for one that he ſow'd: how was the ground advanc'd, from feeding Cattel, to feed <hi>Iſaac</hi> and his Family! ſo how is a Soul exalted and enobled by ſpiritual Tillage, by being plow'd and ſow'd! it brings forth Fruit for Chriſt to gather and eat; <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. ult. <hi>Let my beloved come into his garden, and eat of his pleaſant fruits.</hi> Acts of moral Juſtice may profit Men, may be beneficial to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth and human Society, yet if they flow not from a ſpiritual Spring, grow not on the root of love to God, they do not pleaſe God, they are not accepted with him: The Fathers (as <hi>Voſſius</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> tells us) did call theſe <hi>Opera Sterilia, barren Works,</hi> becauſe they had no tendency to, no influence on Eternal Life: but if you <hi>break up the fallow Ground,</hi> are renew'd by and ſow to the Spirit, you may <hi>receive in this life an hundred fold,</hi> and at laſt reap and inherit <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life,</hi> Mat. 10.29. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Judgment may dwell in your Wilderneſs,</hi> Iſa. 32.16. and you that were formerly altogether unprofitable, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Philemon</hi>'s <hi>Epiſt.</hi> may become profitable, highly ſerviceable to God, greatly beneficial and uſeful to Men; unclean Creatures may be waſhed, old and corrupt Creatures may be renew'd, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider how bad it will be not to be plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſowed: This is threatned as a terrible Judgment, That <hi>the Land of</hi> Canaan <hi>ſhould keep
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35650:55"/>its Sabbaths as long as it lies deſolate and ceaſeth from Tillage.</hi> Is it bad for the Ground to lay deſolate, to keep a Sabbath, to ceaſe from Culture? how much worſe is it for the Soul to keep its Sabbaths, (not holy, but) carnal and prophane Sabbaths, while God's Plow doth not <hi>break it up,</hi> nor his Seed be ſow'd in it? Men then will be <hi>far from Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 46.12. will ſerve divers Luſts and Pleaſures, and be without God in the <hi>World, they will chuſe their own ways, and their Souls de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in their abominations.</hi> The Adverſaries of the <hi>Jews,</hi> in the <hi>Babyloniſh.</hi> Captivity, ſaw their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, and mocked at them, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.7. but the great Enemy of Souls will rejoyce at the idle and prophane Sabbaths that wicked men keep, when they ceaſe to do good, and leave off <hi>Righteouſneſs in the Earth,</hi> Amos 5.7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are not broken up and ſowed, will be Satan's Poſſeſſion; as he claims Strays as his, ſo he is the Lord of <hi>fallow Ground; Such are of their Father the Devil, and his luſts they will do, John</hi> 8.44. It is ſweet and honourable to be God's Husbandry, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. but how dreadful is it to be Satan's Husbandry! Satan will ſtill be working in them, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. and filling of their Hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3. he will be ſowing, planting, and grafting in and on them; he will tutor his Nurſery by continual ſuggeſtions and temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Satan will ſtill be ſerving his turn on, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting his intereſt by, and accompliſhing bis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in Souls that lye <hi>fallow:</hi> how bad will it be to keep Sabbaths, as reſting from ſpiritual til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35650:56"/>This is to keep Sabbaths to gratifie and worſhip Satan; theſe Sabbaths are working days to pleaſe the Fleſh, and rejoyce the Devil; ſuch do the Devil's Will in time, and if Grace doth not prevent, they muſt ſuffer God's Will to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe that are as a <hi>fallow Ground</hi> do bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoke God to anger, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12. laſt, <hi>They bring forth Grapes of gall, their cluſters are bitter,</hi> Deut. 32.33. Can the heavenly Husbandman feed on and delight in ſuch Grapes? doth not his Soul loath and abhor them? but as to good Grapes, are they not <hi>empty Vines?</hi> Hoſ. 10.1. Theſe <hi>fallow Grounds</hi> are like the barren Fig-tree; <hi>Chriſt</hi> hungred and came to this Fig-tree, and found nothing on it but Leaves; this ſo provoked <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he curſed it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.18, 19. <hi>and ſaid unto it, Let no fruit grow on thee henceforward for ever;</hi> and preſently the Fig-tree wither'd away. In what danger are Souls that are barren Fig trees? <hi>Chriſt</hi> may curſe <hi>them</hi> ſo, that their Leaves may wither, their form of Religion decay and be utterly loſt, a Sentence may go forth againſt them, <hi>Cut them down, why ſhould they any longer cumber the ground? Luke</hi> 13.7. Thoſe that are not Trees for Fruit, ſhall be Trees for Fuel; <hi>The Tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and caſt into the fire,</hi> Mat. 3.10. The Ground that after Rain and Dew have come often on it, and yet it <hi>bringeth forth only Briers</hi> and Thorns, it is nigh to <hi>curſing,</hi> and its end is <hi>to be burnt,</hi> Heb. 6.8.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:35650:56"/> 4. If you continue a Fallow Ground, you will bring forth Fruit only to Death, and fit your ſelves for Deſtruction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5. You will pile up fuel in the Infernal Tophet, and fill the Treaſury of God's wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. as the cluſters are bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſo abhorred by God, ſo your Wine is the Poyſon of Dragons, and the cruel venom of Aſps, and ſo moſt fatal, pernicious and deſtructive to your ſelves. As Men now <hi>drink in iniquity like water,</hi> Job 15.16. ſo they muſt ſhortly <hi>drink of the wrath of the Almighty,</hi> Job 21.20. O therefore cry mightily to God, that he would remember you in your miſerable and loſt Eſtate. There is a ſweet Promiſe that God makes to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Ezek. 36.8, 9. <hi>Behold I am for you, and I will turn unto you, and you ſhall be tilled, ſown, and yield your Fruit.</hi> O plead this word with God, put him in remembrance of it: Confeſs you have long lain Fallow. Perhaps ſome of you have kept a Sabbath of Years; yea, are come to a great Sabbatical Year. Forty nine or Fifty Years you have ceaſed from Spiritual Tillage; you have been idle all this while and done no work for God; you have been barren, and have brought forth no Fruit to God; O will you not now ſend up ſtrong cries to Heaven? Will you not now wreſtle mightily with God, that he would be for you, and turn to you in Grace and Mercy, that you may be effectually filled, skilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſown, and plentifully bear Fruit to God?</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>It is the Duty of Unregenerate Men to break up their Fallow Ground: They ſhould not be
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35650:57"/>idle, or ſtand ſtill, or be contented with their preſent Barrenneſs, that God, who calls you to Act, can breathe Life, and put Strength into you, to enable you to work. As God in the firſt Creation ſpake to the Earth, and ſaid, Let it bring forth Graſs, Herbs, and Fruit-bearing Trees, and it was ſo as the Father commanded, and the Son was the Word; ſo the Holy Ghoſt executed all. The Earth had no Seed of Graſs, or Herbs, or Roots of Trees, within it ſelf, or power to bring them forth, yet Gods Word was as Seed then, and gave a productive Power to the Earth: So God ſaid,</hi> Let the waters bring forth Fiſh to move in them, and Fowl that may fly above the waters and earth, in the open Firmament of Heaven; <hi>and tho' the waters had no ſpawn of Fiſh, or Eggs of Fowl in them, yet the Word of God was powerful, effectual, and ſoon fulfilled. So Chriſt is the Reſurrection and the Life, and the beginning of the Creation of God; he can quicken dead Souls, recover and heal a withered arm and hand,</hi> Mark 3.5. <hi>ſo that it ſhall be ſtretched out, and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to hold the Plough, and carry on this Spiritual Tillage, that is required and called for in the Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the proſecuting of the Doctrine, three things are to be inquired into. 1. What it is to break up our Fallow Ground. 2. How, or by what means it muſt be broken up. 3. Why it is neceſſary it ſhould be broken up.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What is it to break up our Fallow ground?</hi> I Anſwer: It is to be ſoundly convinced of, deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with, throughly to be broken and humbled for Sin, and the danger and miſery of our Natural State. This is a Work hard, bitter,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35650:57"/>and grievous to Nature, to ſet God's Plow into our very Souls; to cut and wound them, to make deep and long Furrows in the very Soil of our Hearts. We read of <hi>renting of the heart,</hi> Joel 2.13. and of a <hi>broken heart and contrite ſpirit,</hi> Pſ. 51.17. This <hi>breaking up Fallow Ground,</hi> is expounded in the next Verſe to the Text, by <hi>mens circumciſing themſelves to the Lord, and taking away the foreskin of the heart.</hi> Jer. 4.4. This cutting off the foreskin of the Heart, is cutting up the Turff of our Soil, that hinders the good Seed from taking deep root downwards, and ſpringing upwards. The <hi>Jews</hi> were circumciſed in Infancy, but the thing ſignified doth not always go along with the Sign, they yet wanted the internal and nobleſt part of that Ordinance, they were circumciſed in fleſh, but yet <hi>uncircumciſed in heart,</hi> Jer 9. laſt. Tho' Circumciſion in the Fleſh was an external act, whereby Men did acknowledge them <hi>Jews,</hi> and Members of the viſible Church, yet the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the Heart is the Sign, and internal Note, whereby God doth recognize, and own Men to be vital Members of his Church. <hi>The Lord thy God will circumciſe thine heart, that love the Lord thy God,</hi> Deut. 30.6. God would give the inward and nobleſt part of this Ordinance. And if Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was a Sign and Seal of God's Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing the Heart, it muſt needs be a Sign and Seal of the Covenant of Grace. Thoſe that do partake of the outward Sign of the Covenant, are thereby obliged to ſeek after the inward, and beſt part of that Ordinance they have paſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35650:58"/>and have been the Subjects of. They are not to reſt in this, That they are circumciſed in the Eye, and account of Men, but they are to paſs further, and circumciſe themſelves to the Lord; that is, ſo to circumciſe themſelves, that they may appear to, and be owned by God as circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. So they were to circumciſe themſelves, that they may be inclined towards, and devoted to the Lord. This Soul Circumciſion, this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the Foreskin of the Heart, is the right <hi>breaking up of our Fallow Ground.</hi> The Act of Repentance and Faith is ours, but the Grace whereby we Repent and Believe, is from God and Chriſt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. So it is our Duty to Circumciſe our Hearts, but in all our Endeavours to perform it, we muſt look to the Promiſe of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. and eye the Grace of our Lord Jeſus, who circumciſes the Heart, in cauſing it to put off the Body of the ſins of the Fleſh, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11. Jeſus Chriſt, tho' he had no Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin on his Heart, yet he was Circumciſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.21. that he might fulfil all Righteouſneſs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and be obliged by this Ordinance to the great Work of Circumciſing the Hearts of others, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How muſt Men break up their Fallow Ground?</hi> I Anſwer: There muſt be a Plough to do this Work: There muſt be a keen and ſharp Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhare, that Men may be Converted, and return to be God's Husbandry. The Word is the Plow, conſiderations taken both from the Law and Goſpel, muſt break and wound the Hearts of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35650:58"/>Men. <hi>Moſes</hi> is indeed a Plow-man, but Chriſt is ſaid to be the Seeds-man; he is the <hi>Sower that went forth to ſow,</hi> Matt. 13.3. He that <hi>ſows the good ſeed is the Son of Man,</hi> Matt. 13.37, 38. He doth not only ſow Doctrines, but Perſons. He doth beget a holy Seed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. He waſhes and renews by his Spirit. If Men were convinced of Sin by the Law, and not of Righteouſneſs by the Goſpel; if they were wounded, but had no knowledge of a Phyſician, of a Remedy, of a way of <hi>Salvation,</hi> this would drive Men to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, ſink and overwhelm them with terrors. The Word muſt cut deep, it <hi>muſt prick the heart,</hi> Acts 2.37. It muſt wound the Soul to the quick, that Men may be prepared for the healing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and ſweet Conſolations of Jeſus Chriſt: Weighty, humbling, awakening Conſiderations, muſt be put, and kept on the Heart, and ſink deep into the Soul; ſuch as theſe following Truths.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſhould affect and wound the Heart, that as we deſcend from the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> we are all born Fleſh. <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>That which is born of the ſheſh, is fleſh.</hi> Tho' the Soul be a ſpirit in its nature, yet it is fleſh in its inclination, diſpoſition, ends, and aims. What a debaſing, humbling expreſſion is that, <hi>My ſpirit ſhall not always ſtrive with man, for that he alſo is fleſh,</hi> Gen. 6.3. The Mind of Man is ſtrangely Carnalized, ſunk into, and ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in the Fleſh; it doth not mind its own Concerns, or remember its own Intereſt, it is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſervant to, a <hi>Steward</hi> and <hi>Caterer</hi> for the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; as if a Man ſhould be wholly taken up in
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35650:59"/>thatching, ſupporting, repairing of his Cottage, but ſhould neglect or forget to provide Food and Raiment for himſelf. O that Men ſhould gratify their ſenſes, pleaſe, pamper, and indulge their Fleſh, and put all their happineſs on an inch, on a moment of Time, and not regard <hi>Spiritual Bleſſings in Heaven,</hi> Eph. 1.3. or value a Feaſt in Glory. How dreadfully bad is it to make light, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.5. of the Feaſt, that infinite Wiſdom contrived, and infinite Love hath provided? For Men not to regard the Purchaſe the <hi>Son of God</hi> hath made, the Ranſom he hath paid, the Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies he hath bequeathed. A Carnal Creature ſees no worth or excellency, taſtes no ſweetneſs, takes no deught in <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> Things; they are dry, ſapleſs, hungry Notions, yea, as vain fancies to him. Men underſtand only Carnally, there is fleſh in the mind, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> tho' he was a Maſter and Teacher in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet did not underſtand the Doctrine of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but thought Chriſt meant a Man muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſecond time into his <hi>Mothers Womb,</hi> and be born again from thence, <hi>John</hi> 3.3, 4, 9. The Will and Affections alſo are Fleſh. When Chriſt did diſcourſe with the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> of Water for her Soul, ſhe puts a Carnal ſenſe on Chriſt's words; ſhe deſires that Chriſt would give her of this water, that ſhe might come no more to that Well to draw, but might be eas'd of a great labour and trouble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Truth ſhould wound the Heart, That by Nature we are <hi>ſpiritually dead in ſins and treſpaſſes,</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:35650:59"/>Eph. 2.1, 4. not only ſick, but dead in ſin. That foreskin that is on our Hearts, is the very death of our Souls, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. <hi>You that were dead in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion of your fleſh.</hi> This foreskin diſaffects us to, alienates us from, prejudices us againſt God, and ſpiritual things. <hi>The body is dead by reaſon of ſin,</hi> Rom. 8.10. And the Soul is dead in ſin. By the offence of one, that is, the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> many be dead. Theſe many are all that deſcend from <hi>Adam</hi> by Natural Generation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.15. <hi>By the offence of one judgment came upon all men to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> Rom 5.18. Men are dead under a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, and condemned to an eternal death. Men walk indeed (tho' ſpiritually dead) but it is only contrary to God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.40. Men act indeed, but they only do dead Works, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. Men muſt repent of, and from theſe dead works, and the blood of Chriſt muſt cleanſe Conſcience from them. O what a dreadful State is this, for Conſcience to be loaded with, and burden'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dead Works! Thoſe may well be called dead Works, that are the fruits of ſpiritual Death, and the ſeeds of eternal Death; as we call Pond, or Ditch Water, dead Water, becauſe the Pond or Ditch have no ſpring in them to feed the Water, ſo the beſt Works of unregenerate Men may be called dead Works, becauſe they have no Holy Spring, or Fountain, of their Actions. They are deſtitute of Knowledge, <hi>there is none that underſtandeth,</hi> Rom. 3.11. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1. <hi>They do not truſt in God,</hi> Zeph. 3.2. <hi>They have not the love of God in them,</hi> John 5.42. Knowledge, Faith, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35650:60"/>Love, are the root and ſpring of all living works, but for want of theſe, the <hi>Works of unregenerate Men are dead,</hi> they are empty Vines, ſinfully bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.1. yet abound in corrupt fruit, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.32, 33. they only <hi>bring forth fruit to death,</hi> Rom. 7.5. ſuch as renders them more guilty of, liable, and obnoxious to death. When <hi>Adam</hi> fell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted guilt, and corrupted our nature; thence <hi>we were made ſinners,</hi> Rom. 5.19. and <hi>unregenerate men,</hi> while they continue ſo, ever ſince they were born, have been Sin-makers. This is their only Trade and Imployment, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; it is properly render'd, <hi>He that maketh ſin is the ſervant of ſin.</hi> The word in compoſition ſignifies to <hi>work at a Trade..Aquila, Priſcilla,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Tentmakers. This is a ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and woful Trade, in Thought, Word, and Deed, to be a <hi>Sin maker.</hi> O reflect on this with Self-abhorrency, that as ſoon as you were born you were made Sinners, and ever ſince have been <hi>Sin-makers.</hi> An <hi>unregenerate man, is ſtill out of the evil Treaſure of his heart bringing forth evil things,</hi> Matt. 12.34. Out of the Bullion of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> is ſtill coining <hi>Actual Sin;</hi> and tho' evil things in Words and Actions, are ſtill brought forth out of this <hi>evil Treaſure,</hi> yet this doth not leſſen, waſte, or diminiſh, but ſtill more increaſes the <hi>evil Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of the Heart.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Unregenerate Men are Children of Wrath by Nature,</hi> Epheſ. 2.3. <hi>They are conceived in ſin, ſhapen in iniquity,</hi> Pſ. 51.5. <hi>Born fleſh,</hi> John 3.6. God hath therefore a Controverſie with them, and juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35650:60"/>againſt them. As ſoon as they live Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, God hath provocations to deſtroy them Eternally; God ſeeth then the malignity that lurks, the enmity againſt him that is lodged in the Soul. As the Potters Veſſel, mentioned in <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.3, 4. was marred in making, ſo when men are ſhapen, and formed in the Womb, they are marred, defiled, and deformed with ſin; a Leaven is then laid in the very Meal of our Faculties, Poyſon is then dropt into our Souls: a Diſeaſe, a Plague of Leproſie, is derived to us, together with our Nature, ſo that we are hateful to, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 3.3. and haters of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. By reaſon of that Traiterous and Rebellious Nature that God then ſaw in us, it had been no injuſtice in God, or wrong to us, if Children of wrath had ſoon been <hi>made Veſſels of wrath for ever,</hi> Rom. 9.22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Sinful Men heap up more wrath, more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame, and increaſe Divine Diſpleaſure againſt themſelves. <hi>The Hipocrites in heart do heap up wrath,</hi> Job 36.13. Thoſe that remain hard-hearted, and impenitent, <hi>do treaſure up wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the revelation of the righteous judgment of God,</hi> Rom. 2.5. Such do bring more Fuel to the Fire, and Oil to the flame of Divine Diſpleaſure, that it may burn more hotly, and fiercely againſt them. God is <hi>angry with the wicked every day,</hi> or, as ſome render it, <hi>all the day long,</hi> Pſ. 7.11. They are ſtill doing ſomewhat more to grieve and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God. Sinners are altogether become filthy, or ſtinking, as it is in the margin, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. What ſtinking thoughts, deſires, words and actions, do
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35650:61"/>daily come up into God's noſtrils. God complains, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 65.5. that they were a <hi>ſmoke in his noſtrils, a fire that did burn all the day;</hi> as when ſomething very noiſom and ſtinking is burnt, it gives great offence to the Noſe. And as the ſins of men do always ſtink in God's Noſtrils, ſo they cry loud in God's Ears, to kindle more wrath againſt them, and pluck down more vengeance on them. As the ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi> did make a great cry in God's Ears, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.20. the ſins of men are as ſo many Accuſers of, and Witneſſes againſt them, before the Tribunal of God. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 59.12. <hi>Our ſins teſtifie againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Men are unmindful of God, and Enemies to him,</hi> 1. They are unmindful of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.18. <hi>Of the Rock that begot thee, thou art unmindful, and haſt forgotten God that formed thee.</hi> God is not in all their thoughts; they are <hi>without God in the world,</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. they call not on him, they draw not night to him; they have no delight in him. They are Atheiſts all the day long; yea, all their life long, as if there were no ſuch Being as God, or they had no need of him, had no buſineſs or concerns with him. Men and Women remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſmall matters, but yet forget God. <hi>Can a maid forget her ornaments, or a bride her attire? yet my people</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>have forgotten me days without number,</hi> Jer. 2.32. How great a ſin is it to forget God that is ſo near to us? <hi>Acts</hi> 27.27, 28. Thoſe that are blind Creatures, may grope, and find out God, by feeling of him; <hi>for in him we live, move, and have our being.</hi> All the Creatures do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35650:61"/>and preach God to us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3. Theſe, as continual remembrancers, may preſent God to our thoughts. How great a ſin is it, that men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low no room to God in their minds, and ſhut him out of their hearts, <hi>who fills heaven and earth?</hi> Jer. 23.24. That the precious Cabiner of the Mind ſhould be filled only with the Dung of unclean, vain, worldly thoughts, but not entertain Meditations of God and Chriſt. 2. <hi>Men are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God,</hi> Rom. 8.7. The Carnal Mind is not ſaid to be an enemy, but enmity to God. Enemies may be reconciled, but enmity can never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, but muſt be deſtroy'd. Men are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to God in their minds, through wicked works, or by <hi>their minds being ſet wholly on wicked works,</hi> Col. 1.21. The mind is either <hi>inventing of evil things,</hi> and finding out new ſins, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.30. or projecting and contriving how to juſtifie the fleſh, <hi>and to fulfil the luſts of it,</hi> Rom. 13. ult. Or the mind is taken up in cloaking and covering of ſin; it finds out excuſes, it ſews the Fig-leaves of Pretenſes together, to hide the filthineſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of ſin from the Eye of Conſcience, and ſo to blind and deceive their own Souls. How ſhould this afflict and wound our Souls, that we have been enemies to him, that is the chief good, to a glorious, infinite, eternal Being? who ſpake the World out of nothing, and could as eaſily ſpeak us, and all things elſe, into their Firſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing again? But becauſe men are ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this Charge, and plead not Guilty to it, <hi>Paul</hi> proves mens enmity againſt God, by their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35650:62"/>to, and rebellion againſt the Law of God. <hi>The carnal mind is not ſubject to the law of God, neither indeed can be,</hi> Rom. 8.7.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Men are Children and Captives of the Devil.</hi> 1. They are Children of the Devil. But Men will ſtart, and deny ſuch an Accuſation. The <hi>Jews</hi> affirmed, <hi>That God was their Father,</hi> John 8.41. but Chriſt aſſerted that which was very different from, and contrary to this, <hi>John</hi> 8.44. <hi>Ye are of your father the devil, and the luſts of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye will do.</hi> Was not Chriſt's Teſtimony to be credited rather than theirs? Tho' Men, as to their natural Life, proceed and deſcend from their Parents, yet as to their corrupt Life, they iſſue from Satan. The enmity, and malignity of their Souls againſt God, his People, and his Laws, this is the very image and likeneſs of Satan. The <hi>Jews</hi> hated the Truth that Chriſt preached, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred him, and were inclined to murder him; and theſe were the very Luſts of Satan. Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Gluttony, and Drunkenneſs, are groſs and brutiſh Luſts; but the moſt Spiritual ſins, as Pride, Envy, Hatred, are properly the Luſts of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. In theſe Men do moſt reſemble him; theſe are the very Lineaments of his Face. It is ſaid of wicked men, <hi>Pſal</hi> 58.4. <hi>That their poyſon is like the poyſon of a ſerpent.</hi> This ſeems to be a plain allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the firſt ſin: When the Devil under, and by a Serpent, tempted our Firſt Parents, then he did diſtil his Venom, and drop his Poiſon into them, when his word was believed, and his ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions embraced. He miſrepreſented God as
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35650:62"/>envious of their Good, of their higher Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of their ſweeteſt Pleaſures and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. He did ſet forth the Fruit of a Tree as the beſt, and moſt deſirable Good, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the favour of God, and as if God's threatning was but a vain, and falſe word. This Poiſon of the Serpent we may diſcern, and find in our own Souls, and therefore while <hi>unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> may be juſtly charged to the Satans Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yea, the Souls of Sinners are the Houſe that Satan dwells, and the Shop that he works in, <hi>they have Members,</hi> Col. 3.5. that God never made, they have <hi>Luſts that he never kindled,</hi> 1 John 2.15, 16. and are under a <hi>Law,</hi> Rom 7.21, 23. that God never enacted; but theſe Members, Luſts, and Law, came from Satan. 2. <hi>Unregenerate Men are the Devils Vaſſals, Slaves, and Captives.</hi> Satan did but preſent <hi>Job</hi>'s Cattle as a deſirable Booty and Prey, and blow up the Fire of their Luſts, and the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Sabeans</hi> quickly make an Inroad, Invade <hi>Job</hi>'s Poſſeſſion, and take away his Cattle, <hi>Job</hi> 1.15, 17. Satan carries Men on in the Chanel of their own corrupt Nature, and on the violent ſtream and torrent of their own Luſts. Men are ſaid to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Satan, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. but how is this? The Apoſtle tells us in the next Verſe, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2, 3. <hi>Fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind.</hi> They think they have nothing to do with Satan, when they obey him in ſerving of their Luſts. <hi>The Devil takes men captive at his will,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. laſt. yet he leads men captive by their own Wills.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35650:63"/>The very liberty of their Wills is inſlaved. Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners yield, and give up their own corrupt Wills, and carnal Affections, as ſo many Cords for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to lead them by to. Hell. Satan finds Luſts in us, as Chains to bind us, as Snares to hold us; ſhall not this conſideration deeply wound the Souls of Men, that they ſide and join with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, to ſeduce and deſtroy themſelves? <hi>Men cloſe their eyes,</hi> Matt. 13.15. And <hi>Satan blinds their minds,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.4, 5. and ſo they put the greateſt cheat on their own Souls. They ſee not the Good that Satan deprives them of, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and Deſtruction he brings on them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Unregenerate Men are Priſoners,</hi> Iſ. 42.7. Iſ. 49.9. <hi>they ſit in darkneſs;</hi> and <hi>are bound with chains,</hi> Iſ. 61.1. and dwell in the Priſon Houſe. They are under a ſentence of condemnation, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. <hi>He that believes not is condemned already.</hi> And they are under a fear of a day of Execution, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Through the fear of death they are all their life time ſubject to bondage.</hi> How much are Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Hipocrites affrighted? What dreadful Exclamations do they make? Who among us ſhall dwell with devouring Fire? Who among us ſhall dwell with everlaſting Burnings? O what bitter cries of deſtruction, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 35.5. will Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners lift up, when they ſhall ſee the whetted Sword of Juſtice hanging over their Heads, and their Feet at the brink of the bottomleſs Pit! <hi>When their eyes ſhall ſee their deſtruction, and they ſhall be brought forth to the day of wrath,</hi> Job 21.20, 30.</p>
            <p n="8">8. O let this wound your Souls, <hi>that you go ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35650:63"/>far from God,</hi> Jer. 2.5. <hi>and fly ſo faſt.</hi> Hoſ. 7.13. <hi>Woe unto them,</hi> 1. <hi>For they have fled from me;</hi> as if they could not go too far, or haſten too faſt, from the Father of Mercies, from the Fountain of Life. And Sinners are very unwilling to return; <hi>they hold faſt deceit, they refuſe to return,</hi> Jer. 8.5. <hi>They ſtop their ears, and make their hearts like an adamant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, leſt they ſhould hear the words of the law of the Lord of hosts,</hi> Zech. 7.11, 12. They have an Iron Sinew, a Brow of Braſs, and a Heart of Stone, that will not melt or relent, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 48.4. when God draws near to them with beams of Light, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Obedience, and offers of Grace. <hi>Job</hi> 21.14. <hi>They bid him depart,</hi> as if they had no need of God, owed no homage, obedience, or ſubjection to him; as if they could ſtand, tho' he did not ſupport them; as if they could chuſe their own way, and order their ſteps, tho' he did not direct them, and they could be happy tho' they did not enjoy him. <hi>They caſt God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his Word too, behind their backs,</hi> Ezek. 23.35. When Men bid God depart, is not this to pluck away his props and ſupports from their Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? To baniſh Heaven from themſelves, and to execute a great part of Hell on themſelves? And to provoke God to bid them depart from him, as curſed Creatures, into everlaſting Fire? <hi>Matt.</hi> 25.41. They that are alienated from the Life of God, and eſtranged from Communion with him, how can they hope to be for ever with him? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p n="9">9. This ſhould affect, and awe your Souls,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:35650:64"/>that you are ſtill under God's Eye, and do evil in his ſight, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.4. <hi>The ways of a man are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of the Lord, and he pondereth all his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> Prov. 5.21. <hi>There is no darkneſs, or ſhadow of death, where the workers of iniquity may hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> Job 34.22. This is peculiar to God, that Malefactors are always in the preſence, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the eye of him as their Judge; and he is a Witneſs againſt them for all the Crimes they commit. <hi>The Lord be witneſs againſt you,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.5.</p>
            <p n="10">10. How ſhould this cut your Hearts, <hi>that all your ſins are marked,</hi> Jer. 2.22. <hi>and all your crimes are written before him,</hi> Iſ. 65.6. The great King of the whole World, writes the Chronicles of all the Lives and Actions of his Subjects; all that Men ſpeak, think, or do, is Recorded in his Book, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. and Conſcience keeps a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-part of the Record. <hi>Their ſin is graven as with a pen of iron, and the point of a diamond, in the table of their heart,</hi> Jer. 17.1.</p>
            <p n="11">11. God can make Malefactors to appear, and preſent Delinquents before his Tribunal, they cannot fly, they cannot hide; <hi>As for thoſe mine Enemies, that would not have me to reign over them, bring them before me,</hi> Luke 19.27. This is proper and peculiar to God, that he can make all tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors to appear; and how dreadful will this be, that they muſt appear, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. where yet <hi>they cannot appear with any hope or confidence?</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 15. <hi>where ſhall the ungodly and the ſinner appear? They muſt stand before the Judgment-ſeat
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:35650:64"/>of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 14.10. yet <hi>the ungodly ſhall not stand in the Judgment,</hi> Pſal. 1.5. O what terror may this ſtrike into Men, that <hi>God will bring them into judgment,</hi> Eccleſ. 11.9. and God will alſo bring <hi>all their ſecret actions into judgment,</hi> Eccl. 12.14. God will bring all the hidden things of darkneſs to light.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Impenitent Sinners <hi>ſhall be puniſhed with an everlaſting deſtruction, which ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord, and the glory of his power,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. The ſame Face that ſhines a Heaven into the Souls of Saints, ſhall frown a Hell into the Conſciences of the Wicked; the ſame Arm that puniſhes, ſhall ſupport the puniſhed ſtill to endure more Torments: as God will burn againſt, and on Chaff, Briers, Thorns and Taras, ſo he will preſerve the Fuel, and uphold it to Eternity. <hi>Who knows the power of God's anger,</hi> Pſal. 90.11? how miſerable he can render a Creature, that he fills up as a Veſſel with his Wrath, that he treads on as a footſtool, and ſhoots at as a Mark? God asks <hi>Job, Haſt thou entred into the Springs of the Sea? or haſt thou walked in the ſearch of the deep?</hi> could he tell how deep the great Sea was? could he come to the bottom of it? <hi>Job</hi> 38.16. So it will be ſaid to us, Can you by the line and plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet of your Reaſon ſound and find out the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the deep Sea of the Wrath of God? <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> is deep, there is no coming up out of it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. ult. <hi>The Gulf that is fixed is wide,</hi> there is no paſſing over it, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26. And theſe things are near, our breath is in our Noſtrils, ready to go
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35650:65"/>out, and the Judge ſtands at the Door ready to come in. As the accuſations and threatnings of the Law ſhould be a Plough, ſtriking home and cutting deep into our Hearts, ſo the Mercy of God in Chriſt, and the Grace revealed in the Goſpel, ſhould exceedingly wound and break our Hearts. How amazing is this, that when we had made God to ſerve with our Sins, and wearied him with our Iniquities, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.24. that the Son of God ſhould take on him the form of a Servant, to ſuffer, to ſatisfie for, and purge away our Iniquities <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.76. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3? O, that when God, as a Creator, Preſerver, Benefactor, had been by our Luſts debaſed to be a meer Servant, and Satan exalted to be the Prince, yea, the <hi>God,</hi> of the World, <hi>John</hi> 12.3. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 4, 5. that the Son of God ſhould humble himſelf to be a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant</hi> to his own Law, as a Sacrifice to his Father's Juſtice, to make an end of the guilt of Sin! O that Chriſt ſhould be ſold to redeem us! that he ſhould be wounded to heal us! that he ſhould be arreſted, arraign'd and condemn'd to juſtifie us! ſhould not this make Hearts of ſtone to relent and break? O, that God ſhould complain, that he is <hi>broken with our whoriſh Hearts,</hi> Ezek. 6.9. yet Chriſt, to expiate and put away the guilt of theſe Whoredoms, ſhould complain, that <hi>Reproach had broken his heart,</hi> Pſ. 69.20. We had loaded God with our ſins and provocations, as a Cart is preſſed under the ſheaves, <hi>Amos</hi> 2.13. O how amazing is it, that God ſhould lay all our ſins on Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. and load him with our penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35650:65"/>and puniſhments! that our Debt ſhould be exacted of him, our Curſe executed on him! that he ſhould be as the <hi>Manna</hi> pounded in the Mortar! that as <hi>a cluſter of Grapes</hi> he ſhould be bruiſed in the Wine-preſs of the Wrath and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God! that as a Porter, or bearer of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, he ſhould have our Iniquities bound on him and then bear them quite away. The Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is uſed of Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4. <hi>He hath carried our ſorrows;</hi> and hence he that is a Porter, or bearer of burdens, is called, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.27. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a man of burden.</hi> This Name fitly doth agree to our Lord Jeſus, that he was <hi>a Man of burden:</hi> Never did any one bear ſo vaſt a load, ſo great a burden: We found out Inventions to inſlave our ſelves, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7. ult. and God found out a Ranſom, to redeem and ſet us at liberty, <hi>Job</hi> 33.24. We hated him without a cauſe, and he loved us freely, and without a cauſe; how ſhould this Grace melt our hard, and warm our cold Hearts with love to God? ſhall we continue in the torrid Zone of Enmity and Luſt, when Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are brought into and dwell in the torrid Zone of Love? It is now poſſible that our Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs may bloſſom as a Roſe, that our dry Ground may be water'd, improv'd, and inrich'd, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.1. &amp; 44.3, 4. Enemies may be reconcil'd, dead Souls quicken'd, and ſuch as have been Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan's Children and meer Strangers to God, may be adopted, and taken into his Family.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Q. Why muſt our fallow Ground be broken up?</hi> I anſwer, 1. That our carnal Confidence in our
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35650:66"/>ſelves may be mortified and rooted out; our Pride muſt be abated, our high Mountain of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Confidence muſt be level'd, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.4. How many do truſt in themſelves that they are <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, Luke</hi> 15.8. and this is directly contrary to believing in Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. that they might be juſtified: Thoſe that have ſome Planks, ſome pieces of the wreck of the Fall, to float and ſwim on, will not deſire and cry to be taken up into Chriſt, God's Ark of Salvation; they that build on their Morality, Form of Godlineſs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Performances, are too rich to beg an Alms and receive a <hi>gift of Righteouſneſs</hi> from <hi>Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 5.17. Thoſe that are ſhut up under Sin and Condemnation, will lay hold of and embrace the free Promiſe of <hi>Salvation</hi> and <hi>Life, Gal.</hi> 3.22. Thoſe that highly account of their own qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and attainments, do think they have va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable Gains, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. that they have that which will gain them the favour of God, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, a Right and Title to Eternal life: They judge themſelves to be whole, that their Souls were never ſick or diſeaſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.12. they think they have lived in ſubjection to God their Father, and in obedience to his Commands, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.29. that they have ſerved him when others did rebel againſt him, and that therefore they <hi>need no Repentance,</hi> Luke 15.7. How many do account themſelves as fruitful and flouriſhing Meadows, that <hi>naturally</hi> bear a Crop without plowing or ſowing. Thoſe that do value their own civil and unblamable life, and highly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35650:66"/>of their form of godlineſs, they think it very hard, yea, judge it very unreaſonable and injurious to them, that their green and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Turf ſhould be plowed up and turned in, as if it were of no worth and value; they think they have ſomething of their own to recommend them to God's Holineſs, and ſecure them from his Juſtice; their <hi>fallow Ground</hi> muſt be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore broken up, to root out this carnal Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and to convince them, that they are far from Righteouſneſs, and that nothing they have done will be approved by God's Touchſtone, or hold in his Balance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our <hi>fallow Ground</hi> muſt be broken up, that the Briers and Thorns that grow in us may be wounded, cut, and rooted up. The Word of God ſhould be a grubbing Plough, to tear up our Thorns; a circumciſing Knife, to cut off the fore-skin of our Hearts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. we muſt ſuffer in our Fleſh, even in our corrupt Nature, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. Satan's works in us muſt be deſtroy'd, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. our Navel muſt be cut, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.4. we muſt be ſeparated from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> we muſt be as Branches cut out of the <hi>wild Olive, Rom.</hi> 11.17, 24. To <hi>break up</hi> our <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> is thus expounded in the next Verſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Circumciſe your ſelves to the Lord, take away the foreskin of your heart;</hi> this is as Thorns that choak the Word, that draw away the ſtrength and vigor of the Heart, and ſo ſtarve the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Men muſt <hi>break up</hi> their <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> that they may be meet and fit Patients for Jeſus Chriſt.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35650:67"/>This <hi>Heavenly</hi> Phyſician hath no Practice, but on humbled and broken-hearted Sinners, theſe are they he applys his Remedies to, and works Cures on: He was appointed and deſign'd to bind up <hi>the broken in heart, Iſa.</hi> 61.1. none others do think they need Chriſt's Help, prize his Remedies, or value his Conſolations: Thoſe that are whole, that never ſaw the Plague of their Hearts, or groan'd under the weight of their Guilt, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of their Sins, do not think they need a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician. Chriſt hath few Patients and little Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the World, becauſe Men are not ſick of Sin, wounded or broken for it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Our <hi>fallow Ground</hi> muſt be plow'd and <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up,</hi> that our Soil may be fitted to receive the good Seed of the Goſpel: a broken Chriſt is both ſuited and welcome to a broken Heart. Chriſt crucified is the grain of Corn that ſows the whole Field of God, <hi>John</hi> 12.24. with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>We preach Chriſt crucified,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul: Chriſt is the lilly of the valleys,</hi> Cant. 2.1. His Seed grows and thrives only in poor Ground; the Poor have the Goſpel preached to them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.5. theſe taſte the ſweetneſs of it, are cheer'd by its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, are caſt into its mould; the Seed takes root in broken Ground, it proſpers, it thrives in humbled Souls: how do ſinking and drowning Sinners catch at and hold faſt the Cord of the Promiſe caſt out to them? Thoſe that are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued by their own Guilt, the Wrath of God, the Threatnings and Terrors of the Law, how much do they haſten their pace, and fly for refuge, to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35650:67"/>take hold of the Hope ſet before them? Thoſe that are ſcorched by the ſenſe they have of the Wrath of God, how highly do they prize, and how joyfully and delightfully do they ſit under Chriſt's ſhadow, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Men muſt break up their <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> that they may ſeek the Lord in good earneſt. We may obſerve how theſe two things are join'd together, <hi>Break up your fallow Ground, for it is time to ſeek the Lord, Hoſ.</hi> 10.12. Theſe two things ſeem to be intimated in the words, 1. That in <hi>breaking up</hi> our <hi>fallow Ground</hi> we do <hi>ſeek the Lord.</hi> 2. That none will <hi>ſeek the Lord</hi> ſincerely and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently, but thoſe that break up their <hi>fallow Ground;</hi> ſuch are quickly convinced, and ſoon made ſenſible how neceſſary it is to <hi>ſeek the Lord,</hi> that vile Weeds, that Vices natural to us may be rooted out, and that ſupernatural Graces and Truths may be grafted on and planted in them. The <hi>Pelagians</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us) aſſerted. That <hi>Vitia ingenerata extirpari prorſus incredibile eſt:</hi> they argued thus againſt Original Sin, That <hi>if Vices were naturally bred in us, and born with us, it was altogether an incredible thing that they ever would or could be rooted out.</hi> But God, the great Husbandman, can cleanſe the Soul of them, and mortifie Vice and Luſts that are natural to us, <hi>John</hi> 15.3. <hi>You are clean, through the word that I have ſpoken to you.</hi> Whoredom was a Vice ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to act the part of a <hi>Corinthian,</hi> was to be a Whoremaſter; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle to them ſaith,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35650:68"/>
               <hi>Some of you were Fornicators, Adulterers, but you are waſhed, you are ſanctified,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.10, 11. <hi>Auſtin</hi> himſelf was naturally much inclin'd to Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet the Grace of God ſo changed him, that he ever after became chaſt in a ſingle life. God can unmake Men, as to their ſinful frame, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being unmade <hi>to ſin, you may live to righteouſneſs.</hi> God can create Men in Chriſt Jeſus to good works, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. He can put his Law, his Fear, his Spirit into the Hearts of Men, that natural Vices ſhall be rooted out, and ſupernatural Graces ſhall be planted in the Soul. They that break up their <hi>fallow Ground</hi> will <hi>ſeek the Lord,</hi> and continue ſeeking of him, till he come and rain Righteouſneſs on them: this is a Rain of Seed-Righteouſneſs; it is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful that God can rain Seed, rain Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that will ſow the Soul, and make it fruitful: as when the Husbandman hath plowed and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Ground, he needs to <hi>ſeek the Lord</hi> to rain on it, that the Seed may root and ſpring up, ſo thoſe that plow and <hi>break up</hi> their <hi>fallow Ground</hi> have need to pray, that God would rain Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Righteouſneſs to ſow them. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. ult. God ſaith, <hi>I will ſow them to my ſelf in the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Men muſt <hi>break up</hi> their <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> that they may abound in the Work of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>be filled with the fruits of Kighteouſneſs,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. ult. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.11. A <hi>fallow Ground</hi> is in a great meaſure unprofitable; it bears Thorns and Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but a plowed and ſowed Ground yields a good crop of Corn: none do bear Fruit to God
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35650:68"/>but thoſe that are born again of the Word and Spirit, and made <hi>Trees of Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſa. 61.3. will be filled with the Fruits of Righteouſneſs, walk with, and live to God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24, 25. If our <hi>fallow Ground</hi> be not broken up, our form of Godlineſs will wither and decay, Thorns will famiſh and ſtarve the good Seed, that at laſt they will be twice dead, pluck'd up by the Roots. <hi>Jude</hi> 12. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that did not conquer and root out the Heathen Nations, are ſaid to dwell among the <hi>Canaanites, Judg.</hi> 4.33. theſe did cut the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhort, and much annoy them, and keep them down; ſo the natural crop of Thorns doth much annoy, and hinder any good Seed that is caſt in among them, obſtruct its growth, that it neither roots deep, nor ſprings up to any height.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Men muſt Plow up their <hi>fallow ground,</hi> that they may have a plentiful and joyful Harveſt at laſt. It is very deſirable to ſow to the Spirit, and to reap Everlaſting Life, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5. <hi>To have our fruit to holineſs, and the end everlaſting life,</hi> Rom. 6.22. to bear Fruit that will abound to our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17. Tho' we have not evened with God, and diſcharg'd our Debt, yet God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins a new Account, and writes himſelf Debtor to his People for their Fruits of Holineſs, and of Love; Saints that ſow in Tears, ſhall reap in Joy; they that go forth weeping, bearing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Seed, ſhall come again with Joy, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35650:69"/>bring their Sheaves with them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5, 6. Though Religion may ſeem not only a bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and unprofitable, but a hurtful thing in the Eye of the World; yet at laſt there ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear a vaſt difference between thoſe that fear God, and thoſe that fear him not, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. ult. when the Righteous ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father, and the Tares ſhall burn in a Furnace of unquenchable Fire; when Chriſt ſhall be glorified in the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints, and in the Deſtruction of the Wicked, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.22. Thoſe that pleaſe God do ſow in a fruitful Soil; they will in this life receive a hundred fold, notwithſtanding Perſecutions from the World, and at laſt will <hi>inherit eternal joy and life,</hi> Mark 10.30.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If we plow not up our <hi>fallow Ground,</hi> God may let looſe dreadful and cruel Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men on us. It is ſaid, <hi>Zion ſhall be plowed as a Field,</hi> Micah 3. ult. Enemies may plow on our Backs, and make their Furrows both deep and long, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.3. How have the Backs of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> been cruelty plowed in <hi>France</hi> for about Twelve Years laſt paſt? God threatens, in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 10.11. that <hi>Judah</hi> ſhould plow; they ſhould ſerve their Enemies in and under hard bondage. I have been credibly inform'd, that in <hi>Barbary</hi> ſome <hi>Chriſtian Slaves</hi> have been put into Harneſſes, and being lockt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35650:69"/>in, have been forced to plow the Ground. God ſeems to allude to ſuch a thing, that <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall ſuffer as hard and grievous things, as if he were put to Plow. To draw God's Plow is beneficial and honourable Work, but to draw mens Plow will be bitter and grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous: yea, if you neglect to <hi>break up your fallow Ground,</hi> God will plow your Souls, make deep and long Furrows in Conſcience to Eternity.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Thoſe that will not plow up their <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Ground,</hi> ſhall at laſt beg for an Alms of Mercy, and be rejected. The Sluggard will not plow, by reaſon of the cold; therefore ſhall he beg in Harveſt, and have nothing. Spiritual Sluggards have many Excuſes and Pretences to ſhift off this plowing Work, but when the Harveſt comes they will be in a very bad and woful ſtate. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of it as a great Evil for a Father to waſte his Eſtate by evil Courſes, <hi>and to beget a Son, and there is nothing in his hand,</hi> Eccl. 5.14. he is Heir only to Poverty and Beggery. But it is a great deal worſe for a Man to be born into Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and to have no Good in his Hand, in his Soul. Thoſe that toil about the World ſhall carry away nothing of their labour in their hand, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.15. but if you labour for God, <hi>your Works will follow you,</hi> Revel. 14.13. and the ſweet Fruit of them will be enjoy'd for
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:35650:70"/>ever. But this is not the only Evil, that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sluggards will have nothing of Good, but God will <hi>thunder againſt them, and rain fire and brimſtone on them for working of Iniquity,</hi> Pſal. 11.6. As when God was diſpleas'd with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he ſent <hi>Thunder</hi> and <hi>Rain</hi> in <hi>Wheat-harveſt,</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> 12.17, 18. So when Sluggards have vainly hoped to reap a Harveſt of Happineſs, God will thunder againſt them, pour down his Wrath, and execute Vengeance on them. How earneſtly and importunately will Sluggards beg for Mercy, but all in vain, they will cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, open to us,</hi> Matt. 7.21, 22, 23. but He will profeſs that which is very contrary to their Profeſſions and Hopes, <hi>Then will I profeſs unto them, I never knew you, depart from me ye that work Iniquity.</hi> In the 13th of <hi>Luke, v.</hi> 27. it is thus expreſſed, <hi>Depart from me all ye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Iniquity:</hi> which intimates, that Chriſt will be moſt juſt and impartial; he will no more regard, yea, he will rather much more abhor <hi>workers of Iniquity,</hi> than thoſe without the Church; both ſhall be diſown'd and rejected by Jeſus Chriſt. Theſe Sluggards will begin Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt for ſome ſpiritual Bread, for a Place in the Kingdom, but they ſhall be thruſt out, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy no Good to Eternity.</p>
            <p n="10">10. It is a dreadful Curſe denounced on the Ground of Mount <hi>Gilboa,</hi> by <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Let there be no fields of Offerings there:</hi>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:35650:70"/>that is, let thoſe Mountains never be ſow'd, or if ſow'd, let them be barren: <hi>Let there be no fields of Offerings there.</hi> The <hi>fine Flour</hi> was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd on the Altar to God, of this the <hi>Meat-offering</hi> did conſiſt, <hi>Levit.</hi> 2.1, 2. This was a great honour to the Creatures, for <hi>Meat-offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings</hi> to be made to God of the fine Flour, and Drink-offerings of Wine. In this ſenſe the Vine ſaith in <hi>Jotham</hi>'s Parable, that it did by its <hi>Wine chear the Heart of God,</hi> Judg. 9.13. Now if it be a Curſe on the Ground not to bear Wheat, which will yield fine Flour, fit to be offer'd to God, how much ſorer and more grievous Curſe is it for the Souls of Men to be barren, not to be plow'd and ſow'd, not to yield any Fruit that may be offer'd to God, and that he can take pleaſure and delight in? Will you make light of this dreadful Curſe? Will you pluck it, and continue it on your ſelves? Will you do nothing to pleaſe and glorifie God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. This may reprove many formal and titular Chriſtians, that do neglect this excellent Command, and do ſlight and omit this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Duty and Work of <hi>breaking up their fallow Ground:</hi> Inſtead of wounding and breaking their Hearts, they live in Pleaſure, are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and nouriſh their Hearts, as in a day of ſlaughter, that is, as in a great Feaſt-day, when there is a ſlaughter of the Creatures made to feaſt the Body, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.5. they pleaſe their
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:35650:71"/>Fleſh, they gratifie and indulge their ſenſual Affections, they cannot bear or endure ſuch hard and grievous Work as this, to draw God's Plow, and with its Shear to cut deep Furrows and ſorely wound their own Hearts; they think it very unreaſonable to baniſh carnal Joy out of their Souls, to cloud their Souls with Sorrows, to load their Spirits with a ſenſible feeling of the Evils that they have done, and with the fear of the Puniſhment they have deſerv'd: how few do take God's part, do ſide with him, do plead his Cauſe againſt themſelves and their Luſts? Who do charge their Sins home on themſelves, and ſet forth their heinous and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Aggravations before God? Do not Men deal gently and tenderly with themſelves? Do they not leſſen and extenuate, rather than heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, their Guilt in Filth, and careleſs of their Tranſgreſſions? If the Word doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps touch or wound them, doth not Self-love, (as that <hi>natural Balſam</hi> Chyrurgeons and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians ſay is in the Body) quickly heal it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Doth not Self flattery ſoon chear them again, and ſo cheat them? Their plowing is rather ſcratching the Earth, than ſtriking a deep Furrow; they know not the meaning, or they have no Experience of a broken Heart, of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite Spirit. This is indeed <hi>a great thing,</hi> for the Spirit of a Man to be bruiſed, and, as it were, ground to powder, under the weight of Sin committed, and the ſenſe of Puniſhment deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:35650:71"/>It is ſaid, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>The Revolters were profound to make ſlaughter;</hi> but, alas! where are the Men and Women that are profound in wounding their Souls for <hi>Sin,</hi> and in making a ſlaughter of their <hi>Luſts?</hi> How is it to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, that the Sword of God's Word doth not paſs through the Heart of the Old Man? that the Arrows of God do not cleave the Reins of Sinners, and pour out their very Gall? how few do outlaw their corrupt and vile Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and put them out of their protection, that they may be kill'd when or whereſoever they find, meet with them, or ſee them? But do not Men act quite contrary to this? When God ſhoots his <hi>Arrows,</hi> caſts his <hi>Darts</hi> at them, do they not take the Shield of Unbelief, and guard their baſe Luſts? Do they not quench the fiery Darts that God caſts at them? Is there not a great deal of Art and Labour uſed to enervate, to blunt, to diſpirit keen and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Truths, that they may not enter deep, that come too home and cloſe to their Hearts? They cannot endure that Conſcience ſhould be enlighten'd and awak'd, that its Tongue ſhould be looſed; this they think is intolerable, to raiſe a Storm within their own Breaſts, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb their Peace, to deſtroy their Hopes, to let in Terrors to arreſt and overwhelm their Souls: They think they ſhall never recover Peace and Comfort, or have their Wounds heal'd again, if God's Plough ſhould cut them
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35650:72"/>to the very Heart: Doth not a ſhallow Furrow produce a ſlight Religion, and a ſuperficial Chriſtianity in the World? Inſtead of putting convincing Truths, inſtead of keeping awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thoughts and Meditations on their Hearts, they rather keep them off <hi>at a diſtance,</hi> and ſhut them out of their Souls. O where ſhall we find an humbled Sinner crying out thus, <hi>I am the man that hath riſen up againſt God, I have broken his Yoke, and made his Laws void; I have burſt his Bonds, and caſt away his Cords from me; I, that am but a Worm, have dared to walk contrary to God, and have enter'd the Liſts with the Almighty; I, that am but a Potter's Veſſel, have challeng'd a Rod of Iron; I, that am but Chaff, Briars, and Thorns, have contended with devouring Fire, with eternal burnings; I have exalted my Folly againſt Infinite Wiſdom, and ſet up my perverſe, wicked, rebellious Will, in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the holy Law, the righteous Will of God: though God bears up the frame of Heaven and Earth by the Word of his Power, and doth not faint under this great weight, yet I have laid a heavier burden on him, and cauſed him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, that He is wearied by my Sins,</hi> Iſa. 43.24. <hi>and is preſſed under my Iniquities, as a Cart is preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed under the Sheaves,</hi> Amos 2.13. How few <hi>Ephraim;</hi> are there found thus bemoaning or impeaching themſelves? Men do indeed like to tread out the Corn, and eat the Fruits of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but will not follow the Plough, to convince
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35650:72"/>and humble themſelves for Iniquity. How ſtrange is it, that Perſons will nouriſh in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hopes of a comfortable and plentiful Harveſt hereafter, yet will not now plow and <hi>break up their fallow Ground?</hi> Is it not an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Preſumption, to look for a Harveſt, when there hath been no Ground plow'd, or Seed ſown?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. Examine your ſelves, Is your <hi>fallow Ground</hi> broken up? have you inclin'd your Hearts and ſet your Hands to God's Plough? Though the Earth doth not feel the Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhear, doth not know when the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth till the Land, yet a Soul cannot be both a Plow-man and a plowed Ground, but it muſt needs be ſenſible of what is done on, and wrought within it ſelf. Have you ever been <hi>pricked in Heart?</hi> Acts 2.37. Have God's Words been as Goads to prick you, as Nails to pierce you? Have the Truths of God been as a ſharp Plow-ſhear, cutting and wounding your Souls?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Did you ever come to your ſelves, and ſo make a right judgment concerning your ſelves and your own Eſtate, with reſpect to God and Eternity, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.17. that you are poor, empty, naked Creatures, that you are but a dry Ground and barren Wilderneſs, like the Vineyard of the ſloathful Man, all
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35650:73"/>overgrown with <hi>Thorns</hi> and <hi>Nettles,</hi> Prov. 24.30, 31? It would be bad for a Man to rent a great Farm, and yet not to have one Acre of Corn ſow'd on it; but is it not worſe for us, that hold our Souls and Bodies of God our great Landlord, to whom we owe a great Rent of univerſal Obedience to his Laws, and yet not to have one Faculty of our Souls ſow'd with precious Seed? For our Minds and Wills not to be Tables with the Law of God; for our Veſſels to be empty, and deſtitute of ſpiritual Oyl; for our Meal not to be leavened by the Goſpel, and the Houſes of our Souls to be empty, and not inhabited by the Spirit of God? Have we diſcern'd our ſelves to be empty Vines, barren Fig trees, unprofitable Servants? Our <hi>fallow Ground</hi> will never be broken up, till we are convinc'd how much we need to be plow'd and ſow'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Were our Souls ever rightly, duly, deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected with our woful and wretched State? Are Hearts broken, our Spirits wounded, our <hi>Souls as a bruiſed Reed?</hi> Iſaiah 42.3. Hath the ſenſe of our guilt, and God's wrath, ſo fallen and ſeized on our ſpirits, as to grind them as it were to Powder? <hi>A prick in the heart is both painful and mortal,</hi> Acts 2.37. this wounds the Old Man to death. <hi>How ſhall we, that are dead to ſin, live any longer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:35650:73"/>Rom 6.2. If an Earthen Veſſel be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces, it can no more hold any Water, or ſerve for any uſe, as when it was whole. If our Old Man be Crucified, if the Body of Sin be Deſtroy'd, we cannot ſerve ſin as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. If a Ground be Plow'd deep, and the Roots of Weeds, that grew in it, be cut, they cannot flouriſh in that Ground as before.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Have you received the ſeed of the Word, the Doctrine of the Goſpel gladly?</hi> Acts 2.41. Have the Tidings of Redemption, the News of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, been welcome to you? And as a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Generous Cordial, revived your faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and languiſhing Spirits? And as a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Balſam, healed your bruiſed, broken Hearts? Have you, as drowning Men, laid hold on the Promiſe of Salvation? As famiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, have you catched at the Bread of Life? Have you as weary, and heavy Laden Sinners, leaned on Chriſt? <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.5. and taken hold of the Hope ſet before you? Have you, as a dry and thirſty Ground, drank in the ſpiritual Rain, and Dew from Heaven? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18. And doth the ſeed, ſo received, ſanctify you? Doth the Word work effectually in your Souls? <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.7. Doth it Leaven you, <hi>John</hi> 17.19. with Holineſs, Spirituality, and Heavenly-mindedneſs? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:35650:74"/> 4. <hi>Doth the ſeed of the Word bring forth fruit in your hearts and lives?</hi> Col. 1.5, 6. <hi>Do you ſhine in the world as lights, and hold forth the word of life?</hi> Phil. 2.15, 16. Is the ſweet odour of your Ointments, and Garments ſmelt? <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.10, 11.</p>
            <p>USE 3. <hi>I would Exhort you to this great Duty, O break your Fallow Ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Adam</hi> fell, and was turned out of the Earthly Paradiſe, it was neceſſary for him to become a Husband-man, and a Plow-man. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.23. <hi>God ſent him out of the Garden of</hi> Eden <hi>to Till the ground, from whence he was taken.</hi> Bread could not be had without Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Sowing; our Nature was corrupted and depraved; all Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſo rooted out, that if we break not up <hi>our Fallow Ground,</hi> no ſeed can be ſowed, or Fruit brought forth to God. To be ſpiritual Plow-men, is an Employment neceſſary for all Rich and Poor; Princes and Peaſants, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-men, and thoſe of low Degree, muſt all follow the Plow, muſt all attend to break up their <hi>Fallow Ground;</hi> this is a Work to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by none, Men and Women muſt all proſecute and purſue it. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We are wholly uſeleſs, and altogether unprofitable, if we <hi>continue a Fallow Ground.</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:35650:74"/>It is worſe with us, than with a Field that <hi>lies Fallow,</hi> that may bear ſome Herbage. I have been credibly informed of ſome Land, that have been ſowed once a Year, and mow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the next; ſo ſerviceable is the Earth to Man, but if Men <hi>lie Fallow, they do no good,</hi> Rom. 3.12. They bring forth no Fruit to God; all their Religious, and Common Actions, are grievous and diſpleaſing to God. <hi>The prayer of him that turneth away his ear from hearing the Law, is an abomination to God,</hi> Prov. 28.9. <hi>Yea, the plowing of the wicked is ſin,</hi> Prov. 21.4. <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is an abomination,</hi> Prov. 15.8. <hi>And the way of the wicked,</hi> that is, his common Actions, <hi>are ſin,</hi> Prov. 15.9. <hi>That which they offer is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, and ſo is every work of their hands,</hi> Hag. 2.14. Thus they are altogether <hi>unprofitable,</hi> Rom. 3.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>If you lie Fallow, you will grow worſe and worſe.</hi> The Old Man grows more corrupt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22. As a dead Carkaſs doth putrify more and more, and become more noiſome, unſavory, and ſtinking, ſo it is with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Death in us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. The more a ground is neglected, the longer it lies <hi>Fallow,</hi> the more it is over-run with Briars and Thorns; The deeper the Weeds root in it, the more they over-run, over ſpread, and eat out the heart of it: So here, the Mind grows
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35650:75"/>more vain, more blind; the Heart is more hard, the Affections more ſenſual and carnal. It is ſaid of ſome, <hi>That they have left off to take heed to the Lord,</hi> Hoſ. 4.10. <hi>And that they leave off Righteouſneſs in the Earth,</hi> Amos 5.7. <hi>Evil men, and ſeducers, wax worſe and worſe,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.13.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If you Plow not for God, you Plow for Satan. It is a woful thing to drive Satan's Plow. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks of ſome, <hi>That draw ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with cords of vanity, and ſin as it were with a cart-rope,</hi> Iſaiah 5.18. It is a plain Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to drawing in a Cart, or drawing of a Plow. O how ſad is it to be Satan's ſlaves, to draw his Plow? All the corrupt Reaſonings of Men, that God doth not ſee, obſerve, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their ſins; That he will never revenge them; that God's threatnings are but vain words, as a deſpicable eccho, <hi>and the ſounding again of the mountains,</hi> Ezek. 7.7. Theſe are the Cords of Vanity by which Men draw ſin to themſelves; but though they are but Cords of Vanity, yet they draw as ſtrong, as if they were a thick Cart-rope. What bad Work do Satan's Plow-men, inſtead of breaking up their <hi>Fallow ground? They break God's yoke, burſt his bonds,</hi> Jer. 5.5. <hi>They brake the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant,</hi> Iſaiah 24.5. <hi>Break God's Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes,</hi> Pſal. 89 31. Yea, God himſelf complains, <hi>That he is broken by their whoriſh heart,</hi> Ezek.
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:35650:75"/>6.9. Thus ill are Men imploy'd, <hi>that break not up their Fallow ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>It is honorable to yield Fruit to God.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>The profit of the earth is for all; the King himſelf is ſerved by the Field,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.9. It is moſt true, That the King of Glory is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by a Field broken up, and ſowed. How honorable is it, <hi>when our Prayer is the delight of God?</hi> Prov. 15.8. <hi>And God delighteth in our way?</hi> Pſal. 37.23. <hi>When our Offerings are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the Lord?</hi> Mal. 3.4. <hi>When we can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite Chriſt to come into his Garden, and eat of his pleaſant fruits,</hi> Cant. 4. laſt. <hi>When we treat him with the ſpiced Wine of the juice of our Pomegranate,</hi> Cant. 8.2. <hi>When our voice is ſweet in Chriſt's ears, and our countenance is comely in Chriſt's eyes,</hi> Cant. 2.14. <hi>It is for the glory of the Church, that Chriſt goes down to feed in the Gardens,</hi> Cant. 6.2.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It will be our advantage to break up our <hi>Fallow ground.</hi> God bids our firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>to repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it,</hi> Gen. 1.28. That it is by Tillage they were to maſter the Earth, and compel it to ſerve them, and bear Fruit to them; ſo by breaking up our <hi>Fallow ground,</hi> we ſubdue it to yield Fruit to God, and we more appropriate it, and render it uſeful to our ſelves. One that writes concerning Government and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35650:76"/>(in oppoſition to Sir <hi>Robert Filmer</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives that this was the way at firſt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, and appropriate parcels of the Earth to particular Perſons: That as much as a Man had need of, and could Plow and Sow, that became his own. And he ſaith it is ſo in <hi>Spain</hi> at this day, That any Man may Plow Land, Sow, and Reap it for his own uſe, without oppoſition, or contradiction from any. It is by plowing, and breaking up of our <hi>Fallow ground,</hi> that we become more Maſters of our ſelves, do more poſſeſs our own Souls, as Proprietors uſe them, and as Kings command, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5, 6. in them. So much of our Souls as we Till, as we break up, is devoted to God, and is a Portion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to our ſelves. As it is the Riches of a Husband-man, to have many Acres ſowed with good Corn, with uſeful Grain; ſo it will be both our Honour, and Advantage, to have many Years of our Lives ſowed with the Fruits of Holineſs, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If every Day, Month, and Year, be ſowed with Fruit, that will abound to our account, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.17. how Rich, how Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are we?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider how infamous, and miſerable we ſhall be at laſt, if we <hi>break not up our Fallow ground.</hi> We ſhall <hi>neither ſow to our ſelves in righteouſneſs, nor reap in mercy,</hi> Hoſea
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:35650:76"/>10.12. We ſhall loſe our Seed time of Grace, and our Harveſt of Glory. We ſhall only <hi>reap corruption and deſtruction, Gal.</hi> 6.8. and be reaped as Tares, to be <hi>caſt into a Furnace of unquenchable Fire,</hi> Matt. 3.12. Matt. 13.42. <hi>If we continue dead in ſins,</hi> Epheſ. 2.1. and do no good, we ſhall at laſt be Carkaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes deſolate of all life and comfort, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy no good to Eternity, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. laſt. Yea, Chriſt will fall on you as a weighty ſtone, and <hi>grind you to pouder,</hi> Matt. 21.44.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When we <hi>break up our Fallow ground,</hi> we begin to do ſomething in Religion. All is nothing that we do, yea, we are nothing as to pleaſing of God, till we break up our <hi>Fallow ground.</hi> The Seeds man will not go forth to ſow, till the Plow-man goeth forth, and breaketh up the Ground. As a Man cannot Graft, till the Stock be cut to let in the Graft, ſo a Husband-man cannot Sow till the Ground be Plowed, and fitted to receive the Seed. Corn will not thrive, that is ſown on whole Land; the Graſs and Weeds will kill and choke it. So Goſpel-Truths will not root deep, thrive, or proſper kindly, if our Hearts are not broken. <hi>Till we lie down in our ſhame,</hi> Jer. 3. laſt. We cannot <hi>ſtand in grace,</hi> Rom. 5.2. Till we are convinced that we are enemies, we ſhall not take hold of the word of Reconciliation. Till we find, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35650:77"/>feel our ſelves ſhut up, under Sin and the Curſe, we ſhall not liſten to Chriſt as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, calling us out of Priſon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.9. into the Kingdom of God. And a vain ſhew of Religion, will yield no more than a vain ſhew of Happineſs; if we bring forth no Fruit for Chriſt to eat, there will be no Feaſt for us to enjoy.</p>
            <p>That you may <hi>break up your Fallow ground,</hi> obſerve theſe following Directions:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be convinced of this, and be humbled for this, <hi>That you have ſo long lain as a Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ground.</hi> How evil is it, that Men have continued, perhaps twenty, thirty, forty, fifty Years, or more, a <hi>fallow Ground?</hi> If a <hi>fallow</hi> did not ſerve a <hi>Husbandman</hi> any other way, but by being plow'd, ſow'd, and bearing Corn, would it not be a great ſhame and loſs to him, to ſee a <hi>Fallow</hi> to lye thirty, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or fifty Years, and never to plow it all this while? And ſhould it not grieve and afflict your <hi>Souls,</hi> that you have for many Years lain <hi>fallow,</hi> and have brought forth no <hi>Fruits of Righteouſneſs to God? Jeremiah</hi> ſaith of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to God, <hi>They have done nothing of all that thou commandedſt them to do,</hi> Jer. 32.23. Sinners are wholly at Satan's beck, diſpoſe, command; he hath been ſowing, grafting, and nurſing up his Tares in them. O let
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:35650:77"/>this humble you, That the Devil hath been watering, improving, ſtrengthning your vile Luſts and Affections. O that God ſhould ſpare you ſo long, ſupport you by his arms of Power, and ſupply you out of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his Goodneſs, when you were not only without him, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 12. but alſo againſt him in the World! It is a great Evil to be without God, as if there were no ſuch glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Being, or you had no need of him; but it is worſe to be againſt God, to walk contrary to him, to fight againſt his Laws, and Kingdom, as if he did bereave you of your Liberty and Pleaſure, and enact Laws contrary to your Freedom, Comfort, and Happineſs. How have your Luſts conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med your Time, and eat up thoſe Years that ſhould have been Fruitful to God? O be ſenſible that you have defrauded God, by not bearing good Fruits; and have bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened him by the abundance of your evil Fruit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When you begin to break up your <hi>Fallow Ground,</hi> O call for, and ſeek after the Aſſiſtance of the ſpirit of God, to direct the Plow, to put his Hand on it, that it may cut deep. You need that God ſhould ſpeak with a ſtrong Hand, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 8.11. That the Hand of the Lord ſhould be with them that preach, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.20, 21. That when
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:35650:78"/>Miniſters do ſtrike the Rock of your hearts, that the Lord ſhould ſtand on the Rock, (as he Promiſed <hi>Moſes</hi>) and cauſe it to cleave, and to give out Waters of Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Tears, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6.</p>
            <p>In vain do Miniſters Thunder, and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in the Conſcience, if the ſpirit of God doth not ſet home Convictions, and ſeal up Inſtructions on the Soul. The Holy Ghoſt muſt Arreſt, ſeize upon, and ſhut up the Soul in Priſon, that elſe will go at Liberty, and be under no Reſtraint, either from the Command, or Threatnings of God. If Guilt, and Wrath, do not lie hard, and heavy, on the Soul, Men will not regard Reconciliation, Redemption, and Salvation. Thoſe that make light, yea, a <hi>mock at ſin,</hi> Prov. 14.9. will make light of Chriſt's Feaſt, and Salvation, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.5.</p>
            <p>We need the ſpirit of Chriſt to caſt Chains of Light, and Conviction, about us, and to ſhut us up under the bitter ſenſe of our Tranſgreſſions, and to make us ſuch cloſe Priſoners, as to ſhut out all the Worlds Comforts from us, that they may be able to adminiſter no ſupport, relief, or refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to us, that we may wholly have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Chriſt, and liſten to him for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. It is very contrary to Fleſh and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:35650:78"/>Blood, for Men to acknowledge themſelves worthy of the Curſe, and to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. laſt. But if it be not thus, how can we run to Chriſt, that all the Promiſes may be <hi>Amen</hi> to us through him? We cannot ſubdue our Souls to Spiritual Tillage, if the Holy Ghoſt doth not ſubdue our Iniquities, <hi>Micah</hi> 7.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt take hold of God's gracious and free Promiſes, to incourage us to ſet on this Tillage, and <hi>breaking up of our Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ground.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adam</hi> was ſent out of the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to Till the Ground; but this might much diſhearten him, That the Ground was Curſed for his ſake: And that God did threaten him, That it ſhould bring forth Thorns and Thiſtles to him: That theſe ſhould ſpring up in his Plowed Land, and grow among his Corn. It is grievous to plow and ſow under a Curſe; to break the Ground, and ſow Wheat, and yet to Reap Thorns, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.2, 13. <hi>They ſowed wheat, but reaped thorns, and ſo were aſhamed of their Revenues.</hi> A Harveſt of Thorns was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſad, and ſhameful Crop; but do not Men diſappoint God? He ſoweth good Seed, yet the Souls of Sinners <hi>do bring forth Briars and Thorns,</hi> Heb. 6.8. Juſtly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:35650:79"/>may the Earth diſappoint Man, when Man fruſtrates God. <hi>I looked for Grapes</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>but his Vineyard brought forth wild grapes,</hi> Iſa. 5.4. But this is a great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our Spiritual Husbandry, That there are ſo many great and precious Promiſes, that God's own Power and Grace will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh and fulfil. It is ſaid, <hi>The Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall bloſſom as a roſe.</hi> Iſa. 35.1. <hi>That floods of water ſhall be poured out on the dry ground, to enrich and make it fruitful,</hi> Iſa. 44.3. That the ſpirit ſhall be poured out on the Off-ſpring of the Church, therefore they <hi>ſhould ſpring up as the willows by the water-courſes: One ſhould ſay I am the Lords, another ſhould ſubſcribe, and as by writing bind himſelf to the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 44.4, 5. <hi>That the deaf ſhould hear the word of the book,</hi> Iſa. 29.18. <hi>And the dead ſhould hear the voice of the Son of God, and live,</hi> John 5.25.</p>
            <p>There are Promiſes made to Chriſt that he ſhall ſee his Seed; <hi>behold the travel of his ſoul and be ſatisfied, and that by his knowledge he ſhall juſtify many,</hi> Iſa. 53.11. <hi>That he ſhould call Nations, that knew not him, and they ſhould run to him,</hi> Iſa. 55.5. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles that God ſhould ſend to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhould ſucceed and prevail, and bring in the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (that are called their Brethren) as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Sacrifices, as holy Offerings to God's
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:35650:79"/>ſpiritual Temple, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.18, 19, 20. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Labours of God's Meſſengers can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in vain: As Miniſters are Plowers, and Seeds-men, ſo they ſhall be Harveſt-men, <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. laſt. The Seed they ſow ſhould ſpring up to a Harveſt, Hearers ſhould be Converted, gathered into the Barn of the Church, <hi>there be threſhed and winnowed for the Garner of Heaven,</hi> Matt. 3.12. What ſweet and incouraging words are theſe, <hi>I will put Laws into their inward parts, and write them in their hearts,</hi> Jer. 31.33. Miniſters are but as Pens, but the ſpirit doth handle theſe Pens to write an Epiſtle with them, whereby the Soul is dedicated to God and Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <p>How reviving are theſe Words, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.26, 27. <hi>A new Heart will I give to you, a new Spirit will I put within you: I will take away the Heart of Stone, and give a Heart of Fleſh. My Spirit alſo will I put within you, and cauſe you to walk in my Statutes, and keep my Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As Chriſt doth ſpeak in his Miniſters, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. ſo he works by them, and in them, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.20. how greatly would Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters elſe be deterred from this Tillage? <hi>Shall Horſes run on the Rock? will one plow there with Oxen?</hi> Amos 6.12. <hi>Some Seed</hi> is
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:35650:80"/>ſaid to fall <hi>on a Rock,</hi> Luke 8.6. To plow and ſow on a Rock is very uncomfortable; yet this Promiſe of God, <hi>I will take away the Heart of Stone,</hi> may bear up Miniſters againſt theſe Difficulties.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You muſt perſiſt and go on in this Work of breaking up your <hi>fallow Ground.</hi> As there are Fallows in the viſible Church, many there do need Converſion; ſo in the beſt of the Saints there is a carnal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate part, that well may be called a <hi>fallow Ground;</hi> this Ground ſhould ſtill be plowed up. More Ground in the Soul ſhould be ſubdued, converted to Tillage, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nured; there is ſtill a barren part, there is ſtill a Soil that nouriſhes Weeds, and is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run with Thorns, this is to be broken up: We are ſow'd but in part, bear Fruit but in part; <hi>With our fleſh we ſerve the Law of Sin,</hi> Rom. 17. ult. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> complain'd, That <hi>though their Captivity was turned,</hi> yet they were <hi>Servants in their own Land;</hi> and it yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded much encreaſe to the Kings that GOD had ſet over them: <hi>becauſe of their Sins,</hi> Neh. 9.36, 37. the Kings of <hi>Perſia</hi> were ſtill their Lords, and out of their Labours they paid Tribute, either in Money or Fruits, to them. But how much more is this to be bewail'd and lamented, that Sin and Satan have yet ſome Ground in us that beareth Fruit unto
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:35650:80"/>them? Should we not therefore more break up our <hi>fallow Ground?</hi> Should not the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the Coaſts of the New Creature be more enlarged in us?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſhua</hi> divided to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> even the Nations not yet conquer'd, and did yet remain in <hi>Canaan,</hi> and encouraged the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to fight againſt them, with this Promiſe, <hi>The Lord your God ſhall expel them from before you,</hi> Joſhua 23.4, 5. So all that is poſſeſſed by the Fleſh in us is divided to us, is to be the Portion and Lot of the New Creature. We ſhould ſtill therefore more crucifie and ſubdue the Fleſh, with its Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Luſts; the New Creature ſhould more caſt forth its Roots, and ſpread its Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; we ſhould gain more Ground from the Sea of Corruption, and turn more of our Souls to Tillage.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We ſhould preſently ſet on this Work, and fall to <hi>break up our fallow Ground.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> ſaid, <hi>The time was not yet come, the time that the Lord's Houſe ſhould be built,</hi> Hag. 1.2. So ſloathful Souls are ready to ſay, The <hi>time is not yet come</hi> to fall to plow, and <hi>break up their fallow Ground;</hi> they are yet but in their Youth, in the Morning of their days, two or three hours of their day will ſuffice to ſow Seed enough, and to provide for an
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35650:81"/>Eternal Harveſt: but this Tillage may well take up our whole Day of Life. It is to pleaſe an Infinite God, it is to enjoy an Eternal Harveſt, that we plow; God cannot ſow us to himſelf, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2. ult, and we cannot ſow to our ſelves in Righteouſneſs, and reap in Mercy: We cannot bring our Sheaves with joy, and <hi>eat the fruits of our doings</hi> with comfort for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.10. if we do not <hi>break up our fallow Ground.</hi> We ſhould make haſte, and not delay to obey this Command of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59, 60. Do not mind and purſue the World, as if that were your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Buſineſs and chiefeſt Happineſs: conſider, to <hi>mind earthly things</hi> is a great ſin, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. to <hi>have our Portion in this life</hi> is a ſore Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14. to <hi>have their Backs</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually <hi>bowed down,</hi> to look after and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue carnal things, is a dreadful Curſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.10. be perſwaded, be convinc'd that it is high time to <hi>break up your fallow Ground,</hi> and <hi>to ſeek the Lord:</hi> O deſire to be God's Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. O, cry to him to enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten your dark Minds, to break your hard Hearts, to ſpiritualize your carnal Affections: Seek God diligently, ſeek him with your whole Heart, ſeek him continually, that he would write his Law in you, ſtamp his Image on you, and graft his Word in you, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. and thereby graft you into Chriſt, and <hi>plant you in the likeneſs of his Death and Reſurrection,</hi>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:35650:81"/>Rom. 6.5. to <hi>root and ground you in the Faith,</hi> Col. 2.7. Do not delay, do not defer this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Work of Spiritual Tillage, leſt hereby you fall into the Snare of the Devil, he that now tells you it is yet too ſoon to ſet on this Work, to <hi>break up your fallow Ground;</hi> After your long idleneſs and negligence, the Devil may change his Temptation, and ſuggeſt to you, that the time <hi>to break up your fallow ground</hi> is now paſt; that it is too late to ſet on this Work, when your Hearts are harden'd by the deceitfulneſs of Sin, your Day of Grace is paſt, God's Treaſury is lock'd, his Fountain of Life is ſealed, his Bowels of Mercy ſhut: Therefore you muſt pine away in Horrour and Deſpair, and periſh for ever.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
